<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "document-v10.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Apache Cocoon User Guide</title>
    <subtitle>Web publishing track</subtitle>
    <authors>
      <person name="Bertrand Delacr&#233;taz" email="bdelacretaz@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
      <s1 title="What's in this track?">
          <p>
              This track points to Cocoon documentation and external references which will
              help you to use Cocoon for <em>web publishing</em>.
          </p>
          <p>
              By <em>web publishing</em>, we mean generating various formats (HTML, PDF, RTF, etc.) out
              of XML documents, as opposed to <em>web applications</em> which include transactions,
              database storage, etc.
          </p>
       </s1>
       <s1 title="Prerequisites">
           <p>
               If you have not installed Cocoon yet, have a look at
               the <link href="first-steps-track.html">First steps track</link>.
           </p>
        </s1>
       <s1 title="Web Publishing Track">
           <s2 title="HTML/PDF How-To">
               <p>
                   The <link href="../howto/howto-html-pdf-publishing.html">
                   HTML/PDF How-To
                   </link> shows some simple examples of HTML and PDF publishing, it is a good
                   start to find out how this is done with Cocoon.
               </p>
           </s2>
           <s2 title="XSLT">
               <p>
                   Although there are many options for web publishing with Cocoon, XSLT
                   transforms are probably the most common way of transforming XML documents into the target
                   XML vocabularies required to generate the various formats.
                   The above How-To document points to some reference material about XSLT, which
                   you might want to study if you decide to use this option.
               </p>
           </s2>
           <s2 title="Generators">
               <p>
                   If you need to convert different data sources to XML, you will have to study
                   the available Cocoon
                   <link href="../userdocs/generators/generators.html">Generators</link>,
                   to see what options are available. We hope to have a <em>database queries</em> track
                   soon, to give more detail about the available options to access databases.
               </p>
           </s2>
           <s2 title="Serializers">
               <p>
                   At the other end of the pipeline, you will need a Serializer
                   to generate the target formats. Have a look a the
                   <link href="../userdocs/serializers/serializers.html">available Serializers</link>
                   and the corresponding samples to find out which ones you need to to generate your target
                   output formats.
               </p>
           </s2>
           <s2 title="Samples">
               <p>
                   While looking for Generators and Serializers, do not forget to look at the samples.
                   Searching the sitemap files for the names of components will tell you which samples
                   use which components.
               </p>
           </s2>
        </s1>
      <s1 title="Comments">
        <p>
            Care to comment on this Track?
            Help keep this document relevant by passing along any constructive feedback to the
            <link href="mailto:docs@cocoon.apache.org?subject=web-publishing-track:">cocoon-docs</link>
            mailing list.
        </p>
      </s1>
  </body>
</document>
