<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<document xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Cocoon Main Site - Communication tools that we use</title>
    <author email="cocoon-docs@apache.org">Apache Cocoon Documentation Team</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <div id="contentBody">
      <div id="bodyText">
        <h1 class="docTitle">Communication tools that we use</h1>
        <h1>Mailing lists</h1>
        <p>See below for descriptions of the Cocon mailing lists. A list of all
          available lists as well as links is available a the
          <a href="mail-lists.html">overview</a> page.
        </p>
        <p>When posting, please observe common-sense netiquette when posting.  In
          particular:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>When replying, please
            <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Top-posting#Inline_replying">edit the original message</a>
            and include only enough to establish context, not the entire message.
          </li>
          <li>Don't crosspost to the user and developer lists.  The developers also read
            the users list.
          </li>
          <li>Only reply to a message if you are really posting a reply on that thread;
            don't use your mailer's "Reply" function as a shortcut to get the list address
            into the "To:" field.  Instead, use your mailer's "new message" function to
            start a fresh thread.  When people abuse "Reply" and just change the "Subject:"
            line to a new topic, it makes it harder for threaded mailreaders to display the
            subjects accurately.  This can make it less likely that your message will be
            seen and replied to.
          </li>
        </ul>Regarding content:
        <ul>
          <li>Please ask your questions on the list.  If someone helps you out, don't
            email them off-list to ask your next question.  You will get the best answers if
            you stay on-list, and that way the question and answers can also benefit the
            current and future community.
          </li>
          <li>When asking for help, don't forget to include:</li>
          <ul>
            <li>The version of Cocoon you are using (the most important thing to not forget!
              :-)
            </li>
            <li>The servlet container (e.g. Jetty, Tomcat etc.) you are using.</li>
            <li>Platform details: JDK version and host OS</li>
            <li>Any relevant sitemap configuration, XSLT, Java or Javascript source code you
              are working with
            </li>
            <li>If you're getting an exception thrown, include the stack trace</li>
          </ul>

          <li>Don't just say that something "doesn't work"; explain (a) exactly what you
            did; (b) what you expected to happen; and (c) what happened instead of what you
            expected.  That type of explanation gives people a lot more information to work
            with.
          </li>
          <li>If you can show that you at least made some effort to figure something out,
            you will in turn get a more helpful response.  In particular, if you have in
            mind some idea that might help and it is an easy thing to try, don't post to the
            list to ask "Can I....".  Just try it for yourself and see! :-)
          </li>
          <li>A very common response to user questions is "What are you trying to
            accomplish"?  Try to supply that information when you first ask the question,
            and you will get a definitive answer that much sooner.  Cocoon is a rich
            framework that gives you a lot of tools, so that it's not always obvious to new
            users which tool set is the best to use for a particular problem.  New users
            sometimes get wrapped around the axle on some detail of the solution they are
            trying to make for a given scenario, and then end up posting to the list to ask
            how to do some exotic or bizarre thing.  If you can take a step back and
            describe the scenario itself, the more experienced users may be able to suggest
            one or more simpler solutions.
          </li>
          <li>If you ask for help with something, and then you later figure it out for
            yourself, please follow up on the list and describe what you did to fix the
            problem.  We like to prepend "SOLVED: " to the Subject: line when doing this.
          </li>
          <li>If you feel you must say "Please reply to me off-list, since I'm not
            subscribed", you can certainly do that; you just may or may not get a helpful
            reply!  You'll almost certainly get better results if you let people repond
            on-list.  See the Gmane links below to learn how easy it is to read the Cocoon
            lists without subscribing your own email address.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <section name="User list" style="background:none;padding:0;"/>This is the general community help list and for 
        Cocoon. Use it to learn Cocoon stuff, and share your own knowledge with somebody else!
        Please remember that this list is not really the place to ask questions
        about XSLT, HTML, CSS, Java programming, etc.
        <br/>
        Of course, new Cocoon releases are announced on this list.
        <h3>Archive</h3>
        All available archives are reported on the 
        <a href="mail-lists.html">overview</a> page.
        <br/>
        Note that the mail-archive site changed in July 2003.
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/users@cocoon.apache.org/">http://www.mail-archive.com/users@cocoon.apache.org/
            </a>(since July 2003)
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/cocoon-users%40xml.apache.org/">http://www.mail-archive.com/cocoon-users%40xml.apache.orgtwo</a>
            (before July 2003)
          </li>
        </ul>
        <section name="Developer list" style="background:none;padding:0;"/>This list is for anyone interested in 
        <a href="1273_1_1.html">working on Cocoon itself</a> (application developers making applications
        <em>with</em>Cocoon are Cocoon 
        <em>users</em>). Anyone can read or post to this list; you don't have to
        be a Cocoon committer.  Read this list if you want to learn more about the inner
        workings of Cocoon, or for detailed discussions about bugs or future enhancement
        requests. Please don't post routine user questions to the dev list, though.
        <br/>
        The topic of this list is 
        <em>Cocoon development</em>. If you post a question in the user list, and the 
        discussion gets so geeky that it has to move to the dev list... don't forget to come back to the user
        list with a "SOLVED:" post, once you've gotten everything ironed out! :-)
        <br/>
        The dev list gets automatic update notifications from the 
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/COCOON">JIRA</a> issue tracking system and from the
        <a href="https://builds.apache.org/view/A-F/view/Cocoon/">Jenkins</a> build system.
        <h3>Archive</h3>
        All available archives are reported on the 
        <a href="mail-lists.html">overview</a> page.
        <br/>
        Note that the mail-archive site changed in July 2003.
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/dev@cocoon.apache.org/">http://www.mail-archive.com/dev@cocoon.apache.org/</a>
            (since July 2003)
          </li>
          <li>
            <a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/cocoon-dev%40xml.apache.org/">http://www.mail-archive.com/cocoon-dev%40xml.apache.orgtwo</a>
            (before July 2003)
          </li>
        </ul>
        <section name="Documentation list" style="background:none;padding:0;"/>This 
        <strong>read-only</strong> list is of interest to people who are
        <a href="1273_1_1.html">working on the Cocoon documentation</a>.
        It consists solely of update notifications from the 
        <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/cocoon">Wiki</a>.
        <h3>Archive</h3>
        All available archives are reported on the 
        <a href="mail-lists.html">overview</a> page.
        <section name="SVN repository update list" style="background:none;padding:0;"/>
        This list is probably only of interest to hard-core Cocoon developers. It is a 
        <strong>read-only</strong> list that consists solely of automated update
        notifications from the Subversion source code management system.  The name
        "cocoon-cvs" is a holdover from when the Cocoon project used CVS.
        <h3>Archive</h3>
        All available archives are reported on the 
        <a href="mail-lists.html">overview</a> page.
        <h1>Wiki</h1>There's a 
        <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/cocoon/">Cocoon Wiki</a>.  YMMV
        <h1>IRC</h1>The Cocoon community chat room is the #cocoon channel at
        <a href="http://freenode.net">freenode.net</a>. Get over there and shake things up!
        <h1>JIRA</h1>Bug/issue tracking on the Cocoon project
        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/COCOON">uses Atlassian JIRA</a>.
        This is a communication medium in its own right. Updates to JIRA
        issues trigger notifications to the dev mailing list, so you can monitor each
        issue's mini-discussion from the dev mailing list.
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</document>
