<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--
      Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
      or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
      distributed with this work for additional information
      regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
      to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
      "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
      with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
      software distributed under the License is distributed on an
      "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
      KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
      specific language governing permissions and limitations
      under the License.
    --><document xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd"><properties><title>Cocoon Main Site - Live Sites - 2.1.8</title><author email="cocoon-docs@apache.org">Apache Cocoon Documentation Team</author></properties><body>
         <div id="contentBody"><div id="bodyText"><h1 class="docTitle">Live Sites - 2.1.8</h1><p>This is a list of live sites proudly powered by Apache Cocoon.</p><h1>Cocoon 2.1.8-dev</h1><ul>
<li><a href="http://oszone.org/">The Open Source Zone</a> - The Open Source
Zone's aim is to create a storefront for access to Open Source projects. The
storefront will have the same level of participation that users give back to
Amazon or iTunes by providing their personal feedback in form of reviews,
ratings, comments, developers who liked this project also liked this other one.
</li>
</ul><h1>Cocoon 2.1.8</h1><section name="Encyclopedia of Life Sciences - Wiley InterScience" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><em>Date added: 2006-07-24</em><br/>
<strong>URL:</strong>
<a href="http://www.mrw.interscience.wiley.com/emrw/047001590X/home">http://www.mrw.interscience.wiley.com/emrw/047001590X/home</a>
<br/>
<strong>Contact:</strong> epritcha [AT] wiley.co.uk<p><strong><em>Cocoon version used:</em></strong> 2.1.8 (with AJAX module and
some patches from 2.1.9)<br/>
<strong><em>Short summary:</em></strong> Major Reference work in Wiley
InterScience, first of many to be published using Cocoon-based architecture.
<br/>
<em><strong>How can we verify this site is actually built with Cocoon?</strong>
</em>Check out the X-Cocoon-Version header...</p><p><strong><em>How much time did it take to build the site from design to
publication?</em></strong><br/>
Original IA Specification in October 2005, specs for source XML took
approximately 2 months, actual build 3 months; 3 Cocoon-based engineers, 1
focusing on search, 1 on XHTML/CSS, and one on the rest of the site. We also had
some hard-working Content people working on pre-rendering of XML blobs and
MathML images, and a whole bunch of people in India marking up the XML content
documents.</p><p><strong><em>How much traffic does the site handle?</em></strong><br/>
20000 hits on launch day (24 July 2006).</p><p><strong><em>What made you choose Cocoon to build the site?</em></strong>
<br/>
6 month review of available technologies, Cocoon stood out on handling of XML,
Caching, Component re-use and the Sitemap. We also love Views and the concept of
Flows.</p><p><strong><em>What other information do you want to disclose (e.g. how does it
work, how did you build it, what parts of Cocoon did you use)?</em></strong></p><p>We've actually got some other parts of the site already implemented using
Cocoon, namely ForwardLinking (Citation-Tracking link on Journal Abstract pages:
Crossref web-service based), Author Services (production process tracking for
authors: uses web-services and FlowScript), plus our (yet to be launched) RSS
and OPML feeds, and will be moving forward with the rest of InterScience
along-side a back-end re-architecture.</p><p>We've been able to re-use a number of components from the other Cocoon
projects already, and the bulk of Cocoon work for this site has been XSL and
Sitemap wrangling, rather than application-specific Java code.</p><p>We wrote our own Generators and Transformers for DB access and Search
integration (we use back-end CORBA repositories and custom DOA for DB access,
and a legacy Verity engine for search), plus some generic transformers for SAX
manipulation, e.g. pulling single nodes for our AJAX based topic-tree out of a
huge source document. However, the bulk of the functionality is XSLT based,
using a file-system store (i.e. exactly the kind of thing Cocoon was designed
for), preferring Inclusion to Aggregation in most cases.</p><p>Access control is not implemented using Cocoon simply due to an existing
available web-server plugin, although we use a Cocoon-based 'Action' for access
control in other parts of the site.</p><p>Cocoon has vastly improved our abilty to deliver feature-rich sites on-time
and on-cost, plus, its fun!</p><section name="Computer Science Department 2 Erlangen University" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><p><em>Date added: 2006-06-29</em></p><p>Webpages of the programming systems group at the Friedrich-Alexander
University Erlangen-Nuremberg.</p><p><strong>URL:</strong>
<a href="http://www2.informatik.uni-erlangen.de/">http://www2.informatik.uni-erlangen.de/</a>
<br/>
<strong>Contact</strong>: Thorsten.Meinl [AT] informatik [DOT] uni-erlangen
[DOT] de</p><h4>Additional information</h4><h5>How much time did it take to build the site from design to publication?</h5><p>2 months.</p><h5>How much traffic does this site handle?</h5><p>  ~300MB/day, ~15,000 hits/day</p><h5>What made you choose Cocoon to build the site?</h5><p>Our university-wide information system (UnivIS,
<a href="http://univis.uni-erlangen.de/%29">http://univis.uni-erlangen.de/)</a>
offers an XML export of all data (lecture, publications, person, projects, ...)
To avoid maintaining the data at multiple places we import these data and use
Cocoon to produce our webpages more or less automatically.</p><h5>What other information do you want to disclose (e.g. how does it work, how
did you build it, what parts of Cocoon did you use)?</h5><p>Most importantly, we use eXist as XML database to store the imported data and
use the XMLDBTransformer to include it into the pipeline.</p><section name="Dutch Ministry of Finance" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><p><em>Date added: 2006-05-18</em></p><p>The main website of the Dutch Ministry of Finance is built entirely in Cocoon
2.1.8. Launched in April 2006.</p><p><strong>URL:</strong> <a href="http://www.minfin.nl">http://www.minfin.nl</a>
</p><h4>Additional information</h4><h5>How much time did it take to build the site from design to publication?</h5><p>Total development took around 4 months.</p><section name="Other sites" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><ul>
<li><a href="http://www.pyxx.org/">Pyxx.org</a> - live site on XML-related
authoring and publishing for web and on-line learning.</li>
</ul></div></div>
       </body></document>