<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
  or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
  distributed with this work for additional information
  regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
  to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
  "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
  with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
  software distributed under the License is distributed on an
  "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
  KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
  specific language governing permissions and limitations
  under the License.
-->
<!--+
    | Find usage details at http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-changes-plugin/usage.html
    |
    | @version $Id$
    +-->
<document>
  <body>
    <release version="1.0.0-M1" date="2007-??-??" description="unreleased">    
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        User specific data for a layout is now stored in a separate LayoutInstance. This allows
        the sharing of layout tree.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        CopletLayout only holds the coplet instance id instead of the object itself.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="update">
        Refactor the object model: CopletBaseData has been renamed to CopletType,
        CopletData has been renamed to CopletDefinition and CopletInstanceData
        to CopletInstance.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="update">
        Add Spring post processor to add all configured components implement the Receiver
        interface as subscribers to the event manager. This simplifies component development
        as the component itself does not need to register itself anymore.
        Remove the possibility to configure components or classes as receivers from
        the event manager.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        Add CopletDecorationProvider which provides the information for the
        title bar of a coplet. A coplet adapter can optionally implement
        this interface.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="update">
        Castor source converter can be configured using xconf instead of adding
        a castor.properties file to the classpath.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="update">
        Unify coplet adapters: Caching is now supported by all adapters including
        the portlet and wsrp adapters. Therefore the caching-uri adapter has been removed.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        Add deployment infrastructure.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        Add static layout objects and implement maximize functionality for layouts.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        Portal Service provides access to global configuration settings which can be
        used throughout the portal.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        Add AJAX support.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        Make coplet adapters accessible from portal component manager.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        Add layout source to stream complete coplets/layouts.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        Add temporary attributes to Layout objects.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="update">
        Move Castor support into own package and support roles files for Castor. This makes
        including/excluding the Castor support easier.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="update">
        Simplify object model by removing Producible. Clean up Castor mapping.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="remove">
        Remove the support for aspect data handling.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="update">
        Tab events are now convertable.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="update">
        The lifetime of encoded events is now the user session.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="remove">
        Remove aspect datas from layouts. Parameters are now used instead.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        Add CopletInstanceDataFeatures and CopletDataFeatures utility classes
        to query optional features of coplets and to track changed coplets.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="update">
        Refactor url creation for events (NOT FINISHED YET).
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="remove">
        Remove aspect datas from coplet instance datas. Attributes are now used instead.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="remove">
        Remove AbstractUserProfileManager and AuthenticationProfileManager. Use
        GroupBasedProfileManager instead.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        Add coplet size to coplet instance data. The size can be minimized,
        normal or full-screen. This removed the need for a special full screen
        handling.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="add">
        Enable per sitemap configuration for portal applications and add several roles files
        for default configurations. Using per sitemap configurations and including the provided
        roles files make the configuration of the portal much easier.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="remove">
        Remove aspect datas from coplet datas. Attributes are now used instead.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="remove">
        Remove deprecated Publisher, Subscriber, Filter and Register.
      </action>
      <action dev="cziegler" type="remove">
        Remove deprecated PortletPortalManager.
      </action>
      <action dev="reinhard" type="add">
        Initial creation.
      </action>      
    </release>
  </body>
</document>
