<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Cocoon-based and Cocoon-related Projects</title>
  <authors>
   <person name="Andreas Hochsteger" email="e9625392@student.tuwien.ac.at"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>

<s1 title="Cocoon-based Projects">
<ul>
<li><link href="http://www.wyona.org/">Wyona CMS</link><br/>
	Wyona CMS is an Open-Source Content Management and Publishing System written in 100% pure Java.
	It is based on open standards such as XML ( DOM, SAX) and XSLT.
	One of its core components is the pipeline processor Cocoon from the Apache Software Foundation.
</li>
<li><link href="http://opensource.yourdecor.ca/faq1/index.html">FAQ Project</link><br/>
	A web-based, database driven that make use of JSP and XML and Cocoon.
</li>
<li><link href="http://www.sourcepole.com/sources/software/sp.xsl/">sp.xsl</link><br/>
	Generate simple websites with XSL.
</li>
<li><link href="http://webeditor.sourceforge.net/">WebEditor WCMS</link><br/>
	webEditor is a web application to manage the content of a news-based web site (you know Slashdot?).
	It's based on Apache Cocoon and Apache/ApacheJServ/Tomcat as Web Server/Servlet platform.
</li>
<li><link href="http://chello.sourceforge.net/">Chello - A minimal Cocoon 2 application</link><br/>
	Chello is an Open Source minimal Cocoon 2 application. It features project compilation using ANT,
	unit testing with JUnit, functional testing with HTTPUnit, continuous integration process with CruiseControl,
	documentation generation for Java code using javadoc and XSL Stylesheets using XSLDoc,
	project documentation using Cocoon and automatic build of web archive file (WAR) for easy distribution.
</li>
<li><link href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/holometabolous/">Holometabolous - CMS, Profiling and App Suite</link><br/>
	A content management, profiling and application suite built on top of software from the Apache foundation, most especially Cocoon, with a database back end.
	The goal is to make the power of Java/SQL/XML easy to leverage 'out of the box.'
</li>
<li><link href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/xmlleague/">XMLLeague</link><br/>
	Sports (soccer) league administration.
</li>
<li><link href="http://buglet.sourceforge.net/">Buglet - XML Bugtracking System</link><br/>
	An xml-centric bug system implemented in Java as a servlet running on top of Cocoon/Tomcat. 
	Supports e-mail and web based submission of bugs.
	Buglet offers a standardized form for the data associated with bugs.
</li>
<li>CocoBlog is a free weblogging software tool based on Apache Cocoon and 
 Apache Xindice. For more information see Ugo Cei's weblog at 
 <link href="http://www.beblogging.com/blog/">http://www.beblogging.com/blog/</link>
</li>
<li><link href="http://xreporter.cocoondev.org/">xReporter</link> is an Avalon/Cocoon-based database reporting application that makes use of XML report
  definitions to produce HTML, CSV, Excel and PDF reports available across a web interface.</li>
</ul>
</s1>

<s1 title="Cocoon-related Projects">
<ul>
<li><link href="http://editxml.sourceforge.net/">EditXML - Managing XML files for Cocoon</link><br/>
	Edit XML provides a servlet based solution for managing sets of XML files for XML based publishing systems like Cocoon.
</li>
<li><link href="http://pollo.sourceforge.net/">Pollo XML Editor (with Cocoon sitemap support)</link><br/>
	Pollo lets you edit XML files. It's best suited for files which can be represented in a tree structure.
	It comes with built-in support for Cocoon sitemap files, Ant build files and XML Schemas.
	The editor has a colourful tree widget (not the default Swing one!), drag-and-drop support, unlimited undo, model-view design (open multiple views on the same file), ...
</li>
<li><link href="http://www.plenix.com/dbprism/">DBPrism XML Framework for Oracle DB</link><br/>
	DBPrism is a servlet engine that works in two different modes: as a standalone servlet, or plugged into the Cocoon publishing framework. 
	In the first mode, DBPrism works like the PLSQL Cartridge of Oracle Web Server. 
	Plugged into the Cocoon framework, DBPrism works as a DB Producer, generating dynamic XML from a database.
</li>
<li><link href="http://jeuclid.sourceforge.net/">JEuclid - MathML Transformer for Cocoon</link><br/>
	The project is a component for the Apache Cocoon project which converts MathML documents to GIF images or SVG.
</li>
<li><link href="http://exformula.d-haven.org/">ExFormula - XForms for Cocoon</link><br/>
	ExFormula is an implementation of the XForms specification.
	It allows you to define XML Models and Instances associated with it, to process dynamic forms based on an end markup.
</li>
<li><link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/poi/">POI - OLE2 File System (DOC, XLS, ...)</link><br/>
	The POI project consists of APIs for manipulating various file formats based upon Microsoft's OLE 2 Compound Document format using pure Java.
	There will soon be generators and serializers for Cocoon to read/write MS Office file formats.
</li>
<li><link href="http://opensource.bibop.it/bbp/xforge/index.html">X:Forge XML Framework</link><br/>
	X:Forge is an XML Language whose main focus is in dynamic XML generation.
	X:Forge tags are supposed to be included in XML documents for further processing.
	The tool was designed as a replacement for XSP, an Apache technology originally used for dynamic generation of XML content in the Cocoon Project and slowly evolving into an Internet standard.
</li>
</ul>
</s1>

  <s1 title="How to get listed">
   <p>
    If you do not find your project here, make sure you
    <link href="mailto:cocoon-users@xml.apache.org?subject=Link: Project:">tell us</link>.
    Enter a meaningful title after the words &quot;Link: Project:&quot;
    in the subject, provide a short summary of your project, and do not forget
    to tell us the URL.
    You could also follow the <link href="../contrib.html">Contributing</link>
    page to make it easier for everyone.
   </p>
  </s1>

</body>
</document>
