<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Cocoon Training</title>
  <authors>
   <person name="Andreas Hochsteger" email="e9625392@student.tuwien.ac.at"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>
<s1 title="Cocoon Training">
<ul>
<li><link href="http://www.galatea.com/training/index.html">Galatea Information Strategies</link><br/>
	They have two classes now available: Cocoon Fundamentals and Advanced Cocoon.
	Both courses are two days each and are offered in Denver, Colorado.
	It is also possible to arrange on-site training if there are sufficient participants.
</li>
<li><link href="http://www.s-und-n.de/sunshine/services-training-cocoonschulungen_english">S&amp;N AG</link><br/>
S&amp;N offers Cocoon training. Two courses are available -
"Introducing Cocoon" (3 days) for beginners and "Unraveling Cocoon" for
developers (2 days). The courses are available in English or German.
	It is also possible to arrange on-site training.
</li>
<li><link href="http://www.anyware-tech.com">Anyware Technologies</link><br/>
Anyware Technologies offers <link href="http://www.anyware-tech.com/french/sce_training.html">Cocoon
training</link> in France. Course are organized in two classes (3 day introduction and 2 day advanced),
but can be mixed with our other XML and Java training material to meet specific needs.
Courses are held in French and can be on-site.
</li>
<li><link href="http://www.oio.de/">Orientation in Objects</link><br/>
You can learn how to develop web applications using Cocoon and XSPs in a three
day training course. Courses will take place every 2 months in Mannheim,
Germany.
See <link href="http://www.oio.de/seminar/xml/cocoon-schulung.htm">course
description</link>. We also offer on-site training in English.
</li>
</ul>
</s1>
  
  <s1 title="How to get listed">
   <p>
    If you do not find your site here, make sure you
    <link href="mailto:cocoon-users@xml.apache.org?subject=Link: Training:">tell us</link>.
    Enter a meaningful title after the words &quot;Link: Training:&quot;
    in the subject, provide a short summary of your site, and do not forget
    to tell us the URL.
    You could also follow the <link href="../contrib.html">Contributing</link>
    page to make it easier for everyone.
   </p>
  </s1>

</body>
</document>
