<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Updating Cocoon</title>
  <authors>
   <person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>

 <s1 title="Updating Cocoon">
  <p>
   This is a brief discussion of the changes between the latest official release @released.version@
   and the current development version of Apache Cocoon. So, if you are interested in
   installing the official release, ignore this document. But if you want to know what is going
   on in the development of Cocoon, have a look...
  </p>
  <p>
   Cocoon has developed many Avalon components which are of a more general nature. So, the best
   solution was to donate these components to the Avalon Excalibur project and move them out 
   of Cocoon. This move has lead to some changes in configuration etc. which are described
   by this document.
  </p>
  <p>In addition there were some disadvantages in the internal architecture of Cocoon. The
    new version removes these bottlenecks and gives more flexibility, usability and performance.
   </p>
 </s1>
  <s1 title="Sitemap">
  <p>There are some changes in the sitemap and the configuration of some components in
     the sitemap.</p>
  <s2 title="FOP Serializer">
  <p>FOP serializer's &lt;user-config&gt; relative path now resolves relative
    to sitemap's directory. All Cocoon URIs are supported too.
  </p>
  </s2>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Components">
  <p>
    The Cocoon architecture has had some significant changes. However, great care has been
    taken that all changes are in a compatible way. This effort has been successful except
    one change which shouldn't affect anybody (see below).
  </p>
  <s2 title="Source Resolving">
<p>Under Cocoon 2.0.x, the SourceResolver was not an Avalon component, so it could not be looked up using a component manager. Under 2.1, the SourceResolver is now an Avalon component and can be requested using <em>cocoon.manager.lookup(SourceResolver.ROLE).</em></p>  
  </s2>
  <s2 title="XSLT Processor">
    <p>Mention changes and update strategy...</p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="XML Parser">
    <p>The XML parser has also been moved to Excalibur.
     In the cocoon.xconf the hint name has therefore changed from <em>parser</em> to
     <em>xml-parser</em>. The configuration has not changed, so if you want to
     manually update swap the hint names.</p>
    <p>From within your source code you should not lookup the
      <em>org.apache.cocoon.components.parser.Parser.ROLE</em> anymore; use
      <em>org.apache.excalibur.xml.sax.SAXParser.ROLE</em> instead.
    </p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="XML Entity Resolver">
    <p>The resolver used for resolving XML entities has also been moved to Excalibur.
     In the cocoon.xconf the hint name has therefore changed from <em>resolver</em> to
     <em>entity-resolver</em>. The configuration has not changed, so if you want to
     manually update swap the hint names and the implementation.</p>
    <p>From within your source code you should not lookup the
      <em>org.apache.cocoon.components.resolver.Resolver.ROLE</em> anymore; use
      <em>org.apache.excalibur.xml.EntityResolver.ROLE</em> instead.
    </p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="Stores">
    <p>The Store and StoreJanitor components and implementations have moved to
       Avalon Excalibur.</p>
    <p>TODO:Changes in cocoon.xconf...</p>
    <p>In general the packages changed from org.apache.cocoon.components.store
       to org.apache.excalibur.store (resp. org.apache.excalibur.store.impl). So
       if you have custom java code using this components, you have to change
       your imports.</p>
    <p>The roles PERSISTENT_CACHE and TRANSIENT_CACHE have been renamed to
       PERSISTENT_STORE and TRANSIENT_STORE. The hold() method has been removed
       from the Store interface.</p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="SAXConnectors, Stream and Event Pipeline">
    <p>This is the only real incompatible change (But don't panic, this will
       not affect you, well at least only a little bit :). The internal architecture of Cocoon
       has changed. In the older version, the processing pipeline - constructed by
       a generator, the transformers and a serializer - was represented by two components,
       called stream and event pipeline.</p>
    <p>For a simpler architecture, enhanced functionality and improved performance,
       these components have been combined into one: the processing pipeline.
       The very rarely used feature of SAXConnectors has been removed,
       to avoid overcomponentization.</p>
    <p>In addition the map:pipeline element of the sitemap has gained more meaning
      as it is now possible to configure each map:pipeline section in the sitemap
      differently. So there can be one section using caching, another one not 
      caching at all and a third one using a different caching implementation etc.
    </p>
    <s3 title="Changed Configuration">
     <p>
      The configuration of the pipelines has moved from the cocoon.xconf to the sitemap.
      So, for updating you have to remove the "event-pipeline" and "stream-pipeline" section
      from your cocoon.xconf and add the map:pipes section to the map:components section
      in your sitemap. You can find the pipelines components definition in the sample
      sitemap of Cocoon. Here is an example:
     </p>
     <source><![CDATA[
<map:sitemap>
 <map:components>
      ...
  <map:pipes default="caching">
     <map:pipe name="caching" 
                   src="org.apache.cocoon.components.pipeline.impl.CachingProcessingPipeline"/>
     <map:pipe name="noncaching" 
                   src="org.apache.cocoon.components.pipeline.impl.NonCachingProcessingPipeline"/>
  </map:pipes>
 </map:components>
   ...
</map:sitemap>
     ]]></source>
     <p>The configuration is similar to the configuration of other sitemap components, like
       generators or actions. You can choose these different implementations of pipelines
       in the map:pipeline section by specifying the type attribute:
     </p>
     <source><![CDATA[
<map:sitemap>
   ...
  <map:pipelines>
     <map:pipeline type="noncaching">
           <map:match pattern="welcome">
                  ...
           </map:match>
            ..
     </map:pipeline>
  </map:pipelines>
</map:sitemap>
     ]]></source>
     <p>So again, this is similar to choosing the type of the generator or any other sitemap
       component. If you omit the type attribute the default configuration from the components
       section is used.
     </p>
     <p>The SAXConnectors have been removed, so if you manually upgrade you have to remove
        the <em>sax-connectors</em> configuration from the <em>cocoon.xconf</em>.</p>
     <p>So you see, although this is an incompatible change in the Java code, you have only
       little to do to update your Cocoon installation.</p>
    </s3>
  </s2>
 </s1>
 
</body>
</document>
