<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Updating Cocoon</title>
  <authors>
   <person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org"/>
   <person name="J&#246;rg Heinicke" email="joerg@apache.org"/>
   <person name="Bertrand Delacr&#233;taz" email="bdelacretaz@apache.org"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>
  <s1 title="Known Issues for 2.1.5">
   <p>
     This is a list of known issues for Cocoon 2.1.5.
   </p>
   <s2 title="Store">
     <p>
      Cocoon 2.1.5 uses different implementation of the store based on the
      <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/jcs">JCS</link>.
      This new implementation currently does not allow storing of not serializable objects,
      and it does not write out memory cache to the disk on shutdown. If you depend on
      this functionality, you can keep 2.1.4 store configuration.
     </p>
     <p>
      Cocoon 2.1.4 used MRUMemoryStore as store implementation and JISPStore as persistent
      store implementation. JISPStore is known to corrupt storage file under some
      conditions.
     </p>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="Logging Configuration">
     <p>
      Cocoon 2.1.5 uses a newer version of the Avalon Excalibur logging package
      than version 2.1.4. Unfortunately this logging package has an imcompatibility
      to the version used in Cocoon 2.1.4.
     </p>
     <p>
      If you update your application from 2.1.4 to 2.1.5 make sure that you have
      a log definition for the empty category in your logkit.xconf. Add the following
      lines to your category definition:
     </p>
     <source><![CDATA[
    <category name="" log-level="@loglevel@">
      <log-target id-ref="core"/>
      <log-target id-ref="error"/>
    </category>
     ]]></source>
   </s2>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Updating Cocoon">
   <p>
    Please take your time to read this document completely before trying to upgrade from
    a Cocoon 2.0.x installation to 2.1 (or above). You can also read it if you want to
    know what was going on in the development of Cocoon.
   </p>
   <p>
    The Cocoon team took great care in making this new version as compatible as
    possible. However, in order to achieve even more flexibility, usability and
    performance, the internal architecure of Cocoon has been improved. Due to these
    improvements it has not been possible to be compatible in every little detail.
    If you follow the instructions of document closely, however,
    you should be able to quickly upgrade your Cocoon 2.0.x installation.
   </p>
   <p>
    The Cocoon team has developed many Avalon components that are not specific to Cocoon
    and therefore have been donated to the Avalon Excalibur project and moved out
    of Cocoon. This has led to some configuration changes which are also described
    in this document.
   </p>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Sitemap">
   <note>There are some changes in the sitemap and in the configuration of some
    components in the sitemap. In general we recommend you to start with a new
    sitemap from 2.1 and to adapt it to your needs. But for manual migration we
    will list as many changes as possible.</note>
   <s2 title="Pipelines configuration in the sitemap">
     <p>
      The configuration of the pipelines has moved from cocoon.xconf to the sitemap.
      To update your installation, you have to remove the "event-pipeline" and "stream-pipeline"
      section from your cocoon.xconf (see also the cocoon.xconf section) and add the
      <code>map:pipes</code> section to the <code>map:components</code> section
      of your sitemap. You can find the pipelines components definition in the sample
      main sitemap of Cocoon. Here is an example:
     </p>
     <source><![CDATA[
<map:sitemap>
 <map:components>
      ...
  <map:pipes default="caching">
   <map:pipe name="caching"
    src="org.apache.cocoon.components.pipeline.impl.CachingProcessingPipeline"/>
   <map:pipe name="noncaching"
    src="org.apache.cocoon.components.pipeline.impl.NonCachingProcessingPipeline"/>
  </map:pipes>
 </map:components>
   ...
</map:sitemap>
     ]]></source>
     <p>You can choose these different pipeline implementations
       in the <code>map:pipeline</code> section by specifying their <code>type</code> attribute:
     </p>
     <source><![CDATA[
<map:sitemap>
  ...
 <map:pipelines>
  <map:pipeline type="noncaching">
   <map:match pattern="welcome">
                  ...
   </map:match>
            ..
  </map:pipeline>
 </map:pipelines>
</map:sitemap>
     ]]></source>
     <p>This is similar to choosing the type of a generator or any other sitemap component.
       If the type attribute is omitted, the default configuration from the
       <code>map:components</code> section is used.
     </p>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="FOP Serializer">
    <p>Relative paths in FOP serializer's <code>&lt;user-config&gt;</code> are now resolved
      relatively to the directory that contains the sitemap.</p>
    <p>All Cocoon URIs are supported too.</p>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="Sitemap components">
    <p>Some of the sitemap components have been removed from Cocoon sources, others were renamed.
      If you have the old declaration in your sitemap, you will get
      <code>ClassNotFoundException</code>s. Trial and error will probably be the fastest way for
      removing them and getting a clean and working sitemap. Hopefully you are not using one of the
      removed components. The following components are known to be removed or renamed:</p>
    <ul>
     <li>
      <code>o.a.c.XTTransformer</code> - use the TraxTransformer instead.
     </li>
     <li>
      <code>o.a.c.webapps.authentication.selection.MediaSelector</code> - the full qualified class
      name has changed to <code>o.a.c.webapps.session.selection.MediaSelector</code>.
     </li>
    </ul>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="Error handling">
     <p>The <code>map:handle-errors</code> section must now be a complete pipeline. This means the
       old form</p>
     <source><![CDATA[
    <map:handle-errors>
      <map:transform src="stylesheets/system/error2html.xsl"/>
      <map:serialize status-code="404"/>
    </map:handle-errors>
  ]]></source>
     <p>is no longer valid, because the generator is missing. Therefore you can now describe
     explicitely the error handling. The replacement of the above looks like the following:</p>
     <source><![CDATA[
    <map:handle-errors>
      <map:generate type="notifying"/>
      <map:transform src="stylesheets/system/error2html.xsl"/>
      <map:serialize status-code="404"/>
    </map:handle-errors>
  ]]></source>
     <p>For a more detailed example have a look into the default sitemap delivered with Cocoon
       sources or read the
       <link href="../userdocs/concepts/errorhandling.html">documentation on error handling</link>.
     </p>
   </s2>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Namespace changes">
    <p>
      In order to have consistent namespaces, some transformers and generators
      (listed below) use new namespaces. If you use any of these components, you
      will need to use the new namespaces.
    </p>
    <s2 title="Request Generator">
    <p>RequestGenerator changed its namespace from
      <code>http://xml.apache.org/cocoon/requestgenerator/2.0</code> to
      <code>http://apache.org/cocoon/request/2.0</code>.
    </p>
    </s2>
    <s2 title="I18nTransformer">
      <p>The I18nTransformer supports both
         <code>http://apache.org/cocoon/i18n/2.0</code> and
         <code>http://apache.org/cocoon/i18n/2.1</code> namespace.</p>
    </s2>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Changes in logging interfaces require recompilation">
    <p>
       Due to some interface changes in the Cocoon logging components, custom java
       components (generators, transformers or actions for example) compiled for Cocoon
       2.0.x will not run under Cocoon 2.1 unless recompiled.</p>
       <p>It's also advisable to change your implementations from using <em>Loggable</em>
         to <em>LogEnabled</em> when it comes to logging in your components.
       </p>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Components">
   <p>
    The Cocoon architecture has changed significantly. However, great care has been
    taken to preserve backwards compatibility.
   </p>
   <s2 title="Cocoon Configuration (cocoon.xconf)">
    <p>In order to reflect the new version, the version information in the <em>cocoon.xconf</em>
       has changed from <em>2.0</em> to <em>2.1</em>.
    </p>
    <p>To update <em>cocoon.xconf</em>, we recommend that you start with the new cocoon.xconf from V2.1 and
       incorporate your changes in it, instead of trying to migrate your old configuration file.</p>
     <p>The SAXConnectors have been removed, so if you upgrade manually you have to remove
        the <em>sax-connectors</em> configuration from <em>cocoon.xconf</em>.</p>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="Source Resolver">
    <p>The SourceResolver is now an Avalon component
      which can be accessed using <em>cocoon.manager.lookup(SourceResolver.ROLE).</em>.
      The package name of the component is <em>org.apache.excalibur.source</em>.</p>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="XSLT Processor">
    <p>There are some issues related to JDK 1.4.</p>
     <s3 title="XML/XSLT with JDK 1.4">
      <p>Another serious issue is the presence of the Xalan and Xerces
       package in the JDK 1.4. For general information on this please read the
       <link href="http://xml.apache.org/xalan-j/faq.html#jdk14">Xalan FAQ</link> and our own
       <link href="http://wiki.cocoondev.org/Wiki.jsp?page=EndorsedLibsProblem">EndorsedLibsProblem</link>
       wiki page.
      </p>
      <p>
       Basically, you have to update your libraries in the endorsed dirs of the JDK
       or the servlet containers with every new version of Xalan and Xerces delivered with Cocoon.
       Strange errors can occur if you have different versions of these packages in the
       classpath (independent of those in the JDK).
      </p>
     </s3>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="XML Parser">
    <p>The XML parser component has been moved to Excalibur.
     In cocoon.xconf, the hint name has therefore changed from <em>parser</em> to
     <em>xml-parser</em>. The configuration has not changed, so changing the hint
     names is sufficent.</p>
    <p>Java code should not use
      <em>org.apache.cocoon.components.parser.Parser.ROLE</em> anymore; use
      <em>org.apache.excalibur.xml.sax.SAXParser.ROLE</em> instead.
    </p>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="XML Entity Resolver">
    <p>Similarly, the XML entity resolver component has been moved to Excalibur.
     In cocoon.xconf the hint name has therefore changed from <em>resolver</em> to
     <em>entity-resolver</em>. The configuration has not changed, so changing the hint
     names is sufficent.</p>
    <p>Java code should not use
      <em>org.apache.cocoon.components.resolver.Resolver.ROLE</em> anymore; use
      <em>org.apache.excalibur.xml.EntityResolver.ROLE</em> instead.
    </p>
    <p>The default entities (DTDs, entity sets, etc.) have moved to the
     WEB-INF/ directory.
    </p>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="Caching">
    <p>Although the basic caching mechanism is still the same (each sitemap component
       in the pipeline is queried), the interface for a component have been
       improved as well.</p>
    <p>The old interface <em>Cacheable</em> is deprecated in favour of the new
      <em>CacheableProcessingComponent</em> interface. The basic behaviour of this
      interface has been preserved, however the method names and the signatures
      have changed a little bit.
      </p>
    <p>Some other interfaces, like the validity of the cached information has
      moved to the source packacke in Avalon Excalibur.</p>
    <p>The old interfaces are still support but deprecated, so it's advisable to
      update your components. However, you can support both interfaces at the
      same time, making your component runable in old and new Cocoon installations
      at the same time.</p>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="Stores">
    <p>The Store and StoreJanitor components and implementations have been moved to
       Avalon Excalibur.</p>
    <p>To make upgrading easier, the class attributes of the store janitor
       component have been removed in <em>cocoon.xconf</em> as the class names have changed.
       The <em>cache-transient</em> and <em>cache-persistent</em> components do
       not exist anymore, so any reference to them must be removed from cocoon.xconf.
       Use the <em>persistent-store</em> and <em>transient-store</em> components instead.
    </p>
    <p>In general the package names changed from <em>org.apache.cocoon.components.store</em>
       to <em>org.apache.excalibur.store</em> (and <em>org.apache.excalibur.store.impl</em>). So
       if you have custom java code using these components, you have to change
       your imports.</p>
    <p>The roles <em>PERSISTENT_CACHE</em> and <em>TRANSIENT_CACHE</em> have been renamed to
       <em>PERSISTENT_STORE</em> and <em>TRANSIENT_STORE</em>. The hold() method has been removed
       from the Store interface.</p>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="SAXConnectors, Stream and Event Pipeline">
    <p>This is the only real incompatible change (But don't panic, this will
       not affect you, or maybe just a little bit..).
    </p>
    <p>
       The internal architecture of Cocoon
       has changed: previously, the processing pipeline - consisting of
       a generator, the transformers and a serializer - was represented by two components,
       called <em>stream</em> and <em>event pipeline</em>.</p>
    <p>For a simpler architecture, enhanced functionality and improved performance,
       these components have been combined into one: the <em>processing pipeline</em>.
       The <em>SAXConnectors</em>, which were rarely used, have been removed
       to avoid overcomponentization.</p>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="File Upload">
     <p>The class name for file upload has changed from <em>org.apache.cocoon.components.request.multipart.FilePart</em> to
        <em>org.apache.cocoon.servlet.multipart.Part</em>, and the <em>getFilePath()</em> has been renamed
        <em>Part.getUploadName()</em>.
     </p>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="RequestLifeCycleComponent">
    <p>If you are using the marker interface <em>RequestLifeCycleComponent</em> for your
    own components, you have to make sure that your implementations still implement
    the <em>Component</em> interface. The <em>RequestLifeCycleComponent</em> does no
    longer extend the <em>Component</em> interface, so you have to declare it in your
    own components together with <em>RequestLifeCycleComponent</em>. Otherwise you
    will get a <em>ClassCastException</em> as soon as you access your component.</p>
   </s2>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Components from the scratchpad">
    <p>Cocoon 2.0.x had some components in the scratchpad area that have now moved into
       the main trunk as blocks. With this move some things have changed.
    </p>
    <s2 title="Session, Authentication and Portal">
      <p>The session framework (sunShine), the authentication framework (sunRise)
         and the portal framework (sunSpot) are now blocks (session-fw, authentication-fw
         and portal-fw).
      </p>
      <p>The <em>sunShine transformer</em> has been renamed to <em>session transformer</em>.
        All sitemap components starting with <em>sunrise-</em> have been changed to
        start now with <em>auth-</em>. The <em>sunrise-auth</em> action has been
        renamed to <em>auth-protect</em>.
      </p>
      <p>
      The transformer namespace has changed from <em>http://cocoon.apache.org/sunshine/1.0</em>
      to <em>http://apache.org/cocoon/session/1.0</em> and the context names have changed
      from <em>sunshine</em> to <em>session</em> and from <em>sunrise</em> to
      <em>authentication</em>.
      </p>
    </s2>
  </s1>
 </body>
</document>
