<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">
<document>
    <header>
        <title>Session Management</title>
        <authors>
            <person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@s-und-n.de"/>
        </authors>
    </header>
    <body>
  <s1 title="Introduction">
     <p>A session is a data storage which resides on the server and records
        information about one single user. Cocoon creates a session on demand and
        from that point of time the user is tracked and information can be stored
        inside the session. Each following request of this user is linked to the one
        specific session, so there is always only one session per user on the
        server.</p>
     <p>To avoid a fast growing amount of sessions on the server and the
        overcome potential security problems, a session has usually a valid period of
        time. If during this period no new request comes in from the user, the session
        object on the server will be destroyed by the server (this period of time is
        called session timeout). The web application often allows a user to explictly
        destroy a session.</p>
     <p>The usual web applications create sessions during login of a user and
        destroy them when the user logs out.</p>
     <p>This document describes the basic Cocoon session management using
        the session transformer.</p>
     <p>The chapter "Special Contexts" explains some special
        contexts which do not require a session. They are available everytime. These
        special contexts are the request context, the response context and the
        temporary context.</p>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Session Tracking">
    <p>If a user has a session, Cocoon is able to connect new requests from this user
       to the session of the user. This is done by session tracking. Basically,
       the session tracking of Cocoon uses the session tracking of the environment,
       which is usually the servlet engine.
    </p>
    <p>There are two methods for session tracking: cookies and url rewriting. If you
       use cookies, you don't have to care about session tracking. Just refer to
       the documentation of your servlet engine on how to turn on cookies for session
       handling.</p>
    <p>URL rewriting instead is a little bit complicated. For url rewriting, each link
       the user can select, needs a special session ID appended to this link. 
       Unfortunately, this is not done automatically by Cocoon or the servlet engine.
       You can either do this by hand or you can use the <em>encodeURL</em> transformer
       just before the <em>html serializer</em>.
    </p>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Sessions">
     <p>The session action is responsible for creating and
        terminating a session. It is controlled by a sitemap parameter named "action".
        This parameter can have the values "create" and "terminate". If no parameter is
        set, it defaults to "create".</p>
     <p>The action either creates a new session immediately (if not already
        available), or terminates it (if available).</p>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Contexts">
     <s2 title="session Transformer">
        <p>The session transformer is responsible for interpreting the tags
          and performing the actions required. The session transformer is configured
          in the sitemap and can be used inside a document. All tags must be prefixed
          with the session namespace. So the actual tag used in the document will read
          <em>&lt;session:xxxx&gt;</em>. The current namespace URI for the session 
          transformer is <em>"http://apache.org/cocoon/session/1.0"</em>.</p>
     </s2>
     <s2 title="Context-Tags">
        <p>A context is basically an application specific block of XML data in
          the users session. Each context has a unique name.</p>
        <p>The command <em>createcontext</em> is used to create a new context.
          A <em>name</em> attribute must be given to the context in order to identify it.
          The following names may not be used: request, response, session,
          context, temp, portal or authentication. If a context of the same name already exists
          then this command will have no effect.</p>
        <p><em>&lt;createcontext name="mycontext"/&gt;</em></p>
        <p>In order to delete a context the command <em>deletecontext</em> is
          provided. Again a <em>name</em> attribute must be provided.</p>
        <p><em>&lt;deletecontext name="mycontext"/&gt;</em></p>
        <p>Once created, XML data can then be stored inside or read from a
          given context.</p>
     </s2>
     <s2 title="Accessing context data">
        <p>The data in a context can be dynamically accessed using the
          following commands.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p><em>getxml</em> allows data to be read out of a context. A
          <em>path</em> attribute describes the source of the data inside the context and
          consists of an XPath expression. All <em>path</em> values must be absolute and
          only nodes and attributes can be accessed. </p>
        <p>An optional default value can also be provided to allow for the
          nonexistence of the requested data.</p>
        <p><em>&lt;getxml context="mycontext"
          path="/User/Name"/&gt;</em></p>
        <p><em>&lt;getxml context="mycontext"
          path="/User/Name"&gt;Matthew&lt;/getxml&gt;</em></p>
        <p>Attributes can also be accessed.</p>
        <p><em>&lt;getxml context="mycontext"
          path="/User/Name/@Age"/&gt;</em></p>
        <p><em></em></p>
        <p>Data can be written into a context using the <em>setxml</em>
          command. It is possible to set values or nodes as the following examples
          show.</p>
        <p><em>&lt;setxml context="mycontext"
          path="/User/Name"/&gt;Carsten&lt;/setxml&gt;</em></p>
        <p><em>&lt;setxml context="mycontext"
          path="/User/"/&gt;&lt;Name&gt;Carsten&lt;/Name&gt;&lt;/setxml&gt;</em></p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Using the <em>setxml</em> command causes all the nodes below the
          target node to be deleted. If you wish to maintain the nodes and manipulate
          individual branches of the XML tree - then the session transformer offers the
          <em>mergexml</em> command.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Use the <em>removexml</em> command to remove nodes from the
          context.</p>
        <p><em>&lt;removexml context="mycontext"
          path="/User/"/&gt;</em></p>
        <s3 title="Example">
          <p>The following example shows the use of several commands and in
             particular how the <em>mergexml</em> command can be used to manipulate context
             data.</p>
          <source>&lt;resource xmlns:session="http://apache.org/cocoon/session/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;session:createcontext name="trackdemo"/&gt;
  &lt;!-- build context data --&gt;
  &lt;session:setxml context="trackdemo" path="/"&gt;
    &lt;context&gt;
      &lt;users&gt;
        &lt;user id="1"&gt;
          &lt;name&gt;Carsten&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;/user&gt;
      &lt;/users&gt;
    &lt;/context&gt;
  &lt;/session:setxml&gt;
  &lt;session:mergexml context="trackdemo" path="/context"&gt;
    &lt;users&gt;
      &lt;user id="1"&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;Ziegeler&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;developer&gt;true&lt;/developer&gt;
      &lt;/user&gt;
      &lt;user id="2"&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;Walter&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;/user&gt;
    &lt;/users&gt;
  &lt;/session:mergexml&gt;
  &lt;session:getxml context="trackdemo" path="/"/&gt;
&lt;/resource&gt;</source>
          <p>In the above example, a context for storing data is added. Using
             the <em>setxml</em> command data is then stored into the context. The following
             <em>mergexml</em> command then changes the name of user-1 and adds a further
             tag. As there is no original user-2 the complete subtree is then added to the
             context.</p>
        </s3>
     </s2>
     <s2 title="Reading and writing contexts">
        <p>Aside from the described means of accessing data in a context,
          the session transformer also provides for the reading and writing of contexts. This can be
          used to write an application context out to a database or to read an
          application context in from a file.</p>
        <p>The session transformer offers a very flexible way of defining the source of the
          context data. It is possible to specify a resource (defined in the sitemap) or
          a Java class. Using a resource allows for example the context data to be read
          from a database using the SQL Transformer. As this source is a Cocoon
          pipeline, the data can be generated and transformed before passing into the
          context. </p>
        <p>When a context is created, it can get additional save and load URIs
          which are used for loading/saving to/from the context:</p>
        <p><em>&lt;createcontext name="mycontext" load="cocoon://load-from-db"
          save="cocoon://save-to-db"/&gt;</em></p>
        <p>These URIs can then be used inside a document to load data into a
          context:</p>
        <p><em>&lt;loadxml context="mycontext"/&gt;</em></p>
        <p>This example would then load the context data via the resource
          <em>load-from-db</em> which must be defined in the sitemap.</p>
        <p>Parameters can be passed to and interpreted by the uri or the Java
          class. This allows the context data to be read dependent on say the current
          user.</p>
        <p><em>&lt;loadxml
          context="mycontext"&gt;&lt;user&gt;ben&lt;/user&gt;&lt;/loadxml&gt;</em></p>

        <p>The resource addressed by the uri will receive the parameters as
          request-parameters. In addition the name of the context will always be passed
          as <em>contextname</em>.</p>
        <p>Writing context data works in the same manner.</p>
        <p><em>&lt;savexml context="mycontext"/&gt;</em></p>
        <p>Both commands can use the optional <em>path</em> attribute:</p>
        <p><em>&lt;loadxml context="mycontext" path="/user"/&gt;</em></p>
        <p><em>&lt;savexml context="mycotnext" path="/user"/&gt;</em></p>
        <p>The first command will read xml from the uri and store it in the
          context under the node <em>user</em>, the second one saves only the xml subtree
          under the node <em>user</em> to the uri. The resource addressed by the uri will
          be passed in addition to the <em>contextname</em> parameter the <em>path</em>
          parameter with the corresponding value. If the <em>path</em> attribute is not
          present the <em>path</em> parameter will get the value <em>"/"</em>.</p>
     </s2>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Special Contexts">
     <p>Cocoon creates and maintains special contexts that allow the
        applications to access the environment. This allows the read-only access
        to such things as the current request or the response using the same XPath
        commands previously described. These context do not require any session, they
        are always available and change on every request.</p>
     <s2 title="The Request Context - Accessing the Environment, Part One">
        <p>The request context is an XML description of the current
          (HTTP) request. This context is a special read only context that
          can be accessed with the usual commands:</p>
        <p><em>&lt;getxml context="request" path="/parameter"/&gt;</em></p>

        <p>For example, if you want to get the value of a parameter with the
          name <em>username</em> you can include the following command in your XML and it
          will be replaced with the value of the parameter:</p>
        <p><em>&lt;getxml context="request"
          path="/parameter/username"/&gt;</em></p>
        <p>If you wish to obtain the complete querystring as it was
          passed into Cocoon - without converting the data to XML - then you can use
          the "/querystring" path:</p>
        <p><em>&lt;getxml context="request"
          path="/querystring"/&gt;</em></p>
        <p>The result will be a string in the format
          "?param=aaa&amp;...".</p>
        <p>The complete context you can access via these commands has the
          following XML format:</p>
        <source>&lt;parameter&gt;
  &lt;!-- All parameters: parameter names build the elements with the value of the first parameter with
                          this name as text node child --&gt;
  &lt;firstparameter&gt;value of parameter&lt;/firstparameter&gt;
  &lt;secondparameter&gt;value of parameter&lt;/secondparameter&gt;
&lt;/parameter&gt;

&lt;querystring&gt;the querystring with a leading '?' or empty&lt;querystring&gt;
  (The querystring contains only parameters send by the GET method)

&lt;parametervalues&gt;
  &lt;!-- All parameters. The tags are all inside the cinclude transformer namespace.
    The generated XML can be used without modification for the
    cinclude:includexml command. --&gt;
  &lt;cinclude:parameters&gt;
    &lt;cinclude:parameter&gt;
      &lt;cinclude:name&gt;1st parameter name&lt;/cinclude:name&gt;
      &lt;cinclude:value&gt;1st parameter value&lt;/cinclude:value&gt;
    &lt;/cinclude:parameter&gt;
             ...
    &lt;cinclude:parameter&gt;
      &lt;cinclude:name&gt;2nd parameter name&lt;/cinclude:name&gt;
      &lt;cinclude:value&gt;2nd parameter value&lt;/cinclude:value&gt;
    &lt;/cinclude:parameter&gt;
  &lt;/cinclude:parameters&gt;
  &lt;!-- If a parameter has more than one value, for each value a
      &lt;session:param&gt; block is generated. --&gt;
&lt;/parametervalues&gt;

&lt;attributes&gt;
  &lt;!-- lists all attributes, attribute names build the elements
        with the values as text node childs --&gt;
&lt;/attributes&gt;

&lt;headers&gt;
  &lt;!-- lists all headers, header names build the elements
       with the values as text node childs --&gt;
&lt;/headers&gt;

&lt;cookies&gt;
  &lt;!-- lists all cookies --&gt;
  &lt;cookie name="..."&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;the cookie value&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;the name of the cookie&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;comment&gt;value&lt;/comment&gt;
    &lt;domain&gt;value&lt;/domain&gt;
    &lt;path&gt;value&lt;/path&gt;
    &lt;maxAge&gt;value&lt;/maxAge&gt;
    &lt;secure&gt;value&lt;/secure&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;value&lt;/version&gt;
  &lt;/cookie&gt;
&lt;/cookies&gt;

&lt;characterEncoding&gt;value&lt;/characterEncoding&gt;
&lt;contentLength&gt;value&lt;/contentLength&gt;
&lt;contentType&gt;value&lt;/contentType&gt;
&lt;protocol&gt;value&lt;/protocol&gt;
&lt;remoteAddress&gt;value&lt;/remoteAddress&gt;
&lt;remoteHost&gt;value&lt;/remoteHost&gt;
&lt;scheme&gt;value&lt;/scheme&gt;
&lt;serverName&gt;value&lt;/serverName&gt;
&lt;serverPort&gt;value&lt;/serverPort&gt;
&lt;method&gt;value&lt;/method&gt;
&lt;contextPath&gt;value&lt;/contextPath&gt;
&lt;pathInfo&gt;value&lt;/pathInfo&gt;
&lt;pathTranslated&gt;value&lt;/pathTranslated&gt;
&lt;remoteUser&gt;value&lt;/remoteUser&gt;
&lt;requestedSessionId&gt;value&lt;/requestedSessionId&gt;
&lt;requestURI&gt;value&lt;/requestURI&gt;
&lt;servletPath&gt;value&lt;/servletPath&gt;
&lt;isRequestedSessionIdFromCookie&gt;value&lt;/isRequestedSessionIdFromCookie&gt;
&lt;isRequestedSessionIdFromCookie&gt;value&lt;/isRequestedSessionIdFromCookie&gt;
&lt;isRequestedSessionIdValid&gt;value&lt;/isRequestedSessionIdValid&gt;</source>
     </s2>
     <s2 title="The Response Context - Accessing the Environment, Part Two">
        <p>The response context is an XML description of the current
          (HTTP) response. This context is a special write only context that can be
          accessed with the usual commands:</p>
        <p><em>&lt;session:setxml context="response"
          path="/header"/&gt;</em></p>
        <p>This command will be removed from the XML and the information will
          be added to the response. Headers and cookies can be
          added using the response context .</p>
        <s3 title="Adding headers">
          <p>Headers can be added either by <em>setxml</em> or by
             <em>appendxml</em>. If <em>setxml</em> is used, the header with the name gets
             the given value, regardless if the header had any value beforehand or not. If
             <em>appendxml</em> is used the value will be added.</p>
          <source>&lt;session:setxml context="response" path="/header/headername"&gt;The value&lt;/session:setxml&gt;

   or

&lt;session:appendxml context="response" path="/header/headername"&gt;The value&lt;/session:appendxml&gt;</source>
        </s3>
        <s3 title="Adding cookies">
          <p>Cookies can be added either by setxml or by appendxml. There is
             no difference between these commands.</p>
          <source>&lt;session:setxml context="response" path="/cookie"&gt;
  &lt;!-- Now follows the cookie definition --&gt;
  &lt;name&gt;The cookie name&lt;/name&gt;
  &lt;value&gt;The value of the cookie&lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;!-- The following are optional --&gt;
  &lt;path&gt;value&lt;/path&gt;
  &lt;domain&gt;value&lt;/domain&gt;
  &lt;secure&gt;true or false&lt;/secure&gt;
  &lt;comment&gt;value&lt;/comment&gt;
  &lt;maxAge&gt;value&lt;/maxAge&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;value&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/session:setxml&gt;</source>
        </s3>
     </s2>
     <s2 title="The Temporary Context">
        <p>The temporary context with the name <em>"temp"</em> is available on
          each request. It is independent from the session and has no content when a new
          request starts. It can be used like any other context except that the content
          is lost/deleted when the current response is finished.</p>
        <p>Using the tempory context it is possible to store any XML
          information for processing the current request.</p>
     </s2>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Form Handling">
     <p>To get feedback or information from a user, forms are commonly used
        to present input field in the browser. The usual approach for form handling in
        web application consists of two steps. The first request presents the form to
        the user. This form initiates a second request that processes the form
        values.</p>
     <p>Cocoon supports this two step process, in addition Cocoon offers
        a single step approach.</p>
     <s2 title="The common approach">
        <p>The common approach consists of two steps or of creating two
          resources. The first resource defines the form: All input fields are declared,
          each gets a unique name. This form invokes the second resource.</p>
        <p>This resource uses the session transformer to get the values
          provided by the user. The values are added by the browser to the parameters of
          the request. So using the request context and <em>getxml</em>, the values can
          be fetched.</p>
        <p>If you want to create a form with two values - forename and surname
          of the user, you could generate a base xml file with the information about this
          form:</p>
        <source>&lt;page&gt;
  &lt;form&gt;
    &lt;action&gt;form-handling-page&lt;/action&gt;
    &lt;input name="forename" type="text"/&gt;
    &lt;input name="surname" type="text"/&gt;
  &lt;/form&gt;
&lt;/page&gt;</source>
        <p>A stylesheet can transform this into valid html. The action tag
          indicates that the "form-handling-page" should be invoked by submitting the
          values.</p>
        <p>The "form-handling-page" is a pipeline which is declared in the
          sitemap and uses the session transformer. It could also read the following
          xml:</p>
        <source>&lt;page xmlns:session="http://apache.org/cocoon/session/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;forename&gt;
    &lt;session:getxml context="request" path="/parameter/forename"/&gt;
  &lt;/forename&gt;
  &lt;surname&gt;
    &lt;session:getxml context="request" path="/parameter/surname"/&gt;
  &lt;/surname&gt;
&lt;/page&gt;</source>
        <p>As the form values are appended to the request, <em>getxml</em>
          with specifying the path (which is the parameter name used for the input field)
          inserts the value submitted by the user into the xml stream.</p>
        <p>If you want to write the information in a session context, you must
          wrap the whole xml inside a setxml:</p>
        <source>&lt;page xmlns:session="http://apache.org/cocoon/session/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;session:setxml context="userdata" path="/user"&gt;
    &lt;forename&gt;
      &lt;session:getxml context="request" path="/parameter/forename"/&gt;
    &lt;/forename&gt;
    &lt;surname&gt;
      &lt;session:getxml context="request" path="/parameter/surname"/&gt;
    &lt;/surname&gt;
  &lt;/session:setxml&gt;
&lt;/page&gt;</source>
        <p>The user data is now stored inside the session context "userdata",
          so the context has the following content:</p>
        <source>&lt;user&gt;
  &lt;forename&gt;Walter&lt;/forename&gt;
  &lt;surname&gt;Walterson&lt;/surname&gt;
&lt;/user&gt;</source>
     </s2>
     <s2 title="The Session Framework approach">
        <p>The previous chapter showed the common approach for handling form
          values. It forces the user to create two resources for a single form
          handling.</p>
        <p>Cocoon offers an advanced approach. Only one single resource is
          created. This resources contains the information about the input fields used
          and in addition the information about where the submitted values should be
          stored inside the session.</p>
        <p>The example from the previous chapter could look like this:</p>
        <source>&lt;page xmlns:session="http://apache.org/cocoon/session/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;session:form name="myform"&gt;
    &lt;session:action&gt;the-next-page&lt;/session:action&gt;
    &lt;session:content&gt;
      &lt;session:inputxml name="forename" type="text" context="userdata" path="/user/forename"/&gt;
      &lt;session:inputxml name="surname" type="text" context="userdata" path="/user/surname"/&gt;
    &lt;/session:content&gt;
  &lt;/session:form&gt;
&lt;/page&gt;</source>
        <p>The form tag starts the form definition. The name attribute is
          required to distinct between different forms on the same page. The action tag
          defines the url invoked by the form and the content tag describes the content
          of the form: its input fields.</p>
        <p>The <em>inputxml</em> tag tells Cocoon that the following request
          contains form values which should be stored in the specified context under the
          given path. The session transformer transforms by removing the namespace and
          the context attribute:</p>
        <source>&lt;page xmlns:session="http://apache.org/cocoon/session/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;form action="the-next-page"&gt;
    &lt;inputxml name="forename" type="text"/&gt;
    &lt;inputxml name="surname" type="text"/&gt;
  &lt;/form&gt;
&lt;/page&gt;</source>
        <p>A stylesheet can now generate the appropriate html (or any other
          format). The main difference is, that the resource invoked by submitting the
          values has not to care about the form as Cocoon maintains the form handling.
          The only prerequisit is that a session for the current user and a session
          context to store the information exists.</p>
        <p>The Cocoon approach allows a very easy way of form handling where
          the resource which creates the form also handles the form.</p>
        <p>For editing values - if the context already contains information
          about the user - <em>inputxml</em> inserts the current value inside the tag. So
          the xml streamed would after a second run would look like this:</p>
        <source>&lt;page xmlns:session="http://apache.org/cocoon/session/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;form action="the-next-page"&gt;
    &lt;inputxml name="forename" type="text"&gt;Walter&lt;/inputxml&gt;
    &lt;inputxml name="surname" type="text"&gt;Walterson&lt;/inputxml&gt;
  &lt;/form&gt;
&lt;/page&gt;</source>
        <p>Like <em>getxml</em> it is also possible to provide default values
          for the input field, if the context does not contain any information:</p>
        <source>&lt;session:inputxml name="forename" context="userdata" path="/user/forename"&gt;
     Defaultname
&lt;/session:inputxml&gt;</source>
     </s2>
  </s1>
</body>
</document>
