<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<page
    xmlns:cinclude="http://apache.org/cocoon/include/1.0"
>
    <content>
        <p>
            At this point, our application allows us to navigate in
            our TaskBean objects, and we're ready to start editing them.
        </p>
        <p>
            To take advantage of the Cocoon Forms editing features, we need the
            following:
            <ul>
                <li>
                    A pipeline to call the Flowscript <em>handleForm()</em> function
                    (provided by the Cocoon Forms Flowscript library, <em>Form.js</em>)
                    with the appropriate parameters.
                </li>
                <li>
                    A <em>Form Model</em> file, to define the data model
                    of our form.
                </li>
                <li>
                    A <em>Form Template</em> file, to define the layout
                    of our form while letting Cocoon Forms create the appropriate
                    HTML elements to edit our <em>form widgets</em>.
                </li>
                <li>
                    A <em>Form Binding</em> file, to define a
                    mapping between the Form data model and our Java beans.
                </li>
            </ul>
            This seems a lot of work when described in this way, but notice
            once again how modular things are: each "concern" of our bean editor
            is cleary defined in its own place.
        </p>
        <p>
            Note also that, while our example uses static XML files for these
            definitions, nothing prevents you from generating them dynamically
            using pipelines and the <em>cocoon:/</em> protocol. If your application
            provides a central data dictionary, for example, it would be possible
            to generate at least simple versions of the required definition files
            automatically.
        </p>
        <h2>Sitemap</h2>
        <p>
            Let's look first at the pipeline definition for the
            <em>edit/singleTask</em> request:
            <cinclude:include element="xml-code" src="cocoon:/xml-element/bean-editor/sitemap.xmap/edit"/>
        </p>
        <p>
            What this does is to call the <em>handleForm()</em> function of the
            <em>Form.js</em> Flowscript library, telling it which of
            our own Flowscript function to call to edit the form, and indicating
            the locations of the <em>Form Model</em> (form-definition) and
            <em>Form Binding</em> documents.
        </p>
        <p>
            Later, the Flowscript function shown below will call this pipeline:
            <cinclude:include element="xml-code" src="cocoon:/xml-element/bean-editor/sitemap.xmap/showForm"/>
        </p>
        <p>
            Using the FormsTransformer to generate the appropriate HTML
            elements for our form's <em>widgets</em>.
        </p>

        <h2>Flowscript</h2>
        <p>
            Here's our Flowscript form editing function, called by
            the <em>handleForm</em> library function to edit our form:
            <pre class="code">
0027 // Edit a single TaskBean object using Cocoon Forms
0028 function singleTaskEditor(form) {
0029    id = cocoon.request.getParameter("taskId");
0030    bean = db.getTaskBeanById(id);

0032    form.load(bean);
0033    form.showForm("internal/show-form/singleTask");
0034    form.save(bean);
0035    displayTaskBean(id,bean);
0036 }
            </pre>
        </p>
        <p>
            Notice how simple and readable the code is - the magic happens
            behind the Cocoon Forms scenes, based on the Forms definitions
            shown below.
        </p>

        <h2>Form Model</h2>
        <p>Here's the definition of our Form Model.</p>
        <cinclude:include element="xml-code" src="cocoon:/xml-element/bean-editor/cocoon-app/forms/singleTaskFormModel.xml/form"/>
        <p>
            As you can see, the Forms subsystem uses <em>widgets</em>
            with <em>labels</em> and <em>datatypes</em> to define a Model.
        </p>
        <p>
            If you omit the <em>repeater</em> element above, this is a fairly simple
            data model which represents our form's data. The repeater is used to model
            the 1-N relationship between our TaskBean and TaskCommentBean objects.
        </p>
        <p>
            Strongly typed fields are an important features of Cocoon Forms,
            and provide many standard validation features which make our
            life easier.
        </p>
        <p>
            This model is independent from the way the form
            is going to look in HTML (or WML, or XUL, or whatever), and
            also independent of the internal structure of our java beans.
        </p>
        <p>
            Here we use constants for the widget labels (field names),
            but the i18n transformer could be added to our pipeline to
            easily generate views and forms in multiple languages.
        </p>

        <h2>Form Binding</h2>
        <cinclude:include element="xml-code" src="cocoon:/xml-element/bean-editor/cocoon-app/forms/singleTaskFormBinding.xml/form"/>
        <p>
            Here's the <em>binding</em> definition, which allows the Forms
            subsystem to automatically move data from our Form's internal model
            to our java beans.
        </p>
        <p>
            This looks simple enough: for example, we tell the Forms
            subsystem that the form's <em>taskId</em> field is mapped
            in readonly mode to the bean's <em>id</em> field.
        </p>
        <p>
            The data mapping is triggered by the Flowscript <em>form.load</em> and
            <em>form.save</em> calls shown above.
        </p>
        <p>
            For the <em>taskId</em> form field, the <em>readonly</em> flag
            makes the binding unidirectional,
            The value of the form field will not be copied to the bean
            when <em>form.save</em> is called.
        </p>

        <h2>Form Template</h2>
        <p>
            Here's the template used by the FormsTransformer, which is activated
            by the above sitemap excerpt.
        </p>
        <cinclude:include element="xml-code" src="cocoon:/xml-element/bean-editor/cocoon-app/forms/singleTaskFormTemplate.xml/page"/>
        <p>
            Based on the Form Model definition, The FormsTransformer replaces
            the &lt;ft:widget&gt; elements by the appropriate HTML input elements.
        </p>

        <h2>That's it!</h2>
        <p>
            Well, this time it certainly gets more complicated. But stand back and look
            at the code in the <em>bean-editor/cocoon-app</em> directory
            of this tour's files.
        </p>
        <p>
            You will hopefully notice that we've written little "code", actually
            almost only definitions but very little actual code. Yet, the editing application is
            robust, easy to use, and very adaptable to different presentations or output
            devices.
        </p>
        <p>
            Another important feature of the Cocoon Forms subsystem is its extensibility:
            a clean design makes it fairly easy to add custom java classes for custom formatting,
            validation and bindings.
        </p>
    </content>
</page>
