<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "./dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Making a Contribution to Cocoon</title>
  <authors>
   <person name="Robin Green" email="greenrd@hotmail.com"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>

 <s1 title="Introduction">
  <p>
   There are many ways of contributing to the Cocoon project. This document is mainly about
   contributing new or improved code and/or documentation, but we would also be glad to have
   extra help in any of the following areas:
  </p>
  <ul>
   <li>Answering questions on the <code>cocoon-users</code> mailing list - there is often a problem of
    having too many questioners and not enough experts to respond to all the questions.</li>
   <li>Testing Cocoon (especially its less-frequently-used features) on various configurations
    and reporting back.</li>
   <li>Debugging - producing reproducable test cases and/or finding causes of bugs (at the time of
    writing, some known bugs are informally listed on <connect href="todo.xml">To Do</connect>, but
    eventually a bug database should be made available on the Apache site).</li>
   <li>Specifying/analysing/designing new features for Cocoon 2 - and beyond. (If you wish to get involved
    with this, please join <code>cocoon-dev@xml.apache.org</code>, install and try out Cocoon 2
    and read some of the <link href="http://mail-archives.apache.org">mail archives</link>.
    You should have a strong "fluency" in XML technologies, Java and a basic understanding of
    the Cocoon 2 architecture - don't just say "it should have XYZ" without reading anything first -
    chances are, someone's already thought of that feature!)</li>
   <li>Packaging easy-to-install packages (such as RPMs) for the myriad of possible configurations out
    there. (The Cocoon project does not maintain anything but the basic <code>.zip</code> and
    <code>.tar.gz</code> packages, but anyone is welcome to build their own specific packages and
    announce them on <code>cocoon-users</code>)</li>
   <li>... and there is just one other thing - don't forget to tell everyone who asks how great Cocoon is! ;-)</li>
  </ul>

  <p></p>
 </s1>
</body>
</document>
