<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "document-v10.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Avalon for Apache Cocoon</title>
    <version>0.2</version>
    <type>Technical document</type>
    <authors>
      <person name="Tom Klaasen" email="tom.klaasen@pandora.be"/>
      <person name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org"/>
      <person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
    <abstract>This document tries to give the basic knowledge of Avalon that is
      necessary to understand Apache Cocoon.</abstract>
  </header>
  <body>
    <s1 title="Goal">
      <p>This document tries to provide you with the basic knowledge of Avalon
        that is necessary to understand Cocoon.</p>
      <p>People trying to understand Avalon in depth, will probably not be much
        helped by this document. But, if you want to understand Cocoon, you have
        to have a basic grasp of Avalon.</p>
      <p>The document also outlines the basic steps for configuring Avalon
        components within Cocoon.</p>
      <p>Much of this document is copied and pasted from original Avalon
        documentation. However, I hope that by putting all things relevant to
        Cocoon together in one place I can help you to understand Cocoon more
        quickly.</p>
      <p>For people wishing to learn Avalon in-depth,
        <link href="http://avalon.apache.org/developing/index.html">this
        is your starting point</link>.</p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Overview">
      <p>For a mission statement of Apache Avalon, please read
        <link href="http://avalon.apache.org/index.html">the Avalon
        homepage</link>.</p>
      <p>In short, Avalon tries to take design efforts away from server-side
        programmers by providing a framework that </p>
      <ul>
        <li>provides basic working classes;</li>
        <li>provides interfaces to allow different efforts to be integrated
          more easily.</li>
      </ul>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="The classes and interfaces">
      <p>These classes and interfaces are extensively used by Cocoon:</p>
      <s2 title="ServiceManager">
        <p>
          <code>org.apache.avalon.framework.service.ServiceManager</code>
        </p>
        <p>A <code>ServiceManager</code> selects <code>Component</code>s based
          on a role. The contract is that all the <code>Component</code>s
          implement the differing roles and there is one <code>Component</code>
          per role. If you need to select one of many <code>Component</code>s
          that implement the same role, then you need to use a
          <code>ServiceSelector</code>. Roles are the full interface name.</p>
        <p>To understand roles better let's use the the analogy of a play. There
          are many different roles in a script. Any actor or actress can play
          any given part and you get broadly the same results (same phrases
          spoken, same movements made, etc.), but with each actor the exact
          nuances of the performance are different.</p>
      </s2>
      <s2 title="ComponentManager (deprecated)">
        <p>
          <code>org.apache.avalon.framework.component.ComponentManager</code>
        </p>
        <p>This is the deprecated version of the <code>ServiceManager</code>. In
          some places this component is still used, but over time all the usages
          of this class will be replaced with the <code>ServiceManager</code>.</p>
      </s2>
      <s2 title="Serviceable">
        <p>
          <code>org.apache.avalon.framework.service.Serviceable</code>
        </p>
        <p>A <code>Serviceable</code> is a class that needs to connect to
          software components using a "role" abstraction, thus not depending on
          particular implementations but on behavioral interfaces. This means,
          if you need to use other components in your implementation, you
          have to implement <code>Serviceable</code> to be able to get other
          components.</p>
      </s2>
      <s2 title="Composable (deprecated)">
        <p>
          <code>org.apache.avalon.framework.component.Composable</code>
        </p>
        <p>This is the deprecated version of <code>Serviceable</code>.  In
          some places this component is still used, but over time all the usages
          of this class will be replaced with <code>Serviceable</code>.</p>
      </s2>
      <s2 title="Component">
        <p>
          <code>org.apache.avalon.framework.component.Component</code>
        </p>
        <p>This interface identifies classes that can be used as
          <code>Components</code> by a <code>Composable</code>.</p>
        <p>A <code>Component</code> is the basic building block of Avalon. When
          a class implements this interface, it allows itself to be managed by a
          <code>ComponentManager</code> and used by an outside element called a
          <code>Composable</code>. The <code>Composable</code> must know what
          type of <code>Component</code> it is accessing, so it will re-cast the
          <code>Component</code> into the type it needs.</p>
        <p>
          <code>Component</code>s in Cocoon are e.g. those defined in
          <code>cocoon.xconf</code>.
        </p>
        <note><code>Component</code> is only required in combination with
          <code>ComponentManager</code> and <code>Composable</code>. As these
          are still used in Cocoon, it's required to implement <code>Component</code>
          in order to work properly everywhere.</note>
      </s2>
      <s2 title="Configuration">
        <p>
          <code>org.apache.avalon.framework.configuration.Configuration</code>
        </p>
        <p>
          <code>Configuration</code> is an interface encapsulating a
          configuration node used to retrieve configuration values. This is a
          "read only" interface preventing applications from modifying their own
          configurations. The contract surrounding the
          <code>Configuration</code> is that once it is created, information
          never changes. The <code>Configuration</code> is built by the
          <code>ConfigurationBuilder</code>.
        </p>
      </s2>
      <s2 title="Configurable">
        <p>
          <code>org.apache.avalon.framework.configuration.Configurable</code>
        </p>
        <p>
          <code>Configurable</code> is an interface describing a component which
          can be configured. This component gets a <code>Configuration</code>
          object as input.</p>
      </s2>
      <s2 title="ConfigurationBuilder">
        <p>
          <code>org.apache.avalon.ConfigurationBuilder</code>
        </p>
        <p>A <code>ConfigurationBuilder</code> builds
          <code>Configuration</code>s.</p>
      </s2>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Configuration">
      <p>Most available Avalon components are configured in the cocoon.xconf.</p>
      <s2 title="Pooling configuration">
        <p>Avalon now incorporates a couple of modifiers for a Component
          definition that allows you to control the number of Components in a
          pool, and how quickly it grows.  This is especially helpful in Cocoon
          where the defaults don't always work well.</p>
        <p>The magic attributes are "pool-min", "pool-max", and "pool-grow".
          The defaults are:</p>
        <ol>
          <li>pool-max: 8</li>
          <li>pool-min: 2</li>
          <li>pool-grow: pool-min (2)</li>
        </ol>
        <p>What this means is that the pool for the default component initially
          contains 2 instances. If demand exceeds this then the pool will
          increase, two components at a time, up to 8 instances. Beyond that the
          pool turns into a factory.  That is, new <code>Component</code>
          instances are created, but destroyed when they are returned. This is a
          performance issue - but it does manage the number of instances
          available at one time.</p>
        <p>Please note that if not specified, "pool-grow" always matches
          "pool-min". If not specified "pool-min" always equals "2". If you
          specify the minimum to be higher than the maximum, then the maximum
          will match the minimum, and the pool will be completely filled on
          initialization.</p>
      </s2>
    </s1>
  </body>
</document>

