<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fancy-page-html.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="text-page-html.xsl" type="text/xsl" media="lynx"?>
<?cocoon-process type="xslt"?>

<page>

 <title>The Java Apache Project News</title>
 <author>Stefano Mazzocchi</author>
 <version>$Id: news-page.xml,v 1.1 1999-11-30 16:30:01 stefano Exp $</version>
  
 <newscolumn>
  <news>
   <title>Apache JServ User mail list reaches 500 subscribers!</title>
   <link>http://java.apache.org/</link>
   <date>8 Mar 1999</date>
   <content>
    The Apache JServ User mail list has offically reached 500 people subscribed.
    We would like to thank all of you for being around and for partecipating in 
    the making of such interesting projects. This incredible amount of brain 
    power is what makes us really proud, and we are looking forward to host
    more projects and more people to make what open source is all about: 
    learning, meeting people, challenging ourselves and have fun!
   </content>
  </news>
  <news>
   <title>Apache JMeter 1.1 released!</title>
   <link>../jmeter/dist/</link>
   <date>27 Feb 1999</date>
   <content>
    This new release enhances its testing capabilities adding the possibility 
    to test multiple URLs instead of a single one, to dump the collected 
    samples to a file and to use aliases instead of big URLs.
   </content>
  </news>
  <news>
   <title>Apache JServ 1.0b3 released!</title>
   <link>../jserv/index.html</link>
   <date>19 Feb 1999</date>
   <content>
    A new release of Apache JServ is out. Please see the change notes for 
    more information.
   </content>
  </news>
  <news>
   <title>Java Apache Server Framework project started</title>
   <link>../framework/index.html</link>
   <date>1 Feb 1999</date>
   <content>
    A new project is started to design, implement and control the Java 
    Apache Server Framework, a modular and highly flexible common ground for 
    Java server projects. Based on latest software engineering technologies 
    and design patterns, this framework will allow different projects to share
    functional blocks of code as well as creating a standard environment for 
    configuration, deployment, installation and control. Everyone, even from 
    other projects, is welcome to partecipate in its development.
   </content>
  </news>
 </newscolumn>
 
 <statuscolumn>
 
  <project>
   <title>Apache JServ</title>
   <link>../jserv/index.html</link>
   
   <release>
    <version>1.0b3</version>
    <status type="available">Released</status>
    <comment>
     This new generation comes with: complete Servlet 2.0 compliance, 
     enhanced security, improved installation and documentation, performance
     improvements, tons of bug fixes, and much more.
    </comment>
   </release>
   
   <release>
    <version>0.9.12</version>
    <status type="available">Released</status>
    <comment>
     It offers some new experimental features (including load balancing), 
     performance improvements, and bug fixes, for those who want to upgrade 
     from JServ 0.9.x, without changing to the 1.0 tree (yet). 
     In the long term, the 0.9.x tree will probably be discontinued.
    </comment>
   </release>
 
  </project>
 
  <project>
   <title>Apache JServSSI</title>
   <link>../jservssi/index.html</link>
   
   <release>
    <version>1.0</version>
    <status type="available">Released</status>
    <comment>
     The servlet server side include servlet once contained into the Apache 
     JServ servlet engine has been moved in a separate project to allow 
     independent release cycles.
    </comment>
   </release>
  </project>
 
  <project>
   <title>Apache JMeter</title>
   <link>../jmeter/index.html</link>
   
   <release>
    <version>1.1</version>
    <status type="available">Released</status>
    <comment>
     The 100% pure, swing enabled, Java URL profiler/analyser to test your 
     server performance, your servlet performance, to stress your servlets 
     with heavy multi-threading concurrent requests and much more...
    </comment>
   </release>
  </project>  
 </statuscolumn>
 
 <legal>
  Sun, Sun Microsystems, Solaris, Java, JavaSoft, are trademarks or registered 
  trademarks of Sun Microsystems, Inc. UNIX is a registered 
  trademark in the United States and other countries, exclusively licensed 
  through X/Open Company, Ltd. Windows, WinNT and Win32 are registered trademark 
  of Microsoft Corp. All other product names mentioned herein and throughout 
  the entire web site are trademarks of their respective owners.
 </legal>
 
</page>