<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "dtd/document-v10.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>News about Cocoon</title>
    <subtitle></subtitle>
    <authors>
      <person name="Diana Shannon" email="shannon@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
  <s1 title="Wiki Moving">
    <p>The popular Cocoon Wiki has moved: <link href="http://wiki.cocoondev.org/">http://wiki.cocoondev.org/</link> is the new place to be.</p>
  </s1>
<s1 title="Cocoon GetTogether">
 <p>Outerthought is organizing the <link href="http://outerthought.org/cocoon/gettogether/">Cocoon GetTogether</link> on 19 November 2002 (near Ghent in Belgium).</p>
</s1>
    <s1 title="Cocoon: Building XML Applications Published">
  <p><strong>July 2002</strong> New Riders has just published <em>Cocoon: Building XML Applications</em> written by our very own Carsten Ziegeler, release coordinator for the Cocoon project, and Matthew Langham, leader of the open-source group at S&#38;N AG of Paderborn, Germany. You can download several <link href="http://www.newriders.com/books/product.asp?product_id={C3C05052-BE3B-4E06-A60A-13FB40AF58F6}" >free chapters</link> at the New Riders web site. Weighing in at over 500 pages, the book is a vital new resource for the Cocoon community. We congratulate and thank Carsten, Matthew, and New Riders for their excellent work!
  </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Cocoon Wikis">
  <p>
Cocoon has two promising and complementary wiki efforts underway. 
  </p>
    <ul>
  <li>
<link href="http://wiki.cocoondev.org/">Cocoon Wiki</link> focuses on content development for the Cocoon project. It is designed to facilitate document development and collaboration from all levels of Cocoon users. Documents include FAQs, snippets, how-tos, tutorials, RTs (random thoughts), dreams, surveys, and more. The preliminary focus of this the wiki is to serve as a documentation "breeding ground," where docs can "grow" until mature enough to become official cvs docs. However, it already represents a lively and valid document resource in its own right.
  </li>
  <li>
<link href="http://www.anyware-tech.com/wikiland/">Wikiland</link> is an ongoing development effort to build a Cocoon-based wiki architecture. Wikiland features a Cocoon dictionary as the pretext to use, test and develop the wiki. The project is seeking Cocoon-oriented developers to further its development. For more information, see the <link href="http://rossel.free.fr/" >Wikiland home page.</link>
  </li>
</ul>
</s1>
  </body>
</document>
