<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "document-v10.dtd">

<document>

  <header>
    <title>Database Access</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Christian Haul" email="haul@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>

<body>

	<s1 title="Introduction">
	  <p>
		Publishing dynamic content or creating web-applications 
		eventually involves database access. Apache Cocoon
		offers a number of different approaches to access
		(object) relational and XML databases. This document provides
		an overview of the different ways to access (object)
		relational databases.
	  </p>
	  <p>
		This document will not explain how to set up database
		connectivity with Apache Cocoon. For this, see <link
		  href="../../developing/datasources.html">here.</link>
	  </p>
	  <p>
		Basically, there are three different approaches available:
		<link href="actions.html">Actions,</link> <link
		  href="../xsp/logicsheet-concepts.html">logicsheets,</link>
		and <link href="sitemap.html">transformers.</link> Each approach has
		its pros and cons. 
	  </p>
	</s1>

	<s1 title="Actions Approach">
	  <p>
		<link href="actions.html">Actions</link> are code to be executed
		during pipeline setup. The outcome of an action can change how a pipeline is
		assembled. For example, a pipeline may produce an alternative
		page to display upon failure of a particular database operation.
	  </p>
	  <p>
		Actions are especially great for inserting, changing, or deleting data. 
		Employing the pipeline-switching features of actions will simplify your 
		pages. Such actions are concerned with only one view: either the success
		or failure of an operation.
	  </p>
	  <p>
		Actions can be useful, even when data is not provided by users.
		For example, you could store tracking information in a database in
		a central location without the need to modify every page.
	  </p>
	  <p>
		Database actions can read and return data from a database. This is
		useful when the pipeline assembly depends upon such data. It's also
		useful when setting up an environment for XSP processing.
	  </p>
	  <p>
		Once the database meta data is captured in an XML descriptor file, 
		making use of these actions is simply a matter of placing them in a pipeline. 
		This is a major advantage of the action approach. No programming is
		required, not even SQL query writing.
	  </p>
	  <p>
		For more detailed information, read:  <link
		  href="../actions/database-actions.html">Database Actions</link>.
	  </p>
	</s1>

	<s1 title="ESQL Logicsheet Approach">
	  <p>
		The use of logicsheets is limited to XSPs. ESQL is currently available
		for Java-based XSPs. Its interface is modeled largely on
		JDBC. Thus, it is advantageous to be familiar with JDBC.
	  </p>
	  <p>
		ESQL is great when reading data from a database. However, it is less attractive
		to use when it has to react to operation failures. This is due to the fact
		that it adds a layer of complexity to an XSP file, making it
		more difficult to understand and maintain.
	  </p>
	  <p>
		Complex layouts of the data are easy to achieve. ESQL allows
		the arbitrary nesting of queries and connections. It also provides support for
		stored procedures and complex data types. ESQL provides a means to 
		create a structured representation of the database data with a single tag. 
		This is useful when generating reports to use
		with other XML-aware software or to be formated with XSL or CSS2.
		XML data can be retrieved from the
		database and included in the output. With some supported database
		management systems, ESQL supports skipping part of the
		resultset as well as limiting the result. 
		Given the full power of Java available within XSP,
		any processing of the data is possible. 
	  </p>
	  <p>
		For more detailed information, read:  <link
		  href="../xsp/esql.html">ESQL Taglib</link>.
	  </p>
	</s1>

	<s1 title="SQL Transformer Approach">
	  <p>
		An approach using the SQL transformer can be combined with any kind
		of page. This will result in slightly cleaner pages as you don't need
		some of the setup that an ESQL approach requires.
	  </p>
	  <p>
		On the other hand, it is more or less impossible to react to operation
		failures. This is due to the fact that the pipeline is already assembled 
		and the necessary logic to handle such failures is not
		available inside the SQL transformer, unless of course, you are willing
		to write a custom transformer.
		Thus, the transformer approach is best for retrieving data. Creating
		an XML representation of the query result is even simpler than when
		using the ESQL logicsheet. The transformer also supports stored procedures.
		No programming is required, apart from writing SQL.
	  </p>
	  <p>
		For more detailed information, read: <link
		  href="../transformers/sql-transformer.html">SQL Transformer</link>.
	  </p>
	</s1>

</body>
</document>
