<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <!-- This document will be enhanced by information taken from the javadoc -->
  <header>
    <title>Directory Generator</title>
    <version>1.0</version>
    <type>Technical document</type>
    <authors>
      <person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org"/>
      <person name="Frank Ridderbusch" email="frank.ridderbusch@gmx.de"/>
      <person name="John Morrison" email="morrijr@apache.org"/>
      <person name="Jörg Heinicke" email="joerg@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
    <abstract>This document describes the Directory Generator of Cocoon.</abstract>
  </header>
  <body>
    <s1 title="Directory Generator">
      <p>The root node of the generated document will normally be a <code>directory</code> node. A
          directory node can contain zero or more <code>file</code> or <code>directory</code> nodes.
          A file node has no children. All generated elements have the namespace
          <code>http://apache.org/cocoon/directory/2.0</code>.
      </p>
      <p>Each node will contain the following attributes:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><code>name</code>: the name of the file or directory.</li>
        <li><code>lastModified</code>: the time the file was last modified, measured as the number
            of milliseconds since the epoch (as in <code>java.io.File.lastModified</code>).</li>
        <li><code>date</code> (optional): the time the file was last modified in human-readable form.</li>
        <li><code>size</code>: the file size (or 0 for directories).</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Additionally the node for the requested directory has the attributes:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><code>requested</code>: with the value set to <code>true</code>.</li>
        <li><code>sort</code>: the sort order of the <code>file</code> and <code>directory</code>
                               nodes.</li>
        <li><code>reverse</code>: determines whether reverse sort was chosen.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>This node needs not to be the root node as you will see later.</p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Configuration">
      <source><![CDATA[
  <map:generate type="directory" src="the/requested/directory">
    <map:parameter name="depth" value="2"/>
  </map:generate>
      ]]></source>
      <p>The <code>src</code> attribute on the <code>&lt;map:generate/></code> must be set to the
          directory the XML listing should be created of. This is the <em>requested</em> directory.
      </p>
      <p>The following parameter are all optional and can be specified in the pipeline for the
          generate command (as seen in the example above for the parameter <code>depth</code>):
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>depth: Sets how deep the generator should delve into the directory structure. If
            set to 1 (the default), only the starting directory's immediate contents will be
            returned.</li>
        <li>dateFormat: Sets the format for the date attribute of each node as described in
            <code>java.text.SimpleDateFormat</code>. If unset, the default format for the current
            locale will be used.</li>
        <li>refreshDelay: Sets the delay (in seconds, default is 1) between checks for updates on
            the file system. So this option influences the caching of the directory listing.</li>
        <li>sort: Sets the sort order in which the <code>file</code> and <code>directory</code>
            nodes are returned. Possible values are <code>name</code>, <code>size</code>,
            <code>time</code> and <code>directory</code> (where <code>directory</code> is the same
            as <code>name</code>, except that directory entries are listed first). The default sort
            order is <code>name</code>.</li>
        <li>reverse: Reverses the sort order, defaults to <code>false</code>.</li>
        <li>root: The root pattern. From the requested director upwards a directory is searched
            using this pattern, that is added as root node to the document. The path from this root
            node down to the requested directory will also be in the output. If no root pattern is
            specified or no ancestor of the requested directory matches this pattern, the requested
            directory will be the root in the output document.<br/>
            The pattern is a regular expression as described in the API docs of the
            <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/regexp/apidocs/org/apache/regexp/RE.html">
            Apache RegExp project</link>.</li>
        <li>include: The include pattern. Specifies the directories and files that should be
            included. Also a regular expression.</li>
        <li>exclude: The exclude pattern. Specifies the directories and files that should be
            excluded. Also a regular expression.</li>
      </ul>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="DTD">
      <p>XML generated by Directory Generator uses namespace
          <code>http://apache.org/cocoon/status/2.0</code>. The DTD of XML generated by Directory
          Generator:
      </p>
      <source><![CDATA[
  <!ELEMENT directory (directory|file)*>
  <!ATTLIST directory
    name         CDATA #REQUIRED
    lastModified CDATA #REQUIRED
    date         CDATA #REQUIRED
    size         CDATA #REQUIRED
    requested    CDATA #IMPLIED
    sort         CDATA #IMPLIED
    reverse      CDATA #IMPLIED>

  <!ELEMENT file #EMPTY>
  <!ATTLIST file
    name         CDATA #REQUIRED
    lastModified CDATA #REQUIRED
    date         CDATA #REQUIRED
    size         CDATA #REQUIRED>
      ]]></source>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Example">
      <p>The current Directory Generator may generate following xml:</p>
      <source><![CDATA[
<dir:directory xmlns:dir="http://apache.org/cocoon/directory/2.0"
    name="stylesheets" lastModified="1056668768203" date="27.06.03 01:06" size="0"
    requested="true" sort="name" reverse="false">
  <dir:directory name="sites" lastModified="1056668768203" date="27.06.03 01:06" size="0"/>
  <dir:file name="dynamic-page2html.xsl" lastModified="1056668768203" date="27.06.03 01:06" size="4321"/>
  <dir:file name="simple-xml2html.xslt" lastModified="1056668768203" date="27.06.03 01:06" size="1234"/>
</dir:directory>
      ]]></source>
    </s1>
  </body>
</document>
