<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "dtd/document-v10.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Apache Cocoon User Guide</title>
    <subtitle>First Steps track</subtitle>
    <authors>
      <person name="Bertrand Delacr&#233;taz" email="bdelacretaz@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
     <s1 title="What's in this track?">
       <p>This track is meant to help you take your first steps with Cocoon, by running
           and exploring the samples.</p>
      </s1>
      <s1 title="Prerequisites">
        <p>You will need a JDK (Java Development Kit) installed on your computer,
            and (obviously) an Internet connection to download Cocoon.</p>
          <p>No prior knowledge of Cocoon is needed to study this track.</p>
       </s1>
      <s1 title="First Steps Track">
          <p>
              Here's our suggestion for your first steps with Cocoon:
          </p>
          <s2 title="Have a look at the samples">
              <p>
                  Start by reading
                  <link href="../howto/howto-explore-samples.html">How to run and explore the Cocoon samples</link>
                  and taking a first look at the Cocoon samples. At this point you might not understand much about how they work,
                  but this will give you a feel of what Cocoon is about.
              </p>
          </s2>
          <s2 title="Study the pipeline and sitemap concepts">
            <p>
                  Next, we suggest that you study the <link href="../userdocs/index.html">basics</link> to find
                  out more about how Cocoon works. You should concentrate on understanding the <em>pipeline</em> and <em>sitemap</em>
                  concepts, you don't need much more at this point.
              </p>
          </s2>
          <s2 title="Study selected samples in more detail">
              <p>
                  Once you understand a bit more about how Cocoon works, we suggest that you go back
                  to a few selected samples that might be of interest to you, to study them in more detail.
              </p>
          </s2>
          <p>
              Going through several iterations of looking at the samples and studying the corresponding
              documentation will help you focus on what you need to understand about Cocoon.
          </p>
          <p>
              With more than 45 blocks as of this writing, the samples
              use a wide variety of tools and
              technologies, and attempting to understand everything will most probably leave you frustrated, so
              it is better to limit yourself to a subset of the samples.
          </p>
              <note>
                  <em>Blocks</em> are components which are largely independent of each other, and which are
                  optional when installing Cocoon.
              </note>
       </s1>
      <s1 title="Comments">
        <p>
            Care to comment on this Track?
            Help keep this document relevant by passing along any constructive feedback to the
            <link href="mailto:docs@cocoon.apache.org?subject=first-steps-track:">cocoon-docs</link>
            mailing list.
        </p>
      </s1>
  </body>
</document>
