<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE faqs PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD FAQ V1.0//EN" "../dtd/faq-v10.dtd">

<faqs title="Sitemap FAQs">


<faq>
  <question>
    What are the steps to pre-compile the sitemap and XSP's?
  </question>
  <answer>
    <ul>
      <li>Set the auto-reload to false in your sitemap.xmap as follows:</li>
    </ul>

    <source><![CDATA[
<parameter name="auto-reload" value="false"/>
]]></source>

    <ul>
      <li>Use "-Dbuild.precompile=true" in your build command line when you are
        building your WAR file.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
 <question>I don't want to hand edit the sitemap.  Are there any
   tools?</question>
 <answer>
   <p>Try <fork href="http://pollo.sourceforge.net/">this</fork>
     by Bruno Dumon.</p>
 </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
 <question>How do I create some content which isn't directly visible to
   everyone?</question>
 <answer>
   <p>Put the content in an internal pipeline...</p>

   <source><![CDATA[
<map:pipelines>
 <map:pipeline internal-only="true">
   <map:match pattern="int">
     <map:generate src="docs/description.xml"/>
     <map:serialize type="xml"/>
   </map:match>
 </map:pipeline>
 <map:pipeline>
   <map:match pattern="desc.html">
     <map:generate src="cocoon:/int"/>
     <map:transform src="stylesheets/description2html.xsl"/>
     <map:serialize type="html"/>
   </map:match>
 </map:pipeline>
</map:pipelines>
]]></source>

 </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
 <question>How can I concatenate two xml files?</question>
 <answer>
   <source><![CDATA[
<map:pipelines>
 <map:pipeline internal-only="true">
   <map:match pattern="one">
     <map:generate src="docs/one.xml"/>
     <map:serialize type="xml"/>
   </map:match>
   <map:match pattern="two">
     <map:generate src="docs/two.xml"/>
     <map:serialize type="xml"/>
   </map:match>
 </map:pipeline>
 <map:pipeline>
   <map:match pattern="desc.html">
     <map:aggregate element="newRootElement">
       <map:part src="cocoon:/one" element="firstXMLfile"/>
       <map:part src="cocoon:/two" element="secondXMLfile"/>
     </map:aggregate>
     <map:transform src="stylesheets/merge2html.xsl"/>
     <map:serialize type="html"/>
   </map:match>
 </map:pipeline>
</map:pipelines>
]]></source>

   <p>Where the element attribute names are replaced with something more
     meaningful!  Note that the map:part element attributes can be left off,
     which results in the two parts being placed one immediately after the
     other.</p>
 </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
 <question>I want to use the XXX matcher/serializer/selecter/etc but there's no
   examples :(</question>
 <answer>
   <p>If you've checked the sample webapps which come with Cocoon, and you've
     looked in the documentation, then check both the user and
     dev archives.  If it hasn't been resolved before <strong>first</strong>
     email the user group and, after a <strong>reasonable</strong> (ie 1 or 2
     days) length of time (remember not everyone lives in your timezone) email
     the dev group.</p>
   <p>Please don't cross-post to both the user and dev groups - very few people
     like getting bombarded!</p>
   <p>Oh, and once you do get it working - how about documenting it and
     contributing it back to the group?</p>
 </answer>
</faq>



<faq>
  <question>
    I changed the sitemap, but my changes don't show in the browser.
    Do I need to restart the servlet container?
  </question>
  <answer>
    <p>Cocoon lets you decide whether it needs to poll for sitemap changes
    (with its associated performance penalty) or not. It also lets you decide whether the re-compilation resulting from polling shoud happen in the
    background or in the foreground.</p>

    <p>If you look at the cocoon.xconf file, you'll notice this element:</p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<sitemap file="sitemap.xmap"
         reload-method="asynchron"
         check-reload="yes"/>]]></source>

    <p>Which means:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>The <code>check-reload</code> attribute determines if the sitemap
        is reloaded on change. Set to "no", the sitemap is generated once
        at startup. Set to "yes", the sitemap is regenerated if it changes.</li>
        <li>The <code>reload-method</code> specifies the method for the
          regeneration:
          <ol>
            <li><code>asynchron</code>: If the sitemap changes, the sitemap is
            regenerated at the next request in the background and the incoming
            request is served with the old sitemap. All subsequent requests
            are served with the old sitemap until the regeneration in the
            background has finished.</li>
            <li><code>synchron</code>: If the sitemap changes, the sitemap
            is regenerated at the next request. When the regeneration is
            finished, the request (and all subsequent ones) is served with
            the new sitemap.</li>
          </ol>
        </li>
      </ul>
    <p>
      For a development environment, set the reload-method to "synchron" and the
      check-reload to "yes." For a production environment, 
      set the reload-method to "asynchron." For more safety, set the check-reload
      to "no."
    </p>

    <p>In a nutshell: By default, reload is "asynchron" which means:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Change sitemap</li>
        <li>Hit reload</li>
        <li>Wait while CPU goes up to 100% and back down to 0%</li>
        <li>Hit reload</li>
        <li>Voila - new sitemap is used! :)</li>
      </ol>
    <p>Hence: you don't need to restart the servlet container.</p>

    <p>For sub-sitemaps, this issue is defined in the mounting element:</p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<map:mount uri-prefix="foo" src="file:///c:/foo/"
           check-reload="yes"
           reload-method="synchron"/>]]></source>
    <p>With these settings Cocoon will react to any changes in the sub-sitemap,
      without even hitting the reload button twice. :)</p>
    <p>
      Moreover, it is a good idea to use sub-sitemaps because they reduce
      overall compilation time. For example, changes to a single sub-sitemap won't 
      require recompilation for the the main sitemap or other sub-sitemaps. This
      practice leads to greater degree of modularity.
    </p>
  </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
  <question>When I add an action to a pipeline Cocoon returns an
  error.</question>
  <answer>
  <p>Before the action was added to the pipeline it worked fine. After
  the change Cocoon seems not to find the file specified in the
  variable that is returned by the matcher.</p>

<source><![CDATA[
<map:match pattern="*">
  <map:act type="validate-session">
    <map:generate type="serverpages" src="{../1}.xsp"/>
  </map:act>
  <map:serialize/>
</map:match>
]]></source>

  <p>Please note in the above example the
  "<strong><code>../1</code></strong>".</p> 
  <p>Map objects returned from matchers, actions etc. are organised
  <em>hierarchically</em>. Therefore they are not replaced by new ones
  but older ones are still accessible through a path expression. Here
  "<code>../1</code>" references key ("variable") "1" in the next to
  last Map. </p>
  </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
  <question>
    What is the syntax for absolute filesystem pathnames.
  </question>
  <answer>
   <p>
    In your sitemaps you may need to refer to some resource that is outside
    the webapp context (e.g. UNIX /foo/bar/this.xsl
    e.g. Windows C:\foo\bar\this.xsl). You need to use the file: convention.
   </p>
   <ul>
    <li>UNIX ... <code>file:///foo/bar/this.xsl</code></li>
    <li>Windows ... <code>file:///C:/foo/bar/this.xsl</code></li>
   </ul>
   <p>
    See further explanation of
    <link href="../userdocs/concepts/sitemap.html#file-url">file: URLs</link>
   </p>
  </answer>
</faq>

<faq>
  <question>
What's the difference between having two pipelines with one matcher 
each, and one pipeline with two matchers?
  </question>
  <answer>
   <p>
If there is no other difference in pipeline declarations, then none, really. Note that pipelines can differ by:
  </p>
<ul>
	<li>
visibility: internal-only="true" (not accessible for external requests) or not.
   </li>
   <li>
error handling: using different &lt;handle-errors&gt;s.
   </li>
   <li>
cachability (since 2.1): some requests can use cached responses
from caching pipeline. Others, which should not be cached, can be
handled by the non-caching pipeline implementation.
  </li>
  <li>
logical grouping: logically-related components can be grouped into
separate pipelines to improve readability and ease administrative concerns.
  </li>
  <li>
ids: used to identify pipeline and other elements. See the "sitebuilder" sitemap editor
in scratchpad samples for an example.
  </li>
</ul>
 </answer>
 </faq>
 
 <faq>
  <question>
Where can I find more information about the sitemap?
  </question>
  <answer>
   <p>
Learn more about advanced Sitemap features by downloading the free chapter, <link href="http://www.newriders.com/books/product.asp?product_id={C3C05052-BE3B-4E06-A60A-13FB40AF58F6}" >A User's Look at the Cocoon architecture,</link> from Langham and Ziegeler's <em>Cocoon: Building XML Applications</em> available at the New Riders web site.
  </p>
  <p>
Check out a draft XML Schema <link href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/cocoon-2.1/src/documentation/xdocs/drafts/sitemap-2.1-draft.xsd?rev=HEAD&amp;content-type=text/plain">grammar for the Cocoon sitemap</link>, and some <link href="http://outerthought.net/sitemap/">external documentation</link> generated from this Schema. A poster diagram of the sitemap structure is also available.
   </p>
  </answer>
  </faq>
</faqs>
