<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--
      Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
      or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
      distributed with this work for additional information
      regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
      to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
      "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
      with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
      software distributed under the License is distributed on an
      "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
      KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
      specific language governing permissions and limitations
      under the License.
    --><document xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd"><properties><title>Cocoon 2.2 Site - New in 2.2</title><author email="cocoon-docs@apache.org">Apache Cocoon Documentation Team</author></properties><body>
         <div id="contentBody"><div id="bodyText"><h1 class="docTitle">New in 2.2</h1><p>While developing Cocoon 2.2 the main goal was simplicity, modularity and
consistent configuration. This page is a summary of all the new features and
improvements.</p><h1>General</h1><ul>
<li>Cocoon 2.2 doesn't use an Avalon-based component manager any more but uses
Spring 2 instead.</li>
<li>Cocoon components (sitemap components as well as general components) can be
defined as Spring beans now. This brings all the power of Spring (Dependency
Injection, AOP framework, etc.) to the core of Cocoon without having to rely on
some kind of bridging mechanism. Avalon component configurations are still
supported but deprecated.</li>
<li>Cocoon core has been split up into a bunch of smaller modules (pipeline
api/impl, sitemap api/impl, components, etc.). This is an important step in
order to make Cocoon more easily embeddable in the future and to define clear
contracts.</li>
<li>An optional additional validation of sitemaps based on an XML schema
definition is configureable.</li>
<li>Cocoon 2.2 uses Comons Logging instead of Avalon Logkit as logging interface
and Log4j as logging implementation. (<em>Also see the 'Incompatibles changes'
section of this document.</em>)</li>
</ul><h1>Modularity</h1><ul>
<li>In order to make Cocoon applications more modular, the
Servlet-Service-Framework was introduced. The Servlet-Service-Framework is a
general-purpose framework that makes it possible to establish contracts between
sub-applications.</li>
<li>The Servlet-Service-Framework introduces polymorphic relationships between
services.</li>
<li>The Servlet-Service-Framework has no dependency on the 'traditional' Cocoon
(sitemap/pipeline machinery) and can be used together with any
JavaServlet-compatible web application.</li>
</ul><h1>Configuration and Deployment</h1><ul>
<li>Cocoon 2.1 was configured at build time. This means that you have to build
Cocoon 2.1 yourself in order to get the Cocoon that you need for your
application. There was no simple upgrade path from one minor/patch release to
the next. Cocoon 2.2 expands the meaning of blocks. Blocks have become binary
deployment units which follow a particular directory structure and can provide
Servlet-Services, Java services, Java classes and resources and Cocoon specific
files (templates, stylesheets, etc.).</li>
<li>Cocoon blocks express their dependencies using project object model
descriptors (POM 4.0) defined by the Maven project. This makes it easy to build
Cocoon 2.2 based projects with Maven 2 though it's no hard requirement.</li>
<li>Cocoon 2.2 provides a consistent way of configuration based on the Cocoon
Spring Configurator - a new Cocoon sub project. It supports the configuration of
components based on the Spring property placeholder configurer and the property
overrider configurer and is aware of running modes, i.e. you can provide special
properties for different environments (e.g. development, test, production).</li>
<li>Cocoon 2.2 uses Jakarta Commons Logging 1.1 as logging framework and Log4j
as default implementation.</li>
<li>The number of dependencies of a minimal Cocoon application (sitemaps,
pipelines, XML templates) was reduced and together they amount to less than
10MB  (incl. Xalan and Xerces libs!).</li>
</ul><h1>Tools</h1><ul>
<li>The Cocoon Maven 2 plugin makes is very easy to use Cocoon together with
Maven 2 as build system. The main features are</li>
<ul>
<li>starting a block as web application (+ support for the automatical reload of
Java classes and all other resources),</li>
<li>rewritting web.xml to weave in a shielding classloader that reverses the
classloading hierarchy in order to avoid classloader problems (e.g. with XML
libraries),</li>
<li>a block can supply xpatch files to patch the <tt>web.xml </tt>of the
destination web application.</li>
</ul>

<li>Schema files for sitemaps.</li>
</ul><h1>Deprecation</h1><ul>
<li>Avalon-style component configurations</li>
</ul><div class="fixme"><div><strong>Fixme: </strong>Deprecation is subject of an ongoing dicussion.</div></div><h1>Migrating 2.1 components</h1>When you have avalon based components that you want to use with the new
spring configuration system make sure you are configure them right. Avalon based
components were implementing an interface to e.g. be Threadsafe. In Spring you
will need to configure the scope (default is singletone). If you see a lot of
NPE in concurrency tests then you would need to use the prototype scope as shown
below.<pre/><pre>&lt;beans&gt;
  &lt;bean id="dispatcher" scope="prototype"
    name="org.apache.cocoon.transformation.Transformer/dispatcher"
    class="org.apache.forrest.dispatcher.transformation.DispatcherTransformer"&gt;
    &lt;property name="manager" ref="org.apache.avalon.framework.service.ServiceManager"/&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;
&lt;/beans&gt;</pre><pre/><h1>Incompatible changes</h1><ul>
<li>All Cocoon components don't implement the Avalon Logkit logging interfaces
(<tt><a href="http://excalibur.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/avalon/framework/logger/Logger.html">org.apache.avalon.framework.logger.Logger</a></tt>
) anymore but Commons logging instead. This change also makes it possible to
configure components via Spring configuration files. If you extend one of those
components (e.g.
<a href="http://cocoon.apache.org/2.1/apidocs/org/apache/cocoon/transformation/AbstractSAXTransformer.html">AbstractSAXTransformer</a>),
you have to change the logger implementation and to recompile your classes. We
are sorry but there is no backwards compatible way in doing this move from
Avalon Logkit to Commons Logging.</li>
</ul></div></div>
       </body></document>