<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<!--+
    | Main samples page
    |
    | CVS $Id: samples.xml 216123 2005-07-13 07:18:17Z cziegeler $
    +-->

<samples name="Additional Cocoon Core Samples" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

  <group name="The Power of XML">
    <sample name="XML-ized web sites" href="sites/">
      A couple of existing web sites have been xml-ized to show you
      how easier it is to handle pure-content markup.
    </sample>   
    <sample name="Presentation Slides" href="slides/slides">
      An example of more complex use of XSLT for navigation and content filtering.
    </sample>   
    <sample name="Content Syndication &amp; Aggregation" href="aggregation/">
      Separation of content and style allows not only to serve your content
      in different ways, but also to syndicate, aggregate or otherwise include
      and transform content provided by other web sites.
    </sample>
    <sample name="Catalog Entity Resolver" href="catalog/">
      XML is handy but also very complex. Cocoon integrates a number of 
      facilities to help you during your journey through XML-land. One of these
      is the centralized handling of resolving network resources 
      (e.g. DTDs, symbols, character entity sets, images) to local copies
      through the use of catalogs. Also explains how to use DocBook DTDs.
    </sample>
  </group>

  <group name="More Core Samples">
    <sample href="modules/" name="The Power of Sitemap: Input Modules">
      This example shows the usage of Input Modules in sitemap attribute expressions.
    </sample>
    <sample href="sources/" name="The Power of Sitemap: Sources">
      This example shows the usage of sources in the sitemap.
    </sample>    
    <sample href="errorhandling/" name="Error Handling">
      An example page producing exceptions and handling them. Demonstrates the 
      handler hierarchy and the exception selectors.
    </sample>
    <sample href="components" name="Core Components">
      Some samples of various components that are included with the core,
      e.g. Stream Generators, Paginator Transformers, Image Readers.
    </sample>
    <sample href="misc" name="Miscellaneous samples">
      Some stuff that does not fit into the other groups of samples.
    </sample>
  </group>

</samples>
