<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<page>
    <content>
        <p>
            Here's a non exhaustive but typical list of Cocoon use-cases, including
            some weird ones to show Cocoon's flexiblity...
            <ul>
                <li>Convert XML documents to HTML for publishing</li>
                <li>Generate the presentation and navigation aspects of web sites</li>
                <li>Generate HTML, PDF, RTF documents and images off-line</li>
                <li>Acquire XML data over network connections, process and redistribute it</li>
                <li>Act as a front-end for SOAP or XML-RPC backend components</li>
                <li>Implement a complex HTML forms-based application which saves data in XML</li>
                <li>Build a query and navigation front-end for a relational or XML database</li>
                <li>Generate customized HTML pages depending on the type of client: different browsers, mobile devices, etc.</li>
                <li>Dynamically generate images out of XML data</li>
                <li>Generate MIDI music files from SAP data</li>
                <li>Convert structured text files to XML and HTML</li>
                <li>Build a secure authentication-based web site</li>
                <li>Build a multi-language website using XML dictionaries to translate menus and messages</li>
                <li>Build web portals using the latest JSR-168 standard</li>
                <li>Write web applications with little code and no state management code using the Flow subsystem</li>
                <li>Allow Java objects to be edited from a WAP device</li>
            </ul>
            The combination of components available in Cocoon applies
            to widely varied types of applications. This explains why more and more companies are making Cocoon
            a strategic component of their toolset.
        </p>
        <p>
            See also the list
            of Cocoon features at
            <a href="http://cocoon.apache.org/2.1/features.html">http://cocoon.apache.org/2.1/features.html</a>
        </p>
    </content>
</page>
