<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--
      Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
      or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
      distributed with this work for additional information
      regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
      to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
      "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
      with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
      software distributed under the License is distributed on an
      "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
      KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
      specific language governing permissions and limitations
      under the License.
    --><document xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd"><properties><title>Cocoon Main Site - How to create documentation for a deployment unit (e.g. a block)?</title><author email="cocoon-docs@apache.org">Apache Cocoon Documentation Team</author></properties><body>
         <div id="contentBody"><div id="bodyText"><h1 class="docTitle">How to create documentation for a deployment unit (e.g. a block)?</h1><p>In Cocoon 2.2 each block has its own release cycle and also its own
documentation set. This set is created through a separate site in Daisy. Each
set has its own collection which is used by the Daisy export plugin in Maven to
build the complete site, either locally at your hard disk, or at the official
site.</p><p>The following steps outline the process to go through to create a block site.
As an example we use the CForms block.</p><h1>Create the collection</h1><p>In Daisy, open Administration -&gt; Manage collections.<br/>
Add a new collection for the block. The name should be
<tt>cdocs-blockname</tt>, where <tt>blockname</tt> is the part of the name of
the block after cocoon. Example: when the block is named <tt>cocoon-forms</tt>,
the name of the collection should be <em>cdocs-forms</em>. <br/>
Note the id of the collection (in this case <em>7</em>).</p><h1>Create the navigation document</h1><p>Each block has its own navigation document, which simplifies the packaging of
the documation strictly for that block.</p><ol type="1">
<li>In Daisy, create a New Document and choose type <tt>Book Definition</tt>.
</li>
<li>Set the name of the document to <tt>&lt;user friendly name&gt; Block
[navigation]</tt>. For the CForms block that would be <em>Forms Block
[navigation]</em>.</li>
<li>Go to the Misc tab and add the proper collection, in this case cdocs-forms.
</li>
<li>Underneath the root, add the toplevel folder for this block, by adding a new
section node. Set the title to a user friendly name of the block. For the CForms
block that would be <em>Forms</em>.</li>
<li>Underneath this folder, add two documents, one is called
<strong>Introduction</strong>, one is called <strong>Samples</strong>. You can
create the documents by adding a new section node, and then select the "link to
new document" button (second button after the document ID). Make sure these
documents are also part of the proper collection, i.e. the
<em>cdocs-forms</em>.</li>
<li>Publish the document (mark a checkbox 'Publish changes immediately').</li>
</ol>Note the id of the navigation document (in this case <em>1152</em>).<h1>Create a new Daisy site</h1>Each block gets its own site in Daisy. Before adding documentation about the
block, the site should be selected. This way all documents will automatically be
in the proper collection.The steps below describe how to create a new Daisy site.<ol type="1">
<li>Log in to cocoon.zones.apache.org with your username and password</li>
<li>change to user daisy: <tt>sudo su - daisy</tt></li>
<li><tt>cd daisywikidata/sites</tt></li>
<li>copy another block to the new block with blockname equal to the collection
name. Example: <tt>cp -R cdocs-fop cdocs-forms</tt></li>
<li>cd into the new folder: <tt>cd cdocs-forms</tt></li>
<li>modify the siteconf.xml file:
<ul>
<li>change the <tt>title</tt> to match the name of the navigation document
(without the [navigation] part), e.g. <em>Forms Block</em></li>
<li>change the <tt>description</tt> to match the block name, e.g.<em>
Documentation of the Forms Block<br/>
</em></li>
<li>change the <tt>navigationDocId</tt> to the id of the navigation document (in
this case <em>1152</em>)</li>
<li>change the <tt>homepageDocId</tt> to the id of the introduction document (in
this case <em>489</em>)</li>
<li>change the <tt>collectionId</tt> to the id of the new collection (in this
case <em>7</em>)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>save the file and logout of the server.</li>
</ol><h1>Add the navigation to the master navigation file</h1>To show the block documentation in the total Cocoon documentation site, which
is the source for the official documentation, you need to add the navigation
document to the master navigation file. Do this step <strong>after</strong>
creating the site, as a reminder that the site should be created as well.<br/>
These are the steps to take:<ol type="1">
<li>In Daisy, go to the <tt>cdocs: Apache Cocoon</tt> site</li>
<li>Select <tt>Administration</tt> in the <em>navigation menu</em> (so not on
top!!!)</li>
<li>You should now see a tree that represents the navigation tree of the cdocs
site. This page is here only to provide convenient links to all the navigation
documents.</li>
<li>Edit the document to add the links to the navigation document. Make sure the
block names are in alphabetical order and reflect the actual menu hierarchy.
</li>
<li>Save the document and select the <tt>Cocoon Book</tt> link.</li>
<li>Edit the navigation document and add a <tt>new import navigation node</tt>
with the id of the navigation document (in this case <em>1152</em>)</li>
</ol><div class="note"><div><strong>Note: </strong>When adding documentation for the block, be sure you select the
proper site first!</div></div><h1>Configuring the Maven pom files</h1>With the Daisy Maven plugin the information can be extracted from Daisy and
built into the official site, either locally or at the official Cocoon
documentation site.The steps below configure the Maven pom files to make this happen.<section name="Configure the root pom.xml" style="background:none;padding:0;"/>Create two properties in trunk/parent/pom.xml. This is makes it easier to
maintain these two pieces of information throughout the documentation generation
process:<pre>&lt;properties&gt;
  [...] 
  &lt;docs.m.forms.version&gt;1.0&lt;/docs.m.forms.version&gt;
  &lt;docs.m.forms.relPath&gt;blocks/forms/${docs.m.forms.version}/&lt;/docs.m.forms.relPath&gt;     
&lt;/properties&gt;
</pre>Open the pom.xml in the root and find the plugin with artifactId
daisy-maven-plugin. Under <tt>collections</tt> add<pre> &lt;collection&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;cdocs-forms&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;path&gt;${docs.m.forms.relPath}&lt;/path&gt;
  &lt;/collection&gt;</pre>Try to keep the collections in alphabetical order as well.<section name="Configure the block pom.xml" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><ul>
<li>Open the <tt>pom.xml</tt> file of the block, e.g.
<em>cocoon-forms-impl/pom.xml</em></li>
<li>Open a pom.xml file of a block that is already configured, e.g. cocoon-fop
and copy the plugin with the groupID <tt>org.daisycms </tt>and artifactId<tt>
daisy-maven-plugin</tt></li>
<li>Add this to your pom file under &lt;build&gt;, &lt;plugins&gt;, if necessary
create these tags. The build section should look like this (at least containing
the daisy-maven-plugin part)</li>
</ul><ol type="1"> 
</ol><pre>    &lt;build&gt;
        &lt;plugins&gt;
            &lt;plugin&gt;
                &lt;groupId&gt;org.daisycms&lt;/groupId&gt;
                &lt;artifactId&gt;daisy-maven-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
                &lt;configuration&gt;
                    &lt;navDocId&gt;1152&lt;/navDocId&gt;
                    &lt;collection&gt;cdocs-forms&lt;/collection&gt;                   
                    &lt;skipFirstNavigationDocumentLevel&gt;true&lt;/skipFirstNavigationDocumentLevel&gt;
                &lt;/configuration&gt;
            &lt;/plugin&gt;
        &lt;/plugins&gt;
    &lt;/build&gt;</pre><ul>
<li>Change the <tt>navDocId</tt> to the id of the navigation document, in this
case <em>1152</em></li>
<li>Change the <tt>collection</tt> to the name of the collection, in this case
<em>cdocs-forms</em></li>
<li>Add the distributionManagment part and the properties as well at the same
level as the build tag.</li>
</ul><pre>  &lt;distributionManagement&gt;
    &lt;site&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;website&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;${docs.deploymentBaseUrl}/${docs.m.forms.relPath}&lt;/url&gt;
    &lt;/site&gt;
  &lt;/distributionManagement&gt;
  &lt;properties&gt;
    &lt;docs.name&gt;<strong>Cocoon Forms</strong>&lt;/docs.name&gt;    
    &lt;docs.version&gt;${docs.m.forms.version}&lt;/docs.version&gt;
  &lt;/properties&gt;
</pre><ul>
<li>Change the path in the <tt>url</tt> to match the block name, here
<em>forms</em></li>
<li>Change the property <tt>docs.name</tt> to match the user friendly name of
the block, here <em>Cocoon Forms</em></li>
<li>Set the <tt>docs.version</tt> property to 1.0 initially and update it to
reflect the documentation version.</li>
</ul><section name="Configure the site pom.xml" style="background:none;padding:0;"/>Open the pom.xml in the site and add a module to the section Cocoon Blocks:
<pre>    &lt;module&gt;../blocks/cocoon-forms/cocoon-forms-impl&lt;/module&gt;
</pre>Keep the modules in alphabetical order to ease maintenance.</div></div>
       </body></document>