<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--
      Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
      or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
      distributed with this work for additional information
      regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
      to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
      "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
      with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
      software distributed under the License is distributed on an
      "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
      KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
      specific language governing permissions and limitations
      under the License.
    --><document xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd"><properties><title>Cocoon Main Site - How to contribute?</title><author email="cocoon-docs@apache.org">Apache Cocoon Documentation Team</author></properties><body>
         <div id="contentBody"><div id="bodyText"><h1 class="docTitle">How to contribute?</h1><h1>Code</h1><p>TBD</p><h1>General documentation</h1><p>These instructions only work if you have an active account in our Daisy CMS
and got the doc editor role assigned. If you haven't, create your account at
<a href="http://cocoon.zones.apache.org/daisy/registration">http://cocoon.zones.apache.org/daisy/registration</a>
and ask at dev[_at_]cocoon.apache.org for editing rights.</p><div class="note"><div><strong>Note: </strong>Doc editors are not allowed to publish a document. This can only
be done by Apache Cocoon committers.</div></div><section name="Editing a document" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><p>Simply follow the "Edit" link at the bottom of a page, login in and select
<em>Page Actions - Edit</em> from the menu.</p><section name="Adding a document" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><p>Go to http://cocoon.zones.apache.org/daisy/, login and select the
documentation site where you want to add your new document. Select <em>New
Document</em> from the menu. The recommended document type is <em>Cocoon
document</em>.<br/>
If you want to make your new document appear in a navigation menu, click on
<em>Go to navigation</em> document below the navigation menu and select
<em>Page Actions - Edit</em>.</p><section name="What happens once I've added or edited a document?" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><p>The moment you submit a new or changed document an email is sent to docs at
cocoon dot apache dot org.  An entry is also added to the list on the Daisy
<a href="NO_LINK">Cocoon Site Overview</a> page.  A Cocoon committer should
then see the change, review it and make it live.</p><h1>Sitemap component documentation</h1><p>For documenting sitemap components, we use a system whereby certain parts of
the documentation are extracted automatically from the Java sources using a tool
called sitemaptags2daisy.</p><p>If you are not a committer, make sure that you have checked out the latest
version of the Java source file from SVN, make your changes and create a patch
file. Create a new patch issue in JIRA and add your diff file.</p><section name="Editing the documentation of a sitemap component" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><p>Only edit the content of the the Long Description part in Daisy. The short
description and the value of the fields are automatically assigned from the Java
sources, so if you change them in Daisy, these changes will get overwritten the
next time the sitemaptags2daisy tool is run.</p><section name="Adding documentation for a new sitemap component" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><p>If running the sitemaptags2daisy tool is not an option (no time, no
privileges, ...) then create manually a document of type "Sitemap Component". In
the JavaClass field, enter the fully qualified name of the implementation class.
Leave the other fields and the Short Description part empty, they will be
assigned the next time the sitemaptags2daisy tool runs. Enter the documentation
in the Long Description part.</p><section name="Adding javadoc tags" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><p>The following special javadoc tags are supported (none of these are strictly
required by the sitemaptags2daisy tool):</p><ul>
<li>@cocoon.sitemap.component.name<br/>
default name with which this component is declared in the sitemap</li>
<li>@cocoon.sitemap.component.documentation.disabled<br/>
excludes the component from the documentation</li>
<li>@cocoon.sitemap.component.documentation<br/>
A short (one-paragraph) description of the component. Can contain HTML markup
(preferably only inline tags).</li>
<li>@cocoon.sitemap.component.documentation.caching<br/>
A comment about the caching of this component. The cacheability of the component
is figured out automatially by its implemented interfaces, but this tag allows
to provide a short comment on the chaching conditions. This is mapped to a field
in Daisy, thus should not contain HTML markup.</li>
</ul>Next to these, the @deprecated tag is also synced with the Daisy document.
<section name="Running the sitemaptags2daisy tool" style="background:none;padding:0;"/>TODO, see the README.txt in the sources for now.</div></div>
       </body></document>