<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
      Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
      or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
      distributed with this work for additional information
      regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
      to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
      "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
      with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
      software distributed under the License is distributed on an
      "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
      KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
      specific language governing permissions and limitations
      under the License.
    -->
<document xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Cocoon Main Site - News archive</title>
    <author email="cocoon-docs@apache.org">Apache Cocoon Documentation Team</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <div id="contentBody">
      <div id="bodyText">
        <h1 class="docTitle">News archive</h1>
          <dl class="news">
            <dt>Apache Cocoon 3.0.0-alpha-1 Released</dt>
            <dd>The Apache Cocoon Community is proud to announce the release of Cocoon 3.0.0-alpha-1.
              Apache Cocoon 3 is a major rewrite of Cocoon 2.2.
              Like Cocoon 2 it is based around the concept of pipelines and sitemaps and it is very
              similar to Cocoon 2.2 in many respects but is slimmed down and
              designed to be *easily usable from within any Java environment*.
              [<a href="news-c3-alpha-1-released.html">more</a>] 
            </dd>
            <dd class="newsMeta">submitted by Reinhard Pötz, 01/24/09 12:53:55 GMT</dd>
          </dl>
          <dl class="news">
            <dt>Apache Cocoon 3</dt>
            <dd>Corona was accepted by the Cocoon PMC to become Apache Cocoon 3. The Cocoon 3 website has more details. A first ALPHA release will follow soon.
              [<a href="1487_1_1.html">more</a>] 
            </dd>
            <dd class="newsMeta">submitted by Reinhard Pötz, 8/14/08 7:23:55 AM</dd>
          </dl>
          <dl class="news">
            <dt>Apache Cocoon 2.2.0 Released</dt>
            <dd>The Apache Cocoon Community is proud to announce the release of Cocoon 2.2.0. Apache Cocoon is a Spring-based framework (since version 2.2 of Cocoon) built around the concepts of separation of concerns and component-based development. Cocoon implements these concepts...
              [<a href="1445_1_1.html">more</a>] 
            </dd>
            <dd class="newsMeta">submitted by Reinhard Pötz, 5/15/08 5:19:52 AM</dd>
          </dl>
          <dl class="news">
            <dt>Apache Cocoon 2.1.11 Released</dt>
            <dd>The Apache Cocoon Community is proud to announce the new release   of Apache Cocoon.   Apache Cocoon is a web development framework built around the concept   of separation of concerns (that is: allowing people to do their job without having to step on each other...
              [<a href="1426_1_1.html">more</a>] 
            </dd>
            <dd class="newsMeta">submitted by Grzegorz Kossakowski, 1/9/08 6:57:35 PM</dd>
          </dl>
        <dl class="news">
          <dt>Apache Cocoon 2.2-RC2 Released</dt>
          <dd>The Apache Cocoon Community is proud to announce the second release candidate of Cocoon 2.2. Apache Cocoon is a Spring-based framework (since version 2.2) built around the concepts of separation of concerns and component-based development. Cocoon implements these c...
            [<a href="1421_1_1.html">more</a>] 
          </dd>
          <dd class="newsMeta">submitted by Reinhard Pötz, 10/29/07 7:23:01 AM</dd>
        </dl>
        <dl class="news">
          <dt>Cocoon GetTogether 2007 in Rome</dt>
          <dd> After being three times in Gent, twice in Amsterdam the this year Cocoon GetTogether edition took place iin Rome from Oct 3rd to 5th. Again it was a great event that started with a two days Hackathon followed by a conference day. Most of the presentations are available at our Wiki.  A few folks ...
            [<a href="1417_1_1.html">more</a>] 
          </dd>
          <dd class="newsMeta">submitted by Reinhard Pötz, 10/11/07 8:06:43 AM</dd>
        </dl>
        <dl class="news">
          <dt>Relaunch of cocoon.apache.org</dt>
          <dd> We are pleased to announce the publishing of the new website of Apache Cocoon. This relaunch comprises a new design for the main site and the Cocoon 2.2 documentation. The new documentation reflects the new structure of Cocoon 2.2 with a  small core which is based on the subprojects "Cocoon Conf... 
            [<a href="1416_1_1.html">more</a>] 
          </dd>
          <dd class="newsMeta">submitted by Reinhard Pötz, 10/2/07 8:01:22 AM</dd>
        </dl>
        <dl class="news">
          <dt>[Cocoon GetTogether 2007 - Rome] The program is out!</dt>
          <dd> The CocoonGT team is pleased to announce the conference schedule has been finalized and is available at http://www.cocoongt.org/PROGRAM.html  As usual, we had a great number of high-quality submissions. In keeping with the tradition of having a conference day packed full with great content, we m...
            [<a href="1414_1_1.html">more</a>] 
          </dd>
          <dd class="newsMeta">submitted by Reinhard Pötz, 9/28/07 2:20:11 PM</dd>
        </dl>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</document>