<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--
      Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
      or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
      distributed with this work for additional information
      regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
      to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
      "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
      with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
      software distributed under the License is distributed on an
      "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
      KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
      specific language governing permissions and limitations
      under the License.
    --><document xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd"><properties><title>Cocoon Main Site - Products</title><author email="cocoon-docs@apache.org">Apache Cocoon Documentation Team</author></properties><body>
         <div id="contentBody"><div id="bodyText"><h1 class="docTitle">Products</h1><p>These are products that use Apache Cocoon:</p><section name="Apache Lenya" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><p><a href="http://lenya.apache.org">Apache Lenya</a> is an Open Source Java/XML
Content Management System and comes with revision control, site management,
scheduling, search, WYSIWYG editors, and workflow.</p><section name="Daisy CMS" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><p><a href="http://www.daisycms.org">Daisy</a> is a content management system
that offers rich out-of-the-box functionality combined with solid foundations
for extensibility and integration. Daisy consists of two main components:</p><ul>
<li>a stand-alone repository server accessible through HTTP/XML (using the
<a href="http://naeblis.cx/rtomayko/2004/12/12/rest-to-my-wife">ReST</a> style
of WebServices) and/or a high-level (remote) Java API, and</li>
<li>an extensive editing and publishing front-end web application running inside
<a href="http://cocoon.apache.org/">Apache Cocoon</a>.</li>
</ul>Due to its genericity and flexibility, Daisy can be used for many different
purposes, but is ideally suited for information-rich, structured content and
asset management applications. Even for advanced content management
applications, Daisy can be used and configured without any Java-coding skills:
Daisy offers a Javascript/Cocoon-based extension framework.Daisy is licensed under the open source, business-friendly Apache License 2.0
<section name="Hippo CMS" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><p><a href="http://www.hippocms.org"> Hippo CMS</a> is an
<a href="http://www.hippocms.org/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=2618">open
source</a> information centered content management system. It's targeted at
medium to large organisations managing content for multi-channel distribution
like web sites and intranets. It facilitates an open and flexible way of using
your information by following international accepted
<a href="http://www.hippocms.org/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=2609">open
standards</a>.</p><p>Hippo CMS is licensed under the Apache License 2.0.</p><section name="Mindquarry" style="background:none;padding:0;"/><p><a href="http://www.mindquarry.com">Mindquarry</a> - The OpenSource
Collaborative Software - is a fully Cocoon-based webapplication with document
management, wiki, task tracking and conversations. It provides a powerful set of
collaborative tools for use online and offline to streamline teamwork between
information workers.</p><p>Technically it uses a
<a href="http://naeblis.cx/rtomayko/2004/12/12/rest-to-my-wife">REST</a>-style
API producing either HTML including lots of AJAX, PDF, Atom-Feeds and other
views for users and also a raw XML view for programmatic clients. The latter is
used by the desktop client, which lets you synchronize your documents (aka a
very easy-to-use Subversion client) and gives you a quick view on your tasks.
Mindquarry is one of the first applications to use Cocoon 2.2 and it's new
servlet services architecture.</p><p>Mindquarry is licensed under the Mozilla Public License 1.1. A running
instance is <a href="http://www.mindquarry.org">www.mindquarry.org</a>, which
hosts the Open Source project.</p><p>If you do not find your product here, use the <em>Edit</em> link below and
add yourself. If you are not familiar with the CMS, read the
<em>General</em><em> documentation</em> section of <a href="1273_1_1.html">How to
contribute?</a>.</p></div></div>
       </body></document>