<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--
      Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
      or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
      distributed with this work for additional information
      regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
      to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
      "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
      with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
      software distributed under the License is distributed on an
      "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
      KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
      specific language governing permissions and limitations
      under the License.
    -->
<document xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Cocoon Main Site - Apache Cocoon 3</title>
    <author email="cocoon-docs@apache.org">Apache Cocoon Documentation Team</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <div id="contentBody">
      <div id="bodyText">
        <h1 class="docTitle">Apache Cocoon 3.0.0-alpha-1 Released</h1>
        <pre>
The Apache Cocoon Community is proud to announce the release of Cocoon 3.0.0-alpha-1.

  Apache Cocoon 3 is a major rewrite of Cocoon 2.2. Like Cocoon 2 it is
  based around the concept of pipelines and sitemaps and it is very
  similar to Cocoon 2.2 in many respects but is slimmed down and
  designed to be *easily usable from within any Java environment*.

  Here is an example of a pipeline that uses SAX components:

    Pipeline pipeline = new NonCachingPipeline();
    pipeline.addComponent(new StringGenerator("&lt;x&gt;&lt;/x&gt;"));
    pipeline.addComponent(new XSLTTransformer(
        this.getClass().getResource("/test1.xslt")));
    pipeline.addComponent(new XSLTTransformer(
        this.getClass().getResource("/test2.xslt")));
    pipeline.addComponent(new XMLSerializer());

    pipeline.setup(System.out);
    pipeline.execute();


  On top of this, Cocoon 3 has the goal to become an integration
  platform for RESTful webservices and web applications.

  There are several Maven 2 archetypes available that help you to get
  started. Find a list and usage instructions at
  http://cocoon.apache.org/3.0/download.html

  The release artifacts are available from the central Maven repository
  (http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/) or you can download them from the
  distribution area (http://cocoon.apache.org/3.0/download.html).

  More information about Cocoon 3 is available at
  http://cocoon.apache.org/3.0/

  *************************** W A R N I N G ***************************

  Some user accessible points in this software package should be
  considered "alpha". This means that the developer team is not
  investing _any_ effort to provide backward compatibility between alpha
  releases for these parts. This software will continue to be released
  as "alpha" until its code, schemas, and APIs are considered stable.

  Until then, there will be no warranty that newer versions will
  maintain backward compatibility for such parts, even in the most
  simple cases. However, once "beta" status is reached, backward
  incompatible changes will be made only when absolutely necessary to
  reach "final" status.

  The Cocoon development team understands the importance of reliable
  software as well protecting user investments through the creation of a
  solid development platform that doesn't change. On the other hand,
  Cocoon 3 should give its developers the freedom to experiment and to
  react quickly on feedback. Thus, reliability cannot be guaranteed
  before the software achieves its "final" status.

  Until then, no effort will be provided to guarantee backward
  compatibility for any parts considered alpha.

  You have been warned.

  *************************** W A R N I N G ***************************

The Apache Cocoon Project
</pre>
      </div>
    </div>
  </body>
</document>