<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Apache Cocoon</title>
    <subtitle>XML Web Development Framework</subtitle>
    <authors>
      <person name="cocoon-dev" email="dev@cocoon.apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>

    <figure src="images/cocoon.gif" alt="Cocoon"/>
   <s1 title="News">
     <p>
       XMLForm and JXForms have been removed from the 2.1.x distribution.
       Please use the well established Cocoon Forms (former Woody) framework.
     </p>
   </s1>
    <s1 title="What is Cocoon?">
      <p>
        Apache Cocoon is a web development framework built around the concepts of
        separation of concerns (making sure people can interact and collaborate on a
        project, without stepping on each other toes) and component-based web
        development.
      </p>
      <p>
        Cocoon implements these concepts around the notion of 'component pipelines',
        each component on the pipeline specializing on a particular operation. This
        makes it possible to use a Lego(tm)-like approach in building web solutions,
        hooking together components into pipelines without any required programming.
      </p>
      <p>
        Cocoon is "<em>web glue for your web application development needs</em>". It
        is a glue that keeps concerns separate and allows parallel evolution of the
        two sides, improving development pace and reducing the chance of conflicts.
      </p>
      <p>
        Cocoon has been designed to coexist and interoperate side-by-side with your
        existing J2EE solutions or to give them new functionality without requiring
        any change in the existing infrastructure.
      </p>
      <p>
        Cocoon interacts with many data sources, including filesystems, RDBMS,
        LDAP, native XML databases, SAP&#174; systems and network-based data sources.
        It adapts content delivery to the capabilities of different devices like HTML, WML,
        PDF, SVG, and RTF, to name just a few. You can run Cocoon as a Servlet as well as
        through a powerful, commandline interface. The deliberate design of its abstract
        environment gives you the freedom to extend its functionality to meet your
        special needs in a highly modular fashion.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Cocoon Features">
      <p>
        You want to get an overview of all available features of Cocoon in 5 minutes?
        Read the <link href="features.html">features list</link>!
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Where can I find it?">
      <p>
   To download the latest release @released.version@ of Apache Cocoon, go to the
   <link href="http://cocoon.apache.org/mirror.cgi">download area.</link>
      </p>
      <p>
   If you are looking for a past generation of Cocoon (no longer supported but still available),
   go to the <link href="http://cocoon.apache.org/1.x/">Cocoon 1.x area</link>.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Where to start?">
      <p>
          With a large serving of core components and more than 45 additional "blocks", this has
          become a big project and it is often hard for newcomers to find their way through the
          (wonderful) world of Cocoon.
      </p>
      <p>
          To make it easier, we have started to create <link href="./tracks/index.html">documentation tracks</link>
          to help you locate the parts of the documentation that are the most relevant for your needs.
          There are few tracks at the moment, but we hope to create more of them depending
          on the feedback and help that we can get.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="More News about Cocoon">
      <p>
Check out our <link href="http://cocoon.apache.org/news/">news page</link> for more up-to-date news about Cocoon.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <figure src="images/cocoon-built.gif" alt="Built with Apache Cocoon"/>
  </body>
</document>
