<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "dtd/document-v10.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Apache Cocoon</title>
    <subtitle>XML Publishing Framework</subtitle>
    <authors>
      <person name="cocoon-dev" email="dev@cocoon.apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <figure src="images/cocoon.gif" alt="Cocoon"/>
    <s1 title="What is Cocoon?">
      <p>
   Apache Cocoon is an XML publishing framework that raises the usage of
   XML and XSLT technologies for server applications to a new
   level. Designed for performance and scalability around pipelined SAX
   processing, Cocoon offers a flexible environment based on a separation
   of concerns between content, logic, and style. To top this all off, 
   Cocoon's centralized configuration system and sophisticated caching help
   you to create, deploy, and maintain rock-solid XML server applications.
      </p>
      <p>
   Cocoon interacts with most data sources, including filesystems, RDBMS,
   LDAP, native XML databases, and network-based data sources. It adapts
   content delivery to the capabilities of different devices like HTML, WML,
   PDF, SVG, and RTF, to name just a few. You can run Cocoon as a Servlet as well as
   through a powerful, commandline interface. The deliberate design of its abstract 
   environment gives you the freedom to extend its functionality to meet your 
   special needs in a highly modular fashion.
      </p> 
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Where can I find it?">
      <p>
   To download the latest release @released.version@ of Apache Cocoon, go to the 
   <link href="http://cocoon.apache.org/mirror.cgi">download area.</link>
      </p>
      <p>
   If you are looking for a past generation of Cocoon (no longer supported but still available), 
   go to the <link href="http://cocoon.apache.org/1.x/">Cocoon 1.x area</link>.  
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="More News about Cocoon">
      <p>
Check out our <link href="http://cocoon.apache.org/news/">news page</link> for more up-to-date news about Cocoon.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <figure src="images/cocoon-built.gif" alt="Built with Apache Cocoon"/>
  </body>
</document>
