<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Mailing Lists</title>
  <authors>
   <person name="Robin Green" email="greenrd@hotmail.com"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>
  <s1 title="Important Notice">

   <p><strong>IMPORTANT: Before posting a question or problem to any mailing list,
    </strong>please first look at the following resources:</p>
   <ol>
    <li><link href="faq/index.html">FAQs</link></li>
    <li><link href="link/index.html">Cocoon Links</link></li>
    <li><link href="mail-archives.html">Mailing list archives</link> - 
     a veritable goldmine of Cocoon-specific information - if you know where to look!</li>
   </ol>

   <p><strong>IMPORTANT:</strong> Careful postings please.
    These are high-volume lists, so we all needs ways to help us all
    work smarter.
    See tips for <link href="contrib.html#tips">Contributing</link>
   </p>
  </s1>

  <s1 title="Tips (keeping focus helps your points come across!)">

   <p>We use the mail list both as a media to transmit our thoughts and as a
virtual location to hang around and feel part of something.
   </p><p>
In order for the second to happen, you just have to subscribe. That's
it, nothing fancy.
   </p><p>
But in order for the first to happen (transmit your thoughts) it's an
entirely different matter.
   </p><p>
Here are a few things that help a lot:
   </p><p>
 1) reduce noise, increase signal: your email client will quote the
message you are replying to automatically, but it's *your*
responsibility to remove those parts that aren't part of the signal of
your email. Sure, you might let this operation to the reader, but you
must understand that the reader is not supposed to do this. Or, at
least, it should be *you* to make the reader confortable.
   </p><p>
 2) be respectful, be aware of community dynamics: sending HTML in the
mail more than *doubles* the message size and interferes with text-based
mail clients. You want your point to come across, so make sure that
everybody can get to that point with the *easiest* possible effort, or,
otherwise, your signal might be wasted in the noise and the time you
think you are saving, you are, in fact, loosing it completely.
   </p><p>
 3) promote your signal: people on mail lists are used to read tons of
email a day. Without a good 'promotion' of your points, they might get
missed in the noise. (note: 'noise' is a subjective notion, what is
signal for you might be noise for others, it's up to you to make your
signal stand up). Things that help in this respect:
   </p><p>
    a) a simple yet effective email title. Geeks are ultimately curious
animals, tickle their curiosity!
   </p><p>
    b) be elegant and visually effective. Sure, you have to use ASCII,
but there is a lot that you can convey with ASCII
   </p><source><![CDATA[
          +---------------------------------+
          | I'm sure nobody will miss this! |
          +---------------------------------+
   ]]></source><p>         
    c) structure your text. Whenever possible, use *strong* or
_underline_ or /italic/ or use bullet lists and so on. Consider textual
RFC, that's how you should write your emails. Sure, it takes a little
more time, but I guarantee you that it saves a lot of it later on.
   </p><p>
    d) keep paragraphs short! you can go on and on forever, I'm sure you
do, but keep your point focused, so that the signal/noise ratio is
increased.
   </p><p>
 4) be respectful of other's opinion: your email will be stored forever,
archived in several locations around the world, indexed by Google,
locked in magnetic tapes into the NSA caves and so on. Just keep this in
mind before you hit "send", this will keep your ego honest :)
   </p><p>
 5) admit your incapacity/ignorance/mistakes: there is nothing more
appreciated in a community that someone that can stand up and apologize
for something. Remember: if you don't make mistakes, you can't learn.
And if you don't admit you made it, nobody knows you are learning :)
   </p><p>
Keep all these things in mind and you'll be impressed by how much fun
and knowledge you can get out of all this open development thing.
   </p>
  </s1>
  
  <s1 title="Cocoon Users">
   <p><link href="mailto:cocoon-users-subscribe@xml.apache.org">Subscribe</link>
      <link href="mailto:cocoon-users-unsubscribe@xml.apache.org">Unsubscribe</link>
   </p>

   <p>The general Cocoon list, for problems, bug reports, asking for advice on how
    best to implement a site, comparisons with other XML frameworks, etc.
    But don't forget to look in the FAQ first, please!</p>

   <p><strong>This is not an appropriate list for general XSL and XML questions.</strong> 
    Instead look at the various resources listed at the
    <link href="link/index.html">Cocoon Links</link> pages,
     or try the
    <link href="http://www.mulberrytech.com/xsl/">Mulberrytech XSL list</link>.</p>

   <p><strong>This is also not an appropriate list for general Java questions.</strong>
    Instead try <link href="news:comp.lang.java.help">news:comp.lang.java.help</link>
    or <link href="http://hotdispatch.com/">http://hotdispatch.com/</link>, for
    example.</p>

   <p><strong>IMPORTANT:</strong> If you are posting about a problem you are having
    (as most people do), it will aid in finding a speedy resolution if you provide
    full configuration details (especially the <strong>Cocoon version number</strong>,
    but also your operating system, JDK version, and servlet engine), and full details
    of any errors encountered (including full error messages and stack traces).</p>

   <p>Please also have some consideration for the other users on the list - this is a
    busy list and we do not appreciate getting the exact same message posted impatiently
    several times a day/week! Doing so is only likely to make your question answered more
    slowly, or not at all, not faster.</p>

   <note>This list is moderated, so the first time you post, there will be a
    delay before your post is reviewed and accepted. This is to prevent spam.</note>
  </s1>

  <s1 title="Cocoon Dev">
   <p><link href="mailto:cocoon-dev-subscribe@xml.apache.org">Subscribe</link>
      <link href="mailto:cocoon-dev-unsubscribe@xml.apache.org">Unsubscribe</link>
   </p>

   <p>This list is for developers <strong>working on</strong> or wanting to work on
    Cocoon itself (not developers merely working <strong>with</strong> Cocoon),
    for code patches to Cocoon to be posted (please use <code>diff -u</code> format),
    and for general Cocoon questions.</p>

   <p>Note this is <strong>NOT</strong> for general Cocoon questions like "Why
    isn't Cocoon working on my machine?" - 
    please ask those sorts of questions on cocoon-users (after reading the
    FAQ first, of course).</p>

   <note>This list is moderated, so the first time you post, there will be a
    delay before your post is reviewed and accepted. This is to prevent spam.</note>
  </s1>

  <s1 title="Cocoon Docs">
   <p><link href="mailto:cocoon-docs-subscribe@xml.apache.org">Subscribe</link>
      <link href="mailto:cocoon-docs-unsubscribe@xml.apache.org">Unsubscribe</link>
   </p>

   <p>This list is for everyone (users and developers) to assist with building
    the Cocoon documentation.
   </p>

   <p>
    Please be careful to limit cross-posting between the Cocoon lists. You can
    assume that all developers are also subscribed to cocoon-docs.
    Any docs-related thread on -users or -dev should be moved to -docs (do not
    Cc the original list, but send a short reply to indicate that the thread
    has moved).
   </p>

   <note>This list is moderated, so the first time you post, there will be a
    delay before your post is reviewed and accepted. This is to prevent spam.</note>
  </s1>

  <s1 title="Cocoon Cvs">
   <p><link href="mailto:cocoon-cvs-subscribe@xml.apache.org">Subscribe</link>
      <link href="mailto:cocoon-cvs-unsubscribe@xml.apache.org">Unsubscribe</link>
   </p>

   <p>This <strong>read-only</strong> list sends out notification messages detailing
    any change made to the CVS repository where all the source code and libraries
    are stored for development purposes. The average user probably doesn't need to
    subscribe to this list.</p>

   <note>You should never post to this list at all. Only the
    CVS server should post to it.</note>

  </s1>

  <s1 title="XSP Dev">
   <p><link href="mailto:xsp-dev-subscribe@xml.apache.org">Subscribe</link>
     <link href="mailto:xsp-dev-unsubscribe@xml.apache.org">Unsubscribe</link>
   </p>

   <p>This list began life on November 2000, and was created to discuss the
    standardisation and implementation of the dynamic content language XSP,
    which is used not only in Cocoon but in other software such as AxKit.
    You are recommended to have a strong working knowledge of XSP before joining
    this list.</p>

   <p>Note this is <strong>NOT</strong> for general XSP questions like
    "Why doesn't my XSP page work?" - please ask those sorts of questions on
    the relevant list for your XSP software (e.g. cocoon-users if you're using
    Cocoon) - after checking the FAQ first of course!
   </p>
  </s1>

  <s1 title="Related Mailing Lists">

   <p>(See also <link href="http://dmoz.org/Computers/Data_Formats/Markup_Languages/XML/">
    ODP XML links</link> for related websites.)</p>
   <ul>
    <li><link href="http://www.mulberrytech.com/xsl/">Mulberrytech XSL list</link> -
      more appropriate than Cocoon Users for general XSL questions.</li>
    <li><link href="http://xml.apache.org/mail.html">XML Apache Projects</link> -
      list of mailing lists for all the projects on xml.apache.org.</li>
    <li>Some servlet engines have their own mailing lists for servlet-engine
     configuration questions, such as
     <link href="mailto:tomcat-user-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org">tomcat-user</link> (note it is "user"
     and not "users").</li>
   </ul>
  </s1>
 </body>
</document>
