<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Apache Cocoon Performance Tips</title>
  <authors>
   <person name="Gerhard Froehlich" email="g-froehlich@gmx.de"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>
 
 <s1 title="Disclaimer">
   <p>The Cocoon Performance Tips in this version is a loose collection of
   usenet articles regarding how to improve the Apache Cocoon performance.</p>
   <p>As in the real world, it needs some kind of evolution to get better.
   If you have suggestions how to make it better or new kool tips, then be brave and
   send it to the <link href="http://cocoon.apache.org/community/mail-lists.html">
   Cocoon Mailing Lists</link>!</p>
   <note>Sometimes the tips maybe doubled or contradictory. If you notice something
   like that, then send a note to the <link href="http://cocoon.apache.org/community/mail-lists.html">
   Cocoon Mailing Lists</link>.</note>
 </s1>
 
 <s1 title="Common">
   <ul>
      <li>Logging kills performance. Consider disabling logging entirely from
      Cocoon (leave only the ERROR channel) and let Apache or the servlet
      container log accesses and stuff.</li>
      
      <li>Use a transparent proxy in front of your web server! The fastest
      response is the one that is not even processed. Cocoon is very slow
      (compared to a proxy server) to read resources such as stylesheets and
      images. A transparent proxy (SQUID, for example, don't use Apache's
      mod_proxy because it is not fully compatible with HTTP/1.1 and disables
      connection keep-alive). Make sure you tune how long the static resources
      that Cocoon "read"s from the sitemap are cached (look into the readers
      code to find out more).</li>
      
      <li>Consider prerendering or time-based batch-process the static parts
      of your site. PDF reports, rasterized SVG graphs or things that change
      regularly.</li>
      
      <li>For optimum performance with Tomcat 4 and Cocoon 2, 
      use the HTTP/1.0 connector.</li>
      
      <li>Move static content out of Cocoon's control. Move your static content out of the 
      Cocoon servlet context and into its own context (just letting Tomcat serve directly). 
      An even better approach would be to use a front-end webserver to serve the static, but 
      installing Apache + Tomcat + our Cocoon app would be a bit much when Tomcat + our Cocoon 
      app is doing fine.</li>

      <li>Disable resource reloading. The disk I/O system could become the
      bottleneck.</li>

      <li>Search for messages such as "decommissioning instance of...". This reveals some 
      undersized pools which are corrected by tuning cocoon.xconf and sitemap.xmap. 
      Undersized pools act like an object factory, plus the ComponentManager
      overhead.</li>
   </ul> 
 </s1>
 
 <s1 title="Caching and Pooling">
   <ul>
     <li>Fine-tune the pool sizes for components in the files cocoon.xconf and
     sitemap.xmap. If the pools are too small for the load this will have a great
     impact on your performance. The goal is to achieve such a configuration that for 
     every request there is a free component in the pool. Suppose, you have up 
     to 100 simultaneous requests and your pipelines have up to 2 xslt 
     transformers, then you need to set the maximum pool size to 200 xslt 
     transformers. They will be created when needed and retained to the pool 
     for future use.
     </li>
   
     <li>Fine-tune the Cocoon settings for the store and the other stuff.</li>

     <li>Important is the size of the documents that will be cached, because
     caching appears to be very time consuming process.</li>

     <li>Use the Caching Pipelines in your sitemaps where relevant.</li>
     <li>If your cache is set too small to keep the entire XML in memory,
      then the cache will be of no benefit.</li>

     <li>Watch the cachability in the log files, and make sure that things
      are being fed from the cache.</li>
     <li>Only use dynamic data when it is needed. Dynamic pages can't be
      cached 100%.</li>

     <li>Don't put Cocoon webapp too deep into directory structure. Cache
     keys contain absolute file names (or hash values of the absolute file
     names - in 2.0.X series), and the deeper cocoon is located in the
     filesystem, the longer keys are becoming. Obviously, longer keys will
     take more time to process them. In worst case scenario, slowdown up to
     10% could be achieved (unscientific observations, do your own
     test).</li>
     
   </ul>
     <p>More information about caching can be found 
       <link href="userdocs/concepts/caching.html">in the Caching documentation</link>.
       Especially look at the information about the expires configuration.
     </p>
 </s1>
 
 <s1 title="JVM and OS">
   <ul>
      <li>Consider using a good JVM on a good OS. Scalability is a very
      different beast than pure speed. An Apple DualG4 866 seems to run faster
      than a Sun Enterprise 4500 (and costs a fraction), but try hitting them
      with 2000 concurrent Cocoon requests.</li>

      <li>Fine-tune your JVM settings (max heap-size, initial memory, s.o.).
      Please read the <link 
      href="http://java.sun.com/docs/hotspot/PerformanceFAQ.html">Java Performance
      FAQ's</link> and the <link href="http://java.sun.com/docs/hotspot/gc/index.html">Tuning
      Garbage Collection</link> Document.</li>

      <li>Don't specify the -Xms parameter.</li>

      <li>Set the <code>-Xnoclassgc</code> parameter on the Sun JDK 1.3.1!
      It reduces the frequency of need for garbage collection by permitting the 
      memory allocated to unused classes to be reused (instead of having to be 
      collected and/or compacted).  Less fragmentation means less collection
      means better response times.</li>
   </ul>
 </s1>
 
 <s1 title="Perfomance Formulas">
   <ul>
     <li>Consider following formula for Pipeline Processing:<br />
     <code>Number_of_simultaneous_users * depth_of_content_aggregation</code>
     </li>

     <li>Consider following formula for Generators/Transformers/Serializers:<br />
     <code>Amount_required_to_process_one_request * Number_of_simultaneous_users</code>
     </li>

     <li>Consider following formula for Connectors:<br />
     <code>Count_of_pipeline_components_to_process_one_request * 
     Number_of_simultaneous_users</code></li>

   </ul>
 </s1>
 
 <s1 title="Pipelines">
   <ul>
     <li>Keep an eye on the overall complexity of pipelines.</li>

     <li>Try to keep the size of the documents going through the pipeline
     small. To big documents slows down translation.</li>

     <li>Use the Caching Pipelines in your sitemaps where relevant.</li>
     
     <li>Use the <code>expires</code> parameter (see above) as frequently as you can.
     	It improves the end user experience dramatically. Browsers and intermediate
     	proxy servers love the HTTP <code>Expires</code> header.</li>
   </ul>
 </s1>
 
 <s1 title="XSP">
   <p>Consider turning your XSPs into Generators by hand and call them
    directly. Of course you don't need to do this for all pages, but it's 
    recommended to it for those which are heavy loaded.</p>
   <p>You can try it this way:</p>
   <p>Cocoon will compile your XSP's into Java classes 
    (see tomcat/work/..../org/apache/cocoon/www/my_xsp.class). After that, add
    the generated Generator to the Sitemap:<br />
    <code>
     &lt;map:generator type="myXSP" src="org.apache.cocoon.www.my_xsp"/&gt;
    </code>
   </p>
   <p>And use it:<br />
    <code>
     &lt;map:generate type="myXSP"/&gt;
    </code>
   </p>
 </s1>
 
 <s1 title="XSLT and XSL">
   <note>For more tips and information about XSL and XSLT grep the Internet and the 
   <link href="http://xml.apache.org/xalan-j/index.html">Xalan Homepage</link>
   </note>
 
   <ul>
    <li>Try to keep the number of templates in the XSL translation small.</li>

    <li>There are several ways of doing the same stuff in XSLT, test the 
    difference between them.</li>

    <li>Consider browser-dependent targetting to perform client-side XSLT.
    Cocoon is very fast if it doesn't do transformations. IE 5.5 and 6 are
    pretty compliant and might be something around 30% of your hits
    (probably more on some popular public web sites like Nasa's). Reducing
    one/third of the transformations might speed up a LOT.</li>

   <li>How complicated are the XSLT stylesheets? If you are not using global 
   variables or parameters this will speeds things up.</li>
   
   <li>Consider using XSLTC instead of Xalan. XSLTC compiles XSLT to bytecode (translets)
   	the first time a stylesheet is used. Consequently it uses the compiled code
   	which is faster by a magnitude than the interpreted one.</li>
   	 
   </ul>
  </s1>
 </body>
</document>
