<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>User Documentation</title>
  <subtitle>Overview</subtitle>
  <authors>
   <person name="cocoon-dev" email="dev@cocoon.apache.org"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>
 <s1 title="Overview">

  <p>In getting started with Cocoon, one must learn not only a number of
  concepts, but a number of details as well.  Read the Introduction and ensure that you
  understand concepts such as the sitemap, generators, transformers, serializers
  and actions.  This guide will fill in the details, such as "So how do I turn
  this query into XML data".
  </p>
   <p>If you are interested in developing real-world web-applications requiring
    form handling, authentication or even developing your own portal, have a 
    look at the <link href="../developing/webapps/index.html">web application documentation</link>.</p>
  <p>
   If you've been writing web applications with any other system you should 
   also take a look at Cocoon <link href="flow/index.html">Control Flow</link>,
   which makes writing complex Web applications easy with Cocoon. Complex multi-page 
   interactions can be <link href="flow/continuations.html">described</link> easily as 
   blocking function calls.
  </p>
  <p>
  Come back often...this guide is being updated regularly.
  </p>

  <p>The actual user documentation is available from the side-panel.
  </p>

 </s1>
    <s1 title="What do you need to know before taking-off with Cocoon?">
      <p>Well, the question above is not that easy to answer. It depends on what you
         want to do with Cocoon. If you are a usual user, then you can use Cocoon
         without ever coding Java or knowing how exactly servlet containers work.
         If you become an experienced user of Cocoon you might want to tweak
         and tune your application. Therefore it is helpful to know Java and
         some basics of servlet containers.
      </p>
      <p>  
         However, if you want to develop with Cocoon (building own components
         to extend Cocoon for example), then you need to program Java. So, we
         split up this description into two sections: one for users and one for
         developers.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="The usual Cocoon User profile">
      <p>Before getting started, you should understand some basics for building
         web applications. This knowledge is not specific to Cocoon; it is useful
         for using any web framework.
      </p>
    <ul>
      <li>HTTP and the Request/Response cycle</li>
      <li>Extensible Markup Language (XML)</li>
      <li>Extensible Stylesheet Language (XSL)</li>
      <li>HTML</li>
    </ul>
    <p>As Cocoon enforces the separation of concerns you usually don't have
      to care about all these technologies at once. If you are the web
      application developer, you worry more about the request/response
      cycle and XML. A designer for instance has to have more knowledge
      about XML, XSL and HTML. But as always, it's good if you know
      at least something about the other aspects as well, even if you
      don't need them right now.</p>
    </s1>

 </body>
</document>
