<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<page>
    <content>
        <h2>Architecture</h2>
        <p>
            Cocoon is written in java and based on the
            <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/">Apache Avalon</a> components framework.
        </p>
        <p>
            Modular <em>blocks</em> can be enabled by configuration when installing Cocoon,
            allowing you to have either a small and focused system, or a "kitchen sink" installation
            with all possible options.
        </p>
        <p>
            Many of Cocoon's <em>core components</em> and <em>blocks</em> reuse
            Open-Source libraries, many from other Apache projects and some from outside
            the Apache Software Foundation.
        </p>
        <p>
            The <em>caching subsystem</em> uses sophisticated yet very customizable caching
            algorithms to maximize performance. Although some components or blocks might use a
            lot of resources (for example when generating PDF documents or bitmapped images), the Cocoon
            core itself is very efficient and can be tuned to maximize performance under high
            loads.
        </p>

        <h2>Licensing</h2>
        <p>
            Cocoon is distributed under the liberal
            <em><a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/">Apache License</a></em>
            which maximises its use while still providing protection.
        </p>

        <h2>Community</h2>
        <p>
            The Cocoon project lives through its <em>contributors</em> and <em>committers</em>, a
            community which is recognized for being friendly and efficient. Discussions take
            place on the <em>mailing lists</em> and IRC channels, and conferences or informal mettings
            called <em>GetTogethers</em> happen in various places.
        </p>
        <p>
            The current team comprises more than 40 active committers, of which about 20
            are regularly active. Those committers and the wider Cocoon
            community contribute new components, bug fixes, tests and
            documentation, and provide user support to each other.
        </p>

    </content>
</page>
