<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<page>
    <content>
        <p class="note">
            All documents and files included in this tour are
            Copyright (C) 1999-2004 by the Apache Software Foundation.
            <br/>
            This tour was originally created by Bertrand Delacrétaz
            and donated to the Cocoon project in May 2004.
        </p>
        <p class="note">
            You can generate a printable single-page version of this tour
            <a href="../../print/supersonic-tour.html">here</a> (requires
            an Internet connection for some example pages).
        </p>
        <h2>Overview</h2>
        <p>
            This <em>supersonic tour of Apache Cocoon</em> will give
            you a quick overview of what Cocoon is and does.
        </p>
        <p>
            We won't go deep into any part of Cocoon, but will rather
            get an overall feel of what's in Cocoon.
        </p>
        <p>
            The only parts that we will study in some detail are the
            following Cocoon components, which are becoming the
            mainstream way of using Cocoon:
            <ul>
                <li>
                    The <em>pipelines</em>, used to transform
                    XML data obtained from various sources into
                    many differents output formats like HTML, PDF,
                    SVG, XML, bitmapped pictures, etc.
                </li>

                <li>
                    The <em>Flow subsystem</em>, a powerful yet simple
                    to use mechanism to handle the interaction between
                    multiple web pages and forms in a Web application.
                </li>

                <li>
                    The <em>Cocoon Forms</em> subsystem, which uses
                    simple and modular definitions of Web-based forms
                    to allow java beans, XML documents or other objects
                    to be edited via the Web.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </p>

        <h2>Running this application</h2>
        <p>
            If you're reading this documentation on paper and would like
            to study the application directly in Cocoon, you will find it under
            <em>blocks with samples</em> on the Cocoon samples page.

        </p>

        <h2>Studying this application</h2>
        <p>
            The complete source code of this tour is found under
            <em>src/blocks/tour</em> in the Cocoon source code tree.
            There is one directory with its own sitemap for each part of
            the tutorial, so that you can easily dig deeper in your areas
            of interest.
        </p>

        <h2>Code excerpts</h2>
        <p>
            Note that (according to the <em>lazyness is a virtue</em> rule),
            most of the sitemap, flowscripts, XSLT transforms and
            other code excerpts are dynamically inserted into this documentation
            from the corresponding source files. This avoids having to
            copy and paste code and ensures that the code you see stays up to date.
        </p>

        <h2>Contents</h2>
        <insert-toc/>
    </content>
</page>
