<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<page>
    <content>
        <p>
            Depending on who you ask, you might get different answers: Cocoon 2 has become
            a rather big project, or more precisely a rather big collection of modular
            components, and as such means different things to different people.
        </p>
        <p>
            Today, more than 40 <em>blocks</em> are available to acquire, process and publish
            XML data, and to build interactive applications based on XML and java technologies.
            Cocoon does not contain millions of lines of codes, but rather reuses a lot of
            Open-Source tools and libraries, combining them in a very modular way.
        </p>
        <p>
            In the beginning, Cocoon was only a <em>web publishing framework</em>, meant to
            convert different document types to HTML, PDF and similar formats for publishing.
        </p>
        <p>
            Today, and especially with the <em>Cocoon Forms</em> and <em>Flow</em> components
            that we're going to discuss, Cocoon is becoming a full-blown web applications framework,
            covering a large set of use cases and targeting different styles of developers.
        </p>
        <p>
            By covering the mainstream aspects of Cocoon as it stands at the beginning of 2004,
            this <em>supersonic tour</em> will help you get a feel of what Cocoon is about, and
            help you find your way in this big collection of components.
        </p>
    </content>
</page>
