<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
	 <title>Caching</title>
	 <version>0.9</version>
	 <type>Technical document</type>
	 <authors><person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org"/>
	 </authors>
	 <abstract>This document explains the basic caching algorithm of Apache Cocoon.</abstract>
  </header>
  <body>
	 <s1 title="Goal">
		<p>This document explains the basic caching algorithm of Apache Cocoon.</p>
	 </s1>
	 <s1 title="Overview">
		<p>The caching algorithm of Cocoon has a very flexible and powerful design.
           The algorithms and components used are not hard coded into the core of 
           Cocoon. They can be configured in the sitemap.</p>
            <p>This document describes the components available for caching,
               how they can be configured and how to implement your own cacheable components.
            </p>
	 </s1>
	 <s1 title="How to Configure Caching">
	     <p>The caching can be turned on and off on a per pipeline setting in the sitemap.
	      This means, for each <em>map:pipeline</em> section in a sitemap, it's possible to
	      turn on/off caching and configure the caching algorithm.</p>
	      <p>The following example shows how to turn on caching for a pipeline:</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
       <map:pipeline type="caching">
          ...
       </map:pipeline>
     ]]>
    </source> 
	      <p>If you know that it doesn't make sense to turn on caching for some of 
	      your pipelines, put them together in their own section and use:</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
       <map:pipeline type="noncaching">
          ...
       </map:pipeline>
     ]]>
    </source>
      <p>As you might guess from how the caching is turned on (via a type attribute), you
         can have different caching (or better pipeline) implementation to choose from. This
         is similar to choose from a set of generators the generator to use in your pipeline etc.
         You will find in your main sitemap a section declaring all pipeline implementations.
         It's in the <em>map:components</em> section:
      </p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
       <map:pipes default="caching">
          <map:pipe name="caching" src="..."/>
          <map:pipe name="noncaching" src="..."/>
       </map:pipes>
     ]]>
    </source>
      <p>Depending on your Cocoon installation you might have different implementations in
      that section. As with all components, you can define a default for all pipelines and
      override this whereever it makes sense.</p>
	 </s1>
	 <s1 title="The Default Caching Algorithm">
		<p>The default algorithm uses a very easy but effective approach
           to cache a request: The pipeline process is cached up to the most 
           possible point.</p>
        <p>Therefore each component in the pipeline is queried by Cocoon if it
        supports caching. Several components, like the file generator or the xslt
        transformer support caching. However, dynamic components like the sql transformer
        or the cinclude transformer do not. Let's have a look at some examples:</p>
		<s2 title="Simple Examples">
		  <p>If you have the following pipeline:</p>
          <p>Generator[type=file|src=a.xml] -> Transformer[type="xslt"|src=a.xsl] -> Serializer</p>
		  <p>The file generator is cacheable and generates a key which uses the src 
             (or the filename) to build the key. The cache uses the last modification date of the xml file
             to test if the cached content is valid.</p>
  		  <p>The xslt transformer is cacheable and generates a key which uses
             the filename to build the unique key. The cache validity object
             uses the last modification date of the xslt file.</p>
          <p>The default serializer (html) supports the caching as well.</p>
  		  <p>All three keys are used to build a unique key for this pipeline.
             The first time it is invoked its response is cached. The second time
             this pipeline is called, the cached content is get from the cache.
             If it is still valid, the cached content is directly send to the client.</p>
        </s2>
        <s2 title="Complex Example">
		   <p>Only part of the following pipeline is cached:</p>
           <p>Generator[type=file|src=a.xml] -> Transformer[type="xslt"|src=a.xsl] -> Transformer[type=sql] -> Transformer[type="xslt"|src=b.xsl] -> Serializer</p>
 		  <p>The file generator is cacheable and generates a key which uses the src 
             (or the filename) to build the key. The cache uses the last modification date of the xml file
             to test if the cached content is valid.</p>
   		  <p>The xslt transformer is cacheable and generates a key which uses
             the filename to build the unique key. The cache validity object
             uses the last modification date of the xslt file.</p>
 		  <p>The sql transformer is not cacheable, so the caching algorithm stops
 			   at this point although the last transformer is cacheable again.</p>
 		  <p>The cached response is the output of the first xslt transformer, so when the
 		    next request comes in and the cached content is valid, the cached content is
 		    directly feed into the sql transformer. The generator and the first
 		    xslt transformer are not executed.</p>
	    </s2>
	    <s2 title="Making Components Cacheable">
	      <p>This chapter is only for developers of own sitemap components. It details what you have
	        to do when you want that your own sitemap components supports the caching.</p>
	      <p>Each sitemap component (generator or transformer) which might be
            cacheable must implement the CacheableProcessingComponent interface. When the
            pipeline is processed each sitemap component starting with
           the generator is asked if it implements this interface. This
           test stops either when the first component does not implement
           the CacheableProcessingComponent interface or when the first cacheable component is
           currently not cacheable for any reasons (more about this in a moment).</p>
	      <p>The CacheableProcessingComponent interface declares a method <code>getKey()</code>
           which must produce a unique key for this sitemap component inside
           the component space. For example the FileGenerator returns the
           source argument (the xml document read). All parameters/values
           which are used for the processing of the request by the generator must
           be used for this key. If, e.g. the request parameters are used by
           the component, it must build a key with respect to the current request
           parameters. The key can be any serializable java object.</p>
         <p>If for any reason the sitemap component detects that the current request
           is not cacheable it can simply return <code>null</code> as the key. This has
          the same effect as not declaring the CacheableProcessingComponent interface.</p>
    	<p>Now after the key is build for this particular request, it is looked up
           in the cache if it exists. If not, the new request is generated and cached
           for further requests.</p>
         <p>If a cached response is found for the key, the caching algorithm checks
           if this response is still valid. For this check each cacheable component
           returns a validity object when the method <code>getValidity</code>
           is invoked. (If a cacheable component returns <code>null</code> it
           is temporarily not cacheable, like returning <code>null</code> for the key.)</p>
           <p>A <code>SourceValidity</code> object contains all information the component
           needs to verify if the cached content is still valid. For example the
           file generator stores the last modification date of the xml document parsed
           in the validity object.</p>
          <p>When a response is cached all validity objects are stored together with
            the cached response in the cache. Actually the <code>CachedResponse</code>
            is stored which encapsulates all this information.</p>
          <p>When a new response is generated and the key is build, the caching
           algorithm also collects all uptodate cache validity objects. So if the
           cached response is found in the cache these validity objects are compared.
           If they are valid (or equal) the cached response is used and feed into
           the pipeline. If they are not valid any more the cached response is removed
           from the cache, the new response is generated and then stored together with
           the new validity objects in the cache.</p>
        </s2>
	 </s1>
	 <s1 title="Configuration">
		<p>The caching of Cocoon can be completely configured by different Avalon
               components. This chapter describes how the various components work
               together.</p>            
		<s2 title="Configuration of Pipelines">
			<p>Each pipeline can be configured with a buffer size, and each
			  caching pipeline with the name of the Cache to use.</p>
     	<s3 title="Expiration of Content">
     	<p>
     	Utilize the pipeline <code>expires</code> parameter to dramatically reduce
     	redundand requests. Even the most dynamic application pages have a 
     	reasonable period of time during which they are static. 
     	Even if a page doesn't change for just one minute, still use the 
     	<code>expires</code> parameter. Here is an example:
     	</p>
<source><![CDATA[
<map:pipeline>
  <map:parameter name="expires" value="access plus 1 minutes"/>
  ...
</map:pipeline> 
]]></source>
		<p>
     	The value of the parameter is in a format borrowed from the Apache HTTP module mod_expires.
     	Examples of other possible values are:
     	</p>
<source><![CDATA[
access plus 1 hours
access plus 1 month
access plus 4 weeks
access plus 30 days
access plus 1 month 15 days 2 hours
]]></source>
     	<p>
     	Imagine 1'000 users hitting your web site at the same time.
     	Say that they are split into 5 groups, each of which has the same ISP.
     	Most ISPs use intermediate proxy servers to reduce traffic, hense
     	improving their end user experience and also reducing their operating costs.
     	In our case the 1'000 end user requests will result in just 5 requests to Cocoon.
     	</p>
     	<p>
     	After the first request from each group reaches the server, the expires header will
     	be recognized by the proxy servers which will serve the following requests from their cache.
     	Keep in mind however that most proxies cache HTTP GET requests, but will not cache HTTP POST requests.
     	</p>
     	<p>
		 To feel the difference, set an expires parameter on one of your pipelines and
		 load the page with the browser. Notice that after the first time, there are no 
		 access records in the server logs until the specified time expires.
     	</p>
     	<p>This parameter has effect on all pipeline implementations, even on 
     	the non caching ones. Remember, the caching does not take place in Cocoon,
     	it's either in a proxy inbetween Cocoon and the client or in the client
     	itself.</p>
         </s3>
         <s3 title="Response Buffering">
          <p>Each pipeline can buffer the response, before it is send to the client.
            The default buffer size is unlimited (-1), which means when all bytes of
            the response are available on the server, they are send with one
            command directly to the client.</p>
          <p>Of course, this slows down the response as the whole response
            is first buffered inside Cocoon and then send to the client instead of
            directly sending the parts of the response when they are available.
            But on the other hand this is very important for error handling. If you
            don't buffer the response and an error occurs, you might get corrupt
            pages. Example: you have a pipeline that already send some content
            to the client and now an exception occurs. This exception "calls"
            the error handler that generates a new response that is appended
            to the already send content. If content is already send to the client
            there is no way of reverting this! So buffering in these cases makes
            sense.
           </p>
           <p>If you have a stable application running in production where the
           error handler is never invoked, you can turn off the buffering, by
           setting the buffer to <em>0</em>.</p>
           <p>You can set the buffer to any other value higher than 0 which means
           the content of the response is buffered in Cocoon until the buffer is
           full. If the buffer is full it's flushed and the next part of the
           response is buffered again. If you know the maximum size of your
           content than you can fine tune the buffer handling with this.</p>
           <p>You can set the default buffer size for each pipeline implementation
            at the declaration of the pipeline. Example:</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
        <map:pipe name="noncaching" src="...">
            <parameter name="outputBufferSize" value="2048"/>
        </map:pipe>
     ]]>
    </source>
          <p>The above configuration sets the buffer size to <em>2048</em> for the
          non caching pipeline. Please note, that the parameter element does not
          have the sitemap namespace!</p>
          <p>You can override the buffer size in each <em>map:pipeline</em> section:</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
        <map:pipeline type="noncaching">
            <map:parameter name="outputBufferSize" value="4096"/>
            ...
        </map:pipeline>
     ]]>
    </source>
          <p>The above parameters sets the buffer size to <em>4096</em> for this
          particular pipeline. Please note, that the parameter element does have
          the sitemap namespace!</p>
         </s3>
	    </s2>
		<s2 title="Configuration of Caches">
			<p>Each cache can be configured with the store to use.</p>
	    </s2>
		<s2 title="Configuration of Stores">
			<p>Have a look at the store configuration.</p>
	    </s2>
 	 </s1>
 	 <s1 title="Additional Information for Developers">
  	   <s2 title="Java APIs">
		<p>For more information on the java apis refer directly to the
               javadocs of Cocoon.</p>
            <p>The most important packages are:</p>
		<ol>
			<li><code>org.apache.cocoon.caching</code>: This package declares all interfaces for caching.</li>
			<li><code>org.apache.cocoon.components.pipeline</code>: The interfaces and implementations of the pipelines.</li>
		</ol>
  	   </s2>
		<s2 title="The XMLSerializer/XMLDeserializer">
			<p>The caching of the sax events is implemented by two Avalon components: 
                     The XMLSerializer and the XMLDeserializer. The XMLSerializer gets
                     sax events and creates an object which is used by the XMLDeserializer
                     to recreate these sax events.</p>
			<s3 title="org.apache.cocoon.components.sax.XMLByteStreamCompiler">
			      <p>The <code>XMLByteStreamCompiler</code>compiles sax events into a byte stream.</p>
			</s3>
			<s3 title="org.apache.cocoon.components.sax.XMLByteStreamInterpreter">
				<p>The <code>XMLByteStreamInterpreter</code> is the counterpart of the 
				   <code>XMLByteStreamCompiler</code>. It interprets the byte
                           stream and creates sax events.</p>
			</s3> 
			<s3 title="Configuration">
			<p>The XMLSerializer and XMLDeserialzer are two Avalon components which
			   can be configured in the cocoon.xconf:</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
<xml-serializer
    class="org.apache.cocoon.components.sax.XMLByteStreamCompiler"/>

<xml-deserializer
    class="org.apache.cocoon.components.sax.XMLByteStreamInterpreter"/>
     ]]>
    </source> 
			<p>You must assure that the correct (or matching) deserializer is 
                     configured for the serializer.</p>
            <p>Both components are poolable, so make sure you set appropriate pool sizes
               for these components. For more information on component pooling have a look
               at the Avalon documentation.</p>
		</s3>
		</s2>
 	 </s1>
 
  </body>
</document>
