<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
    <title>Modules</title>
    <authors>
      <person name="Christian Haul" email="haul@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <s1 title="Introduction">
      <p>
        Many sitemap components serve a purpose regardless how the input is
        obtained. Still, to provide a wide range of components to quickly get
        you up to speed, variants for different inputs exist. Modules allow to
        create generic components and plug-in input or output later.
      </p>
      <p>
        This document will explain how modules work and how to make use of
        them. If you plan on writing your own modules, it is highly recommended
        to read <fork
          href="http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon/developing/index.html">
          Developing With Apache Avalon</fork>. It is a very good description
        of the underlying rationale and principles.
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Types of Modules">
      <p>
        Currently, three different types of modules exist: Input modules
        provide means to enumerate attributes and to retrieve them, output
        modules allow storing of data and exhibit transaction like semantics,
        database modules encapsulate different mechanisms for auto increment
        columns of various database management systems. Please refer to the
        javadoc documentation of these interfaces.
      </p>
      <p>
        Input modules are modelled after request attributes. The main
        difference is, that every method takes two additional arguments, the
        request object and a configuration object. The configuration object is
        used to allow arbitrarily complex instructions for the input module.
        Apart from that, input modules are more or less a drop-in replacement.
      </p>
      <p>
        Output modules are again very similar to using request
        attributes. Basically, they provide a method to set an attribute to a
        value. Again, a request and a configuration object is the only change
        to request attributes. A fundamental difference is, however, that
        output modules should exhibit transactional behaviour. Thus setting an
        attributes implicitly starts a transaction that must be ended by
        calling rollback or commit. Only if the transaction is completed by
        calling commit, the values set should be visible. This is needed
        e.g. by the database actions.
      </p>
      <p>
        Database modules, actually named AutoIncrementModule, contains
        configuration information how to retrieve a value for an auto increment
        column. It is possible to obtain the value before inserting a row,
        while inserting as part of the SQL or after successful insert. If the
        value is obtained before inserting, it can be generated
        externally. Currently, supported database management systems include
        HSQL, Informix, MySQL, and querying the database for the current max
        value. 
      </p>
    </s1>
    <s1 title="Using modules">
      <p>
        Using any of these modules requires a two step setup process. Step one
        has already been done for your for all modules that come with Apache
        Cocoon. Exception to this rule are the auto increment modules: only the
        HSQL module is already setup.
      </p>
      <s2 title="Step 1: Making a new module known to Apache Cocoon">
        <p>
          Like other core components of Apache Cocoon, modules are declared in
          <code>cocoon.xconf</code>. There are already too many to list here.
        </p>
        <source>
<![CDATA[
<input-modules>
  <component-instance name="request"   
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.input.RequestParameterModule"/>

  <component-instance name="attribute" 
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.input.RequestAttributeModule"/>

  <component-instance name="URI"       
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.input.RequestURIModule"/>

  <component-instance name="context"       
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.input.RequestContextPathModule"/>

  <component-instance name="header"    
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.input.HeaderAttributeModule"/>

  <component-instance name="session"   
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.input.SessionAttributeModule"/>

  <component-instance name="date"      
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.input.DateInputModule"/>

  <component-instance name="defaults"  
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.input.DefaultsModule">
    <input-module name="request"/>
    <values>
      <skin>defaultSkin</skin>
      <base-url>http://localhost:8080/cocoon</base-url>
    </values>
  </component-instance>
</input-modules>

<output-modules>
  <component-instance name="attribute" 
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.output.RequestAttributeOutputModule"/>

  <component-instance name="session"   
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.output.SessionAttributeOutputModule"/>
</output-modules>

<autoincrement-modules>
  <component-instance name="auto" 
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.database.HsqlIdentityAutoIncrementModule"/>

  <!--
  <component-instance name="auto" 
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.database.ManualAutoIncrementModule"/>
  <component-instance name="auto" 
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.database.IfxSerialAutoIncrementModule"/>
  <component-instance name="auto" 
  class="org.apache.cocoon.components.modules.database.MysqlAutoIncrementModule"/>
  -->
</autoincrement-modules>]]>
        </source>
        <p>
          The above snippet declares a number of modules. After this, the
          modules are accessible through the given name. Thus, when an
          <code>input-module</code> is expected, it is sufficient to give the
          name of a module, like <code>header</code>.
        </p>
        <p>
          For the auto increment modules only one is declared as the name
          <code>"auto"</code> has special meaning to the modular database
          actions. If more than one is needed at the same time, the
          configuration of the database actions needs to explicitly specify
          which one to use.
        </p>
      </s2>
      <s2 title="Step 2: Use it">
        <p>
          The following alternatives for using modules exist:
        </p>
        <s3 title="Step 2a: Use it as sitemap variable">
          <p>
            Input modules can be used in a sitemap almost like a sitemap
            variable. If the variable name contains a colon (":"), the
            preceeding string is used as the name of the module to use and the
            trailing string is passed to the module. The expression is replaced
            with the string value returned from the module.
          </p>
          <source>
<![CDATA[
<map:transform src="resources/stylesheets/{../skin}.xsl"/>]]>
          </source>
          <p>
            The above example uses the variable <code>skin</code> declared
            e.g. by an action for the stylesheet to apply to the page. The
            example below uses an input module instead. The way this module was
            declared above allows to override the skin with a request parameter
            named "skin".
          </p>
          <source>
<![CDATA[
<map:transform src="resources/stylesheets/{default:skin}.xsl"/>]]>
          </source>
          <p>
            Some of the input modules are JXPath-enabled, so you can use
            XPath expressions to access values (see Input Modules sample for details).
            The following example demonstrates the use of XPath function 
            with <code>system-property</code> module.
          </p>
	  <source>
<![CDATA[
<map:parameter name="users-home-base"
  value="{system-property:substring-before(user.home, user.name)}"/>]]>
	  </source>
        </s3>
        <s3 title="Step 2b: Use it on an XSP">
          <p>
            The input logicsheet allows easy use of InputModules from an
            XSP. Currently, it provides tags for getting one value, an
            array of values, and an Iterator for a Collection of
            parameter names.
          </p>
          <source>
<![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<xsp:page language="java"
    xmlns:xsp="http://apache.org/xsp"  
    xmlns:input="http://apache.org/cocoon/xsp/input/1.0">

  <page>
    <title>Testing InputModules</title>

    <p>
      Parameter name=<input:get-attribute module="request-param"
                       as="string" name="module" default="John Doe"/>;
    </p>
    <p>
      Parameter cars=<input:get-attribute-values module="request-param" 
                       as="xml" name="car"/>;
    </p>
  </page>
</xsp:page>]]>
          </source>
        </s3>
        <s3 title="Step 2c: Have sitemap components use a module">
          <p>
            This depends on the component that is to be used. As an example the
            <code>CachingWildcardMatcher</code> requires to set the
            <code>input-module</code> on declaration.
          </p>
          <source>
<![CDATA[
<map:matchers default="wildcard">
  <map:matcher name="cached-uri" 
      src="org.apache.cocoon.matching.modular.CachingWildcardMatcher">
    <input-module name="URI"/>
  </map:matcher>
</map:matchers>]]>
          </source>
          <p>
            By replacing the input module name with any of the other declared
            input modules, this matcher can be used to match e.g. on session
            attributes, request headers or even dates!
          </p>
        </s3>
      </s2>
    </s1>
  </body>
</document>
