<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "./dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Installing Cocoon2</title>
  <authors>
   <person name="Stefano Mazzocchi" email="stefano@apache.org"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>

 <s1 title="System Requirements">
  <p>
   Cocoon requires the following systems to be already installed in your
   system:
  </p>

  <ul>
   <li><strong>Java Virtual Machine</strong>
    A Java 1.1 or greater compatible virtual machine must be present for both
    command line and servlet type usage of Cocoon. Note that all servlet engines
    require a JVM to run so if you are already using servlets you already have
    one installed.
   </li>
   <li><strong>Servlet Engine</strong>
    A Servlet 2.x compliant servlet engine  must be present in order to support
    servlet operation and dynamic request handling. Note that this requirement
    is optional for command line operation.
   </li>
  </ul>
 </s1>

 <s1 title="Required Components">
  <p>
   Cocoon is a publishing framework and was designed to be highly modular to
   allow users to choose their preferred implementation for the required
   component and to allow better and faster parallel development.
  </p>

  <p>
   Previous releases of Cocoon forced you to download all the basic required
   packages for the installation, but this generated lots of problems for
   lack of synch between the projects and the complexity of the operation.
   For this reason, Cocoon now ships with all the required packages,
   a sort of a simple distribution to make things easier for you. We apologize
   for the increased size of the distribution, but we think this will be
   worthwhile even for users with low bandwidth.
  </p>

  <p>
   In the <code>/lib</code> directory you'll find all the required packages.
   Now jump to the installation instructions for your servlet engine.
  </p>

  <note>
   The Ant and Stylebook packages are only used in the build system and
   are <strong>not</strong> used by Cocoon at run-time. So you can safely
   ignore them in the installation.
  </note>
 </s1>

 <s1 title="Installing Cocoon 2">
  <p>
   Being Cocoon a servlet, you should be able to install it on every compliant
   servlet engine by associating the "org.apache.cocoon.servlet.CocoonServlet" 
   servlet with the requests you want it to handle. In order to do this, there 
   is no standard way, so we try to provide detailed information for the most 
   used servlet systems.
  </p>

  <s2 title="Installing Cocoon2 on Apache JServ">
   <p>
    First thing to do is to make sure that Cocoon and all the needed components
    (as explained in the previous section) are visible. This implies adding
    this to the servlet engine classpath by adding a bunch of classpath lines
    to your <code>jserv.properties</code> file for each jar package.
   </p>

<source>wrapper.classpath=[path-to-jar]/[jar-name].jar</source>

   <p>
    Here is an example:
   </p>

<source>
wrapper.classpath=/usr/local/java/lib/xerces.jar
wrapper.classpath=/usr/local/java/lib/xalan.jar
wrapper.classpath=/usr/local/java/lib/fop.jar
...
</source>

   <note>
    We suggest you <strong>do not</strong> place the package <code>cocoon.jar</code> in the
    classpath but rather follow the instructions in details. 
   </note>

   <note>
    JServ is a Servlet 2.0 compliant servlet engine and will not work if you
    place the Servlet_2.2.jar in its classpath. So ignore the servlet_2.2.jar
    package that is shipped with Cocoon if you use Jserv.
   </note>

   <p>
    At this point, you must installe the Cocoon package and set the Cocoon 
    configurations. To do this, you must choose the servlet zone(s) where you 
    want Cocoon to reside. If you don't know what a servlet zone is, open the
    <code>zone.properties</code> file.
   </p>

   <p>
    To configure Cocoon, you must pass the <code>cocoon.xconf</code>
    file location to the <em>cocoon</em> servlet and you do so by adding the 
    following lines to the servlet zone properties:
   </p>

<source>servlet.cocoon.code = org.apache.cocoon.servlet.CocoonServlet
servlet.cocoon.initArgs=configurations=[path-to-cocoon]/conf/cocoon.xconf</source>

   <p>
    That file contains XML configurations for Cocoon in order to do its job and
    you should not need to change <em>anything</em> to test Cocoon installation
    at this point.
   </p>

   <p>
    Now your cocoon servlet is properly configured, but you should tell Apache
    to direct any call to a resource you want Cocoon to process it. To do this
    add the following lines to your <code>jserv.conf</code> file:
   </p>

<source>Action cocoon /servlet/cocoon

<location /cocoon>
 SetHandler cocoon
</location>
</source>

   <p>
    Restart Apache (or just Apache JServ if in manual mode), then point your
    browser to the following URI:
   </p>

<source>http://localhost/cocoon/hello</source>

   <p>
    where Cocoon will greet you.
   </p>

   <note>
    If this doesn't work, it's a bug in Cocoon2. The above should be the correct
    behavior and we should aim to have Cocoon2 work that way. So, if it doesn't 
    work, please help us fixing it. Thank you!
   </note>
  </s2>

  <s2 title="Installing Cocoon2 on Jakarta Tomcat">
   <p>yet to be written. Volunteers welcome!</p>
  </s2>
 </s1>
</body>
</document>