<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "dtd/document-v10.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
  <title>Webapps Developer Documentation</title>
  <subtitle>Overview</subtitle>
    <authors>
      <person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org"/>
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
<s1 title="Overview">
 <p>This section contains several documents about developing real-world web applications
  with Cocoon.</p>
 <p>Some of these concepts are currently in development. The development of the
  <link href="session.html">Session handling</link>, the 
  <link href="authentication.html">authentication</link> framework and
  the <link href="portal.html">portal framework</link> is nearly finished. You will
  find these components in the latest CVS version of Cocoon. The documentation
  listed in the menu conforms to the current CVS version.</p>
 <p>However, the current release @released.version@ contains alpha versions in the
   scratchpad area of these three components. So you can already have a look at them. The
   documentation in the "scratchpad" folder contains the description conforming to the
   scratchpad. But be warned that they are in the scratchpad area and will change in 
   upcomming releases. So if you are really planning to use them, have a look at the
   latest CVS.
 </p>

 </s1>
    <s1 title="Introduction">
     <p>A session is a data storage which resides on the server and records
        information about one single user. Cocoon creates a session on demand and
        from that point of time the user is tracked and information can be stored
        inside the session. Each following request of this user is linked to the one
        specific session, so there is always only one session per user on the
        server.</p>
     <p>To avoid a fast growing amount of sessions on the server and the
        overcome potential security problems, a session has usually a valid period of
        time. If during this period no new request comes in from the user, the session
        object on the server will be destroyed by the server (this period of time is
        called session timeout). The web application often allows a user to explictly
        destroy a session.</p>
     <p>The usual web applications create sessions during login of a user and
        destroy them when the user logs out.</p>
     </s1>

  </body>
</document>
