<?xml version="1.0" ?> 
 <rss version="2.0">
 <channel>
  <title>Cocoon and more</title> 
  <link>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/</link> 
  <description>This is the personal weblog of Carsten Ziegeler.</description> 
  <copyright>Copyright 2003 Carsten Ziegeler</copyright> 
  <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2003 07:56:00 GMT</lastBuildDate> 
  <docs>http://backend.userland.com/rss</docs> 
  <generator>Radio UserLand v8.0.8</generator> 
  <managingEditor>cziegeler@s-und-n.de</managingEditor> 
  <webMaster>cziegeler@s-und-n.de</webMaster> 
  <category domain="http://www.weblogs.com/rssUpdates/changes.xml">rssUpdates</category> 
 <skipHours>
  <hour>23</hour> 
  <hour>0</hour> 
  <hour>1</hour> 
  <hour>2</hour> 
  <hour>3</hour> 
  <hour>4</hour> 
  <hour>5</hour> 
  <hour>6</hour> 
  </skipHours>
  <cloud domain="radio.xmlstoragesystem.com" port="80" path="/RPC2" registerProcedure="xmlStorageSystem.rssPleaseNotify" protocol="xml-rpc" /> 
  <ttl>60</ttl> 
 <item>
  <title>Growing Up</title> 
  <link>http://petergabriel.com/moonclub/tours/tour_page.html</link> 
  <description><P>Tomorrow: <A href="http://www.koenig-pilsener-arena.de/index.htm">Live in Oberhausen</A></P></description> 
  <guid>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/04/29.html#a111</guid> 
  <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2003 07:55:59 GMT</pubDate> 
  </item>
 <item>
  <title>Cocoon Milestone 1</title> 
  <link>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/04/28.html#a110</link> 
  <description>Hurray, it seems that Cocoon is reaching a new milestone: 2.1-M1 (a.k.a. 2.1-Beta1). Although we don't have such a detailed plan as for example Eclipse, I guess we will reach the release candidate phase this year :)</description> 
  <guid>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/04/28.html#a110</guid> 
  <pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2003 13:24:46 GMT</pubDate> 
  </item>
 <item>
  <title>Home, sweet home - sort of</title> 
  <link>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/04/28.html#a109</link> 
  <description>After travelling around for the last four weeks, I'm finally back in my home...eh...office and can work at my own desk again. Don't get me wrong, I like being at customer sites but most times you are limited with respect to emails, internet access, cvs etc.</description> 
  <guid>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/04/28.html#a109</guid> 
  <pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2003 13:23:28 GMT</pubDate> 
  </item>
 <item>
  <title>Books about open source</title> 
  <link>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/04/17.html#a108</link> 
  <description><P>I just read a book about using open source in own projects and I was a little bit disappointed. In general the book is good as it details different open source projects, for example for logging, for persistence, for server-site programming etc. And then I came to the Struts chapter...and read this: "Whenever you start a project, you should not ask 'can we use Struts for this?', you should ask 'Why not using Struts?' Struts is the perfect fit for every web application."</P> <P>Now, I really value Struts and I think it makes perfect sense in some cases, but Struts is not the golden hammer tool, if you understand what I mean. It doesn't make sense to use the same tool for every problem. This is nonsense for Struts and this is nonsense for Cocoon and this is nonsense for every server-site programming as well. </P> <P>The key in successful programming is to choose the right tools or frameworks or libraries for the job to do.</P></description> 
  <guid>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/04/17.html#a108</guid> 
  <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2003 13:51:26 GMT</pubDate> 
  </item>
 <item>
  <title>CruiseControl - the endless story has an end</title> 
  <link>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/04/07.html#a107</link> 
  <description><P>Finally I got CruiseControl 2.0.2 running - it wasn't that easy as the documentation is a little bit confusing, the default settings are unusable and sometimes you have to guess what the correct settings are.</P> <P>Ok, I guess, most of you have cruisecontrol or anthill or whatever running since years, anyway; but for me it's a little success because during the last months I accidentally tried to install it from time to time and always failed :(. But I never gave up!So after all: a little success.</P> <P>The next question is: Where to use it? Hmm....</P></description> 
  <guid>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/04/07.html#a107</guid> 
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2003 13:12:35 GMT</pubDate> 
  </item>
 <item>
  <title>New music</title> 
  <link>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/04/07.html#a106</link> 
  <description><P>Over the weekend I had some time to listen to some new music:</P> <P>The new album "Sleeping with Ghosts" from <A href="http://www.placeboworld.co.uk/">Placebo</A> is very good. Now, putting it simple: it's like the other albums with new songs. So if you like this kind of music, it's a must buy.</P> <P>The new album "Long gone before daylight" from the <A href="http://www.cardigans.com">Cardigans</A> is in my eyes not so good. The released single is nice to listen to (again, as always :) ), but the other songs are in my ears only nice, like the usual everyday songs.</P> <P>Next up is a copy of the latest Coldplay album - I only listened to two tracks.</P> <P>I will upload the albums to my (new) mp3 player with 20GB space for all my CDs; so I can listen everywhere to "my" music without carrying tons of CDs with me.</P></description> 
  <guid>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/04/07.html#a106</guid> 
  <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2003 12:28:13 GMT</pubDate> 
  </item>
 <item>
  <title>The Lion King</title> 
  <link>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/03/31.html#a105</link> 
  <description><P>Last week I visited the <A href="http://www.loewenkoenig.de/index2.php">Lion King</A> in Hamburg. It's really a great musical with very good sound and visual effects.</P> <P>Ok, the story is not very good and the texts are not very sophisticated - so, at the end it's like a good action movie: the story doesn't matter but the effects are worth seeing it. Especially the african music (sounded a little bit like some PG songs) and the interesting animal costumes.</P> <P>So, if you have time to see the musical, watch it! The stage is located in the habor of Hamburg at the opposite site of the city. So you can take a boat for free to travel over the river to the stage or you can use the old tunnel and walk by feet under(!) the river (which takes some time).</P></description> 
  <guid>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/03/31.html#a105</guid> 
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2003 13:38:43 GMT</pubDate> 
  </item>
 <item>
  <title>The Cocoon Family</title> 
  <link>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/03/31.html#a104</link> 
  <description><FONT size="2"> <P>Some users/readers might be wondering what's going on in Cocoonland and perhaps some users might get worried about the "mysterious things" taking place in the mailing list over the past weeks. And this might scare them.</P> <P>So, what's going on and what will be the meaning for Cocoon? Now, to be honest I currently don't know what's going on (well at least, I know some things that are happening, but unfortunately not all). But I'm trying to figure it out.</P> <P>So, what does this mean for using Cocoon? I really think: viewed globally: nothing. There were some bad comments over the last weeks, one important committer left the project (which is really sad) because of that, and currently others are thinking about leaving/taking a break as well. </P> <P>Everything seems quiet now, but I still think that the storm is not over yet. Perhaps we can get the new release out without any problems, but it's unlikely that sooner or later the same problems will arise, because I guess that the root of the problems is not really solved yet - and the root is not clearly visible by now, but again, I'm trying to figure it out.</P> <P>But on the other hand, there are many other committers keeping on the great work taking place over the last years, and there are many users helping as well. Most of them were active over the last years and are still committed to Cocoon, and they will not discontinue their work because of some stupid comments. And even more important, there is a big commercial committment to Cocoon, and all these (big) companies will asure that Cocoon will continue.</P> <P>So don't worry if you see these ego-fights and verbal attacks in the mailing list; this happens from time to time, but it has no real impact on the success of the project. It's like a big family - there is not always sunshine and from time to time some black sheep arrive and try to cause confusion and discredit. But after a time, the problems will be solved and the family can keep on living happily.</P></FONT></description> 
  <guid>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/03/31.html#a104</guid> 
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2003 13:33:39 GMT</pubDate> 
  </item>
 <item>
  <title>Once Upon a Time</title> 
  <link>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/03/21.html#a103</link> 
  <description><P>Today I had some time to think about the good old past: the first time I got in contact with Cocoon. So here are some facts:</P> <P>It's nearly three years ago.  I started in June 2000 by exploring the differences between Cocoon 1 - which was the current version of that time - and the pre-pre-pre alpha version of Cocoon 2.</P> <P>Although most features of Cocoon 2 were even not implemented, for example the sitemap did not compile well, actions were not defined, selectors were not implemented etc, it became clear that Cocoon 2 would be the way to go.</P> <P>And then a time with real fun started (and I really mean it the way I say). As we started in July 2000 with using the available Cocoon 2 version, we ran into several problems, bugs and missing features from day to day. And we tried to fix each issue and submit a patch to the community. Don't get me wrong, it's absolutely natural, that a project at that stage has bugs and problems. So we knew what lay ahead of us.</P> <P>Although this was a hard time, we believed the community of Cocoon that a first version of 2.0 would be available in November 2000 - now, we know that this was wrong :) The first version was indeed released in November, but in 2001.</P> <P>Then one day, the Cocoon community had enough of my patches ;) and voted me in as a committer! Wow! It became evident that some important parts were still missing, like caching, internal cocoon calls etc. As I already implemented such things for our product called sunShine, I added those things to Cocoon as well.</P> <P>The whole time between June 2000 and November 2001 was really fun, because we acted really like a community (or family if you want). When a problem was detected, you were never alone. Most time, the problem was fixed by working together. And also new things were always discussed by most committers and then implemented.</P> <P>This changed after the first release of Cocoon 2.0 in November 2001, because there were no real itches to scratch. Everything (well, at least the core) was working very well.</P> <P>So, looking back it was a real great time to be directly involved in the development of such a great open source project. </P> <P>Today, it's still fun to be part of the great Cocoon community but I'm really missing the collaboration between the different committers.<br/>From time to time two or three committers try to solve together a problem/add a feature but mostly this lasts only for this single issue.</P> <P>But it's <EM>still</EM> fun even if the weather is not too sunny at the moment.</P></description> 
  <guid>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/03/21.html#a103</guid> 
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2003 10:17:49 GMT</pubDate> 
  </item>
 <item>
  <title>Everything about Cocoon - JAX Speaker</title> 
  <link>http://www.jax2003.de</link> 
  <description><P>If you want to get to know something about Cocoon, well the <A href="http://www.jax2003.de/">JAX 2003</A> might be the right place for it. I will present two sessions about Cocoon (in German) and together with <A href="http://www.need-a-cake.com">Matthew</A> I will give a one day power workshop about Cocoon! And Matthew gives of course some sessions as well, so you have to be there.</P> <P>Apart from our presentations, the JAX will have several other very interesting talks as well. So make sure that you mark the date in your calendar.</P></description> 
  <guid>http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/2003/03/20.html#a102</guid> 
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2003 12:25:33 GMT</pubDate> 
  </item>
  </channel>
  </rss>