<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE todo SYSTEM "./xdocs/dtd/todo-v10.dtd">

<!--
  History of Cocoon changes
  $Id: todo.xml,v 1.6.2.32 2001-04-21 10:09:30 giacomo Exp $
-->


<todo title="Things To Do for Apache Cocoon 2">

 <devs>
  <!-- in strict alphabetical order -->
  <person name="Donald Ball" email="balld@apache.org" id="DB"/>
  <person name="Ross Burton" email="ross.burton@mail.com" id="RB"/>
  <person name="Paul Russell" email="prussell@apache.org" id="PR"/>
  <person name="Pierpaolo Fumagalli" email="pier@apache.org" id="PF"/>
  <person name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org" id="BL"/>
  <person name="Stefano Mazzocchi" email="stefano@apache.org" id="SM"/>
  <person name="Giacomo Pati" email="Giacomo.Pati@pwr.ch" id="GP"/>
  <person name="Ricardo Rocha" email="ricardo@apache.org" id="RR"/>
  <person name="Davanum Srinivas" email="dims@yahoo.com" id="DM"/>
  <person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org" id="CZ"/>
  <person name="Gerhard Fr&#246;hlich" email="g-froehlich@gmx.de" id="GF"/>
  <person name="Volunteer needed" email="giacomo@apache.org" id="open"/>
 </devs>

 <actions priority="high">
  <action context="code" assigned-to="open">
   Reloading of jar-files.
   The class-path for the Cocoon-Servlet is only build once when the servlet
   is initialised. If you want to deploy other jar files you have to restart
   the servlet. A reloading of the Cocoon is not sufficient. This is not
   very convenient. Suggestion: When Cocoon is reloaded (a new cocoon instance
   is created then) the classpath is rebuild and used.
  </action>

  <action context="code" assigned-to="DM">
   Make the evaluation/application of logicsheets in the XSP system reliable
   and usable without hassle to the logicsheet programmer
  </action>

  <action context="code" assigned-to="open">
   Complete (means put everything we know of into even if it has to be commented)
   the cocoon.xconf file and put descriptions into it
  </action>

  <action context="code" assigned-to="open">
   Complete (means put everything we know of into even if it has to be commented)
   the web.xml file and put descriptions into it (similar to the
   httpd.conf file of the web server or the server.xml of Catalina)
  </action>

  <action context="code" assigned-to="GP">
   Implement content aggregation at the sitemap level.
  </action>

  <action context="code" assigned-to="PR">
   Implement transparent content aggregation at the pipeline level.
  </action>

 </actions>

 <actions priority="medium">

  <action context="code" assigned-to="GF">
    Extend the Store to keep the most fequently used objects in the 
    memory portion available to the Store (defined by number of objects or 
    bytes) and all other objects on the file system. 
  </action>

  <action context="code">
   Check and fix xsl:import which doesn't seem to work expected... very strange..
   it might be an XSLT problem with the XSP example since it uses namespaces
   heavily... should we use the namespace() axis?
  </action>

  <action context="code">
   Remove deprecated methods from org.apache.cocoon.xml.util and make it clean
   for SAX2 final.
  </action>

  <action context="code">
   Finish writing the command line interface and design the link rewriting
   behavior that cannot work with views.
  </action>

  <action context="code">
   Create a form validation Action that uses an external configuration file
   to validate the form and make sure that values are within acceptable ranges.
   IIRC this has beed recently posted to the dev list.
  </action>

  <action context="code">
   Complete/write documentation in general
  </action>

  <action context="code">
   Implement an internal profiling tool that should indicate the load and history of
   such along with the status page. Something both useful and fancy to show the
   power of C2.
  </action>

 </actions>

</todo>
