<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 1999-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<n:news xmlns:n="http://www.betaversion.org/linotype/news/1.0" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:r="http://apache.org/cocoon/requestgenerator/2.0" online="on" author="" creation-date="May 26, 2003" creation-time="16:38" creation-fulldate="Mon, 26 May 2003 21:38:07 GMT"><n:title>Welcome to Linotype 1.1</n:title><body xmlns:h="http://apache.org/cocoon/requestgenerator/2.0"><p>Linotypes were machines that first allowed a single individual to mass-produce content without sacrificing typesetting elegance and text readability. Blogs turned the web into writeable media without sacrificing the ability to remain hypertextual. This is simply an attempt to combine the two concepts together.</p>

<p>Linotype uses the very bleeding edge of web technologies:</p>

<ul><li>It's powered by the <a href="http://cocoon.apache.org/">Apache Cocoon</a> framework and its amazing flowscript that, thanks to the power of continuation-enabled javascript, makes writing complex XML web applications a piece of cake.</li>
<li>It's based on <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/editor/midas-spec.html">Mozilla Midas</a>, the inline editor available from the 1.3 release.</li>
<li>The content is stored and edited as <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/">XHTML 1.0</a>.</li>
<li>All content is served as valid XHTML pages.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt">XSLT 1.0</a> is used only on the server side to perform tree transformations (such as wrapping the DHTML editor around the original XHTML content), but it's <strong xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">never</strong> used for styling.</li>
<li>Styling is performed entirely by <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-CSS2/">CSS2</a>.</li>
<li>Javascript 1.5 in used for Midas customizations and for client-side XHTML serialization when the edited content is transmitted back to the server.</li>
<li>The <a href="http://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI">URL space is kept clean</a>, designed to last and extension free. Extensions are used <strong xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">only</strong> when they are meant to imply a specific MIME-type.</li>
<li><a href="http://my.netscape.com/publish/formats/rss-spec-0.91.html">RSS</a> feeds are created automatically using Cocoon's aggregation capabilities and XSLT.</li>
<li>The editing capabilities are restricted to <q>semantic</q> XHTML: you can't change style, but only structure. Style will change accordingly, depending on the CSS2 parameters associated to the various markup elements or to their semantic class.</li>
<li>Image inclusion, resizing and uploading are all done inside the editor page without a need for external upload.</li>
<li>The stylesheets are designed for both text readability and elegance. The use of serif fonts is intentional because it increases text readability and gives a pleasant retro style that matches the linotype concept.</li>
<li>The entire thing has been designed around the <q>less is more</q> paradigm.</li>
<li>The code is licensed under the <a href="http://www.apache.org/foundation/licence-FAQ.html">Apache License 2.0</a> which doesn't force code contribution back to the project but does protect the name, thus the project recognition and its community.</li>
</ul>

<p>Enjoy and spread the word.</p>

<p><strong>Stefano Mazzocchi.</strong></p>
</body></n:news>
