<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Configuring Coplets</title>
  <subtitle>Overview</subtitle>
  <authors>
   <person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>
  <s1 title="Overview">
   <p>This document gives an overview over configuring coplets.
     The sample portal that comes with the Cocoon distribution contains several
     samples.
   </p>
   <p>
    The configuration of a coplet is done in several steps that are outlined
    in the next chapters. We use the provided sample as a base. This sample
    stores all profiles in XML documents that are all stored in the
    samples/portal directory. So all file and directory names are relative
    to this directory. It's not required that you store the configuration
    in XML files, you can also store them in a database, an LDAP system etc.
    This is also configurable and customizable.
   </p>
  </s1>
  <s1 title="Configuring Coplets">
   <p>
    Configuring coplets is like defining a class and creating their instances.
    So in fact, you define the available coplets (= classes) and each portal
    view gets some instances of these coplets. 
   </p>
   <p>
    In addition to the classes and the instances, we have coplet types which can
    be seen as a classification of the coplet classes. There are different coplet
    types, uri based coplets, JSR-168 coplets, application coplets etc. The coplet
    type defines, how the coplet works or how the coplet gets it's content. For 
    example, the uri based coplet triggers a uri to get the coplet - this can be
    an http request or an internal cocoon pipeline request.
   </p>
   <p>
    Another exsample is the JSR-168 coplet type. This type allows to use JSR-168
    compliant portlets for fetching the content. So let's start with the coplet
    types:
   </p>
   <s2 title="Available Coplet Types">
    <p>
     Before you can define your available coplets, you have to define the
     available coplet types, or the so called coplet base data. The current
     exsample contains an XML document for this (the file is in the
     profiles/copletbasedata directory and is called portlal.xml). This is
     an excerpt from the file:
   </p>
          <source>
<![CDATA[...
<coplets>
   <coplet-base-data id="URICoplet">
      <coplet-adapter>uri</coplet-adapter>
   </coplet-base-data>
</coplets>
...]]>
          </source>
   <p>
    In the example above, we define one coplet type, the <em>URICoplet</em>,
    that uses the <em>uri coplet adapter</em>. By this we define a type,
    that uses URIs to get the content of a coplet. A uri can either be
    targetted at a different server (using http, ftp etc.) or it can
    be an internal cocoon pipeline (using cocoon:).
   </p>
   <p>
    You can add different coplet types with additional configuration here,
    but rarely have to touch this file as most is preconfigured already.
   </p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="Available Coplets">
   <p>
    Based on the coplet types, you can define the available coplets in your
    portal application (= classes). In the example portal an own configuration
    file contains these so called coplet datas (it's in the profiles/copletdata
    directory and has the filename portal.xml). Here is an excerpt:
   </p>
   <source>
<![CDATA[...
<coplets>
   <coplet-data id="CZ Weblog" name="standard">
      <title>CZ's Weblog</title>
      <coplet-base-data>URICoplet</coplet-base-data>
      <attribute>
      	<name>uri</name>
      	<value xsi:type="java:java.lang.String" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">cocoon:/news/liverss?feed=http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/rss.xml</value>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
      	<name>buffer</name>
      	<value xsi:type="java:java.lang.Boolean" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">true</value>
      </attribute>
      <attribute>
      	<name>error-uri</name>
      	<value xsi:type="java:java.lang.String" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">cocoon:/news/CZ_weblog.rss</value>
      </attribute>
   </coplet-data>
</coplets>
...]]>
   </source>
   <p>
    Each coplet data contains a unique id and additional configuration. A required
    configuration is the underlying coplet base data. In the example above,
    the <em>URICoplet</em> is used that we have configured in the previous chapter.
   </p>
   <p>
    The above configured coplet data requires some configuration. This configuration
    depends on the coplet type. In this case we use the URICoplet and this needs
    of course the URI to fetch the content from for this coplet. This configuration is
    passed in the different attributes you see above. Each attribute has a name and value.
   </p>
   <p>
    The set of coplet datas defines the set of available coplets a user can
    choose from. If a user chooses to view a coplet, an instance of this coplet
    data is created. If, e.g. the user chooses the same coplet twice,
    two instances are created. This is useful for configurable coplets where
    the user can choose the same coplet with different configurations.
   </p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="Selected Coplets">
   <p>
    The selected coplets are described by the set of coplet instance datas This is
    again another XML document (that is stored in profiles/copletinstancedata and
    has the name portal.xml). Here is an excerpt:
   </p>
   <source>
<![CDATA[...
<coplets>
   <coplet-instance-data id="CZ Weblog-1" name="standard">
      <coplet-data>CZ Weblog</coplet-data>
   </coplet-instance-data>
</coplets>
...]]>
   </source>
   <p>
     The coplet instance data refers to its coplet data (the class) by specifying the
     unique ID. The instance itself has a unique ID as well that is referenced
     from the portal view. This id of the instance has only the be unique within
     the scope of a user. Different users can have different instances with the
     same id.
   </p>
   <p>
     In addition, a coplet instance data could have own configuration information.
     This configuration depends on the coplet type and on the coplet (class).
   </p>
  </s2>
 </s1>
 <s1 title="Common Coplet Configuration">
  <p>
   As outlined above, a coplet can be configured at various places. In general,
   configuration values are most often configured at the coplet type (coplet
   base data) and may be overwritten by the coplet class (coplet data).
  </p>
  <p>
   The coplet base data takes the information as config entries whereas 
   the coplet data uses attributes. Apart from that the keys and 
   the data types are the same. Let's have a look at an example:
  </p>
   <source>
<![CDATA[...
   <coplet-base-data id="URICoplet">
      <coplet-adapter>uri</coplet-adapter>
      <configuration>
      	<name>buffer</name>
      	<value xsi:type="java:java.lang.Boolean" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">true</value>
      </configuration>
   </coplet-base-data>
   ...
   <coplet-data id="CZ Weblog" name="standard">
      <title>CZ's Weblog</title>
      <coplet-base-data>URICoplet</coplet-base-data>
      <attribute>
      	<name>buffer</name>
      	<value xsi:type="java:java.lang.Boolean" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">false</value>
      </attribute>
   </coplet-data>
...]]>
   </source>
   <p>
    As you can see in the exsample above, there is no real difference in configuring
    a coplet type (base data) and a coplet class (coplet data) apart that the first
    one uses the element name <em>configuration</em> and the last one uses 
    <em>attribute</em>.
   </p>
  <s2 title="Output Buffering">
   <p>
    Each coplet can be configured with the boolean value <em>buffer</em>
    (default is false) that defines if the xml data stream from the coplet 
    is buffered before it is streamed in the main portal pipeline. 
   </p>
   <p>
    If the stream is not buffered and an exception occurs during the
    streaming of the one coplet, then the whole portal might be rendered invalid.
    Therefore you should turn on buffering whenever you can't guarantee
    that the output of a coplet is always valid XML.
   </p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="Delivery Timeout">
   <p>
    Usually the portal waits forever(!) for a coplet to deliver it's content.
    If you want to fine-tune this behaviour, you can configure a <em>timeout</em>
    value. This integer value (default is endless) defines the
    maximum time (in seconds) the coplet has to deliver it's content.
   </p>
   <p>
    If the timeout is reached the content is assumed as not
    gettable. If you set a timeout, the content is automatically
    buffered and the <em>buffer</em> configuration is ignored.
   </p>
  </s2>
 </s1>
 <s1 title="The URICoplet">
  <p>
   This section describes the URICoplet and the different possibilities to
   configure it. For general configuration see the previous chapter.
  </p>
  <s2 title="The Content Location and Parameter Handling">
   <p>
    A URICoplet uses a uri to fetch the coplet. This configuration is obviously
    a configuration of the coplet class (and not of the coplet type) as each
    coplet uses a different location.
   </p>
   <p>
    The attribute <em>uri</em> takes the complete uri (as a string) to fetch the
    content from:
   </p>
   <source>
<![CDATA[...
   <coplet-data id="CZ Weblog" name="standard">
      <title>CZ's Weblog</title>
      <coplet-base-data>URICoplet</coplet-base-data>
      <attribute>
      	<name>uri</name>
      	<value xsi:type="java:java.lang.String" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
      	  cocoon:/news/liverss?feed=http://radio.weblogs.com/0107211/rss.xml
      	</value>
      </attribute>
   </coplet-data>
...]]>
   </source>
   <p>
    If you're using the cocoon protocol to call internal pipelines, you can also
    configure the boolean attribute <em>handleParameters</em> (default is false),
    that defines if the coplet handles request parameters itself. This should
    be used for coplets that process request parameters (have forms for example).
    In that case, the parameters from the request are only forwarded to the
    coplet, if they are meant for this coplet. All other coplets that use
    request parameters don't get them in this request-response-cycle.
   </p>
  </s2>
  <s2 title="Error Handling">
   <p>
    Usually, in the case of an error during rendering the content of a coplet,
    a message is included in the coplet window instead of the coplet content.
    If you want to customize this, you can specifiy the attribute <em>error-uri</em>
    that should contain a valid uri that deliveres the content for a better
    error message.
   </p>
  </s2>
 </s1>
 <s1 title="Coplet Rendering">
  <p>
   Each coplet can be configured for supporting different features, like minimizing
   or removing. These are aspect configurations that are configured similar to 
   attributes.
  </p>
  <s2 title="Sizing">
   <p>
    By default, the window size of a coplet can be changed by the user.
    The user can choose between maximized and minimized.
   </p>
   <p>
    This is configurable by the boolean aspect <em>sizable</em> on
    the coplet data (class). The default is true:
   </p>
   <source>
<![CDATA[...
   <coplet-data id="CZ Weblog" name="standard">
      <title>CZ's Weblog</title>
      <coplet-base-data>URICoplet</coplet-base-data>
      <aspect>
      	<name>sizable</name>
      	<value xsi:type="java:java.lang.Boolean" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
      	  false
      	</value>
      </aspect>
   </coplet-data>
...]]>
   </source>
   <p>
    In addition the size of a coplet (minimized/maximized) can be preconfigured
    as well by the integer aspect value <em>size</em>. The value <em>0</em>
    means minimized and <em>1</em> is maximized (with 1 as the default).
   </p>
   <source>
<![CDATA[...
   <coplet-data id="CZ Weblog" name="standard">
      <title>CZ's Weblog</title>
      <coplet-base-data>URICoplet</coplet-base-data>
      <aspect>
      	<name>size</name>
      	<value xsi:type="java:java.lang.Integer" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
      	  0
      	</value>
      </aspect>
   </coplet-data>
...]]>
   </source>
 </s2>
  <s2 title="Mandatory Coplets">
   <p>
    By default, the user can delete any coplet from his portal view. However
    important coplets can be configured as <em>mandatory</em>. In this case,
    the remove icon is not displayed, and the coplet can never be removed 
    by the user.
   </p>
   <p>
    This is configurable by the boolean aspect <em>mandatory</em> on
    the coplet data (class). The default is false:
   </p>
   <source>
<![CDATA[...
   <coplet-data id="CZ Weblog" name="standard">
      <title>CZ's Weblog</title>
      <coplet-base-data>URICoplet</coplet-base-data>
      <aspect>
      	<name>mandatory</name>
      	<value xsi:type="java:java.lang.Boolean" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
      	  true
      	</value>
      </aspect>
   </coplet-data>
...]]>
   </source>
  </s2>
 </s1>
</body>
</document>
